				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				Safety, Fulness, and Sweet Refreshment in Christ
				
				    Isaiah 32:2 -- And a man shall be as an hiding-place from the wind, and a
				    covert from the tempest; as rivers of water in a dry place, as the shadow of
				    a great rock in a weary land.
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				   In these words we may observe,
				
				   1. The person who is here prophesied of and commended, viz. the Lord
				   Jesus Christ, the King spoken of in the preceding verse, who shall
				   reign in righteousness. This King is abundantly prophesied of in the
				   Old Testament, and especially in this prophecy of Isaiah. Glorious
				   predictions were from time to time uttered by the prophets concerning
				   that great King who was to come: there is no subject which is spoken of
				   in so magnificent and exalted a style by the prophets of the Old
				   Testament, as the Messiah. They saw his day and rejoiced, and searched
				   diligently, together with the angels, into those things. I Peter 1:11,
				   12. "Searching what, or what manner of time, the Spirit of Christ which
				   was in them did signify, when it testified beforehand the sufferings of
				   Christ, and the glory that should follow. Unto whom it was revealed,
				   that not unto themselves, but unto us, they did minister the things,
				   which are now reported unto you by them that have preached the gospel
				   unto you with the Holy Ghost sent down from heaven; which things the
				   angels desire to look into."
				
				   We are told here that "a man shall be a hiding-place from the wind,"
				   &c. There is an emphasis in the words, that "a man" should be this. If
				   these things had been said of God, it would not be strange under the
				   Old Testament; for God is frequently called a hiding-place for his
				   people, a refuge in time of trouble, a strong rock, and a high tower.
				   But what is so remarkable is, that they are said of "a man." But this
				   is a prophecy of the Son of God incarnate.
				
				   2. The things here foretold of him, and the commendations given him.
				   "He shall be a hiding-place from the wind, and a covert from the
				   tempest:" that is, he shall be the safety and defence of his people, to
				   which they shall flee for protection in the time of their danger and
				   trouble. To him they shall flee, as one who is abroad, and sees a
				   terrible storm arising, makes haste to some shelter to secure himself;
				   so that however furious is the tempest, yet he is safe within, and the
				   wind and rain, though they beat never so impetuously upon the roof and
				   walls, are no annoyance unto him.
				
				   He shall be as "rivers of water in a dry place." This is an allusion to
				   the deserts of Arabia, which was an exceedingly hot and dry country.
				   One may travel there many days, and see no sign of a river, brook, or
				   spring, nothing but a dry and parched wilderness; so that travelers are
				   ready to be consumed with thirst, as the children of Israel were when
				   they were in this wilderness, when they were faint because there was no
				   water. Now when a man finds Jesus Christ, he is like one that has been
				   traveling in those deserts till he is almost consumed with thirst, and
				   who as last finds a river of cool and clear water. And Christ was
				   typified by the river of water that issued out of the rock for the
				   children of Israel in this desert: he is compared to a river, because
				   there is such a plenty and fulness in him.
				
				   He is the "shadow of a great rock in a weary land." Allusion is still
				   made to the desert of Arabia. It is not said, as the shadow of a tree,
				   because in some places of that country, there is nothing but dry sand
				   and rocks for a vast space together, not a tree to be seen; and the sun
				   beats exceedingly hot upon the sands, and all the shade to be found
				   there, where travellers can rest and shelter themselves from the
				   scorching sun, is under some great rock. They who come to Christ find
				   such rest and refreshment as the weary traveller in that hot and
				   desolate country finds under the shadow of a great rock.
				
				   We propose to speak to three propositions that are explicatory of the
				   several parts of the text.
				
				   I. There is in Christ Jesus abundant foundation of peace and safety for
				   those who are in fear and danger. "A man shall be a hiding-place from
				   the wind, a covert from the tempest."
				
				   II. There is in Christ provision for the satisfaction, and full
				   contentment, of the needy and thirsty soul. He shall be "as rivers of
				   water in a dry place."
				
				   III. There are quiet rest and sweet refreshment in Christ Jesus for him
				   who is weary. He shall be "as the shadow of a great rock in a weary
				   land."
				
				   I. There is in Christ Jesus abundant foundation of peace and safety for
				   those who are in fear and danger.
				
				   The fears and dangers to which men are subject, are of two kinds;
				   temporal and eternal. Men are frequently in distress from fear of
				   temporal evils. We live in an evil world, where we are liable to an
				   abundance of sorrows and calamities. A great part of our lives is spent
				   in sorrowing for present or past evils, and in fearing those which are
				   future. What poor, distressed creatures are we, when God is pleased to
				   send his judgements among us! If he visits a place with mortal and
				   prevailing sickness, what terror seizes our hearts! If any person is
				   taken sick, and trembles for his life, or if our near friends are at
				   the point of death, or in many other dangers, how fearful is our
				   condition! Now there is sufficient foundation for peace and safety to
				   those exercised with such fears, and brought into such dangers. But
				   Christ is a refuge in all trouble; there is a foundation for rational
				   support and peace in him, whatever threatens us. He, whose heart is
				   fixed, trusting in Christ, need not be afraid of any evil tidings. "As
				   the mountains are round about Jerusalem, so Christ is round about them
				   that fear him."
				
				   But it is the other kind of fear and danger to which we have a
				   principal respect; the fear and danger of God's wrath. The fears of a
				   terrified conscience, the fearful expectation of the dire fruits of
				   sin, and the resentment of an angry God, these are infinitely the most
				   dreadful. If men are in danger of those things, and are not asleep,
				   they will be more terrified than with the fears of any outward evil.
				   Men are in a most deplorable condition, as they are by nature exposed
				   to God's wrath; and if they are sensible how dismal their case is, will
				   be in dreadful fears and dismal expectations.
				
				   God is pleased to make some sensible of their true condition. He lets
				   them see the storm that threatens them, how black the clouds are, and
				   how impregnated with thunder, that it is a burning tempest, that they
				   are in danger of being speedily overtaken by it, that they have nothing
				   to shelter themselves from it, and that they are in danger of being
				   taken away by the fierceness of his anger.
				
				   It is a fearful condition when one is smitten with a sense of the
				   dreadfulness of God's wrath, when he has his heart impressed with the
				   conviction that the great God is not reconciled to him, that he holds
				   him guilty of these and those sins, and that he is angry enough with
				   him to condemn him for ever. It is dreadful to lie down and rise up, it
				   is dreadful to eat and drink, and to walk about, in God's anger from
				   day to day. One, in such a case, is ready to be afraid of every thing;
				   he is afraid of meeting God's wrath wherever he goes. He has no peace
				   in his mind, but there is a dreadful sound in his ears; his mind is
				   afflicted and tossed with tempest, and not comforted, and courage is
				   ready to fail, and the spirit ready to sink with fear; for how can a
				   poor worm bear the wrath of the great God, and what would not he give
				   for peace of conscience, what would not he give if he could find
				   safety! When such fears exist to a great degree, or are continued a
				   long time, they greatly enfeeble the heart, and bring it to a trembling
				   posture and disposition.
				
				   Now for such as these there is abundant foundation for peace and safety
				   in Jesus Christ, and this will appear from the following things:
				
				   1. Christ has undertaken to save all such from what they fear, if they
				   come to him. It is his professional business; the work in which he
				   engaged before the foundation of the world. It is what he always had in
				   his thoughts and intentions; he undertook from everlasting to be the
				   refuge of those that are afraid of God's wrath. His wisdom is such,
				   that he would never undertake a work for which he is not sufficient. If
				   there were some in so dreadful a case that he was not able to defend
				   them, or so guilty that it was not fit that he should save them, then
				   he never would have undertaken for them. Those who are in trouble and
				   distressing fear, if they come to Jesus Christ, have this to ease them
				   of their fears, that Christ has promised them that he will protect
				   them; that they come upon his invitation; that Christ has plighted his
				   faith for their security if they will close with him; and that he is
				   engaged by covenant to God the Father that he will save those afflicted
				   and distressed souls that come to him.
				
				   Christ, by his own free act, has made himself the surety of such, he
				   has voluntarily put himself in their stead; and if justice has any
				   thing against them, he has undertaken to answer for them. By his own
				   act, he has engaged to be responsible for them; so that if they have
				   exposed themselves to God's wrath, and to the stroke of justice, it is
				   not their concern, but his, how to answer or satisfy for what they have
				   done. Let there be never so much wrath that they have deserved, they
				   are as safe as if they never had deserved any; because he has
				   undertaken to stand for them, let it be more or less. If they are in
				   Christ Jesus, the storm does of course light on him, and not on them;
				   as when we are under a good shelter, the storm, that would otherwise
				   come upon our heads, lights upon the shelter.
				
				   2. He is chosen and appointed of the Father to this work. There needs
				   to be no fear nor jealousy, whether the Father will approve of this
				   undertaking of Christ Jesus, whether he will accept of him as a surety,
				   or whether he will be willing that his wrath should be poured upon his
				   own dear Son, instead of us miserable sinners. For there was an
				   agreement with him concerning it before the world was; it was a thing
				   much upon God's heart, that his Son Jesus Christ should undertake this
				   work, and it was the Father that sent him into the world. It is as much
				   the act of God the Father as it is of the Son. Therefore, when Christ
				   was near the time of his death, he tells the Father that he had
				   finished the work which he gave him to do. Christ is often called God's
				   elect, or his chosen, because he was chosen by the Father for his work;
				   and God's anointed, for the words Messiah and Christ signify anointed,
				   because he is by God appointed and fitted for this work.
				
				   3. If we are in Christ Jesus, justice and the law have its course with
				   respect to our sins, without our hurt. The foundation of the sinner's
				   fear and distress is the justice and the law of God; they are against
				   him, and they are unalterable, they must have their course. Every jot
				   and tittle of the law must be fulfilled, heaven and earth shall be
				   destroyed, rather than justice should not take place; there is no
				   possibility of sin's escaping justice.
				
				   But yet if the distressed trembling soul who is afraid of justice,
				   would fly to Christ, he would be a safe hiding-place. Justice and the
				   threatening of the law will have their course as fully, while he is
				   safe and untouched, as if he were to be eternally destroyed. Christ
				   bears the stroke of justice, and the curse of the law falls fully upon
				   him; Christ bears all that vengeance that belongs to the sin that has
				   been committed by him, and there is no need of its being borne twice
				   over. His temporal sufferings, by reason of the infinite dignity of his
				   person, are fully equivalent to the eternal sufferings of a mere
				   creature. And then his sufferings answer for him who flees to him as
				   well as if they were his own, for indeed they are his own by virtue of
				   the union between Christ and him. Christ has made himself one with
				   them; he is the head, and they are the members. Therefore, if Christ
				   suffers for the believer, there is no need of his suffering; and what
				   needs he to be afraid? His safety is not only consistent with absolute
				   justice, but it is consistent with the tenor of the law. The law leaves
				   fair room for such a thing as the answering of a surety. If the end of
				   punishment in maintaining the authority of the law and the majesty of
				   the government is fully secured by the sufferings of Christ as his
				   surety, then the law of God, according to the true and fair
				   interpretation of it, has its course as much in the sufferings of
				   Christ, as it would have in his own sufferings. The threatening, "thou
				   shalt surely die," is properly fulfilled in the death of Christ, as it
				   is fairly to be understood. Therefore if those who are afraid will go
				   to Jesus Christ, they need to fear nothing from the threatening of the
				   law. The threatening of the law has nothing to do with them.
				
				   4. Those who come to Christ, need not be afraid of God's wrath for
				   their sins; for God's honour will not suffer by their escaping
				   punishment and being made happy. The wounded soul is sensible that he
				   has affronted the majesty of God, and looks upon God as a vindicator of
				   his honour; as a jealous God that will not be mocked, an infinitely
				   great God that will not bear to be affronted, that will not suffer his
				   authority and majesty to be trampled on, that will not bear that his
				   kindness should be abused. A view of God in this light terrifies
				   awakened souls. They think how exceedingly they have sinned, how they
				   have sinned against light, against frequent and long-continued calls
				   and warnings; and how they have slighted mercy, and been guilty of
				   turning the grace of God into lasciviousness, taking encouragement from
				   God's mercy to go on in sin against him; and they fear that God is so
				   affronted at the contempt and slight which they have cast upon him,
				   that he, being careful of his honour, will never forgive them, but will
				   punish them. But if they go to Christ, the honour of God's majesty and
				   authority will not be in the least hurt by their being freed and made
				   happy. For what Christ has done has repaired God's honour to the full.
				   It is a greater honour to God's authority and majesty, that, rather
				   than it should be wronged, so glorious a person would suffer what the
				   law required. It is surely a wonderful display of the honour of God's
				   majesty, to see an infinite and eternal person dying for its being
				   wronged. And then Christ by his obedience, by that obedience which he
				   undertook for our sakes, has honoured God abundantly more than the sins
				   of any of us have dishonoured him, how many soever, and how great
				   soever. How great an honour is it to God's law that so great a person
				   is willing to submit to it, and to obey it! God hates our sins, but not
				   more than he delights in Christ's obedience which he performed on
				   account. This is a sweet savour to him, a savour of rest. God is
				   abundantly compensated, he desires no more; Christ's righteousness is
				   of infinite worthiness and merit.
				
				   5. Christ is a person so dear to the Father, that those who are in
				   Christ need not be at all jealous of being accepted upon his account.
				   If Christ is accepted they must of consequence be accepted, for they
				   are in Christ, as members, as parts, as the same. They are the body of
				   Christ, his flesh and his bones. They that are in Christ Jesus, are one
				   spirit; and therefore, if God loves Christ Jesus, he must of necessity
				   accept of those that are in him, and that are of him. But Christ is a
				   person exceedingly dear to the Father, the Father's love to the Son is
				   really infinite. God necessarily loves the Son; God could as soon cease
				   to be, as cease to love the Son. He is God's elect, in whom his soul
				   delighteth; he is his beloved Son, in whom he is well pleased; he loved
				   him before the foundation of the world, and had infinite delight in him
				   from all eternity.
				
				   A terrified conscience, therefore, may have rest here, and abundant
				   satisfaction that he is safe in Christ, and that there is not the least
				   danger but that he shall be accepted, and that God will be at peace
				   with him in Christ.
				
				   6. God has given an open testimony that Christ has done and suffered
				   enough, and that he is satisfied with it, by his raising him from the
				   dead. Christ, when he was in his passion, was in the hands of justice,
				   he was God's prisoner for believers, and it pleased God to bruise him,
				   and put him to grief, and to bring him into a low state; and when he
				   raised him from the dead, he set him at liberty, whereby he declared
				   that it was enough. If God was not satisfied, why did he set Christ at
				   liberty so soon? he was in the hands of justice, why did not God pour
				   out more wrath upon him, and hold him in the chains of darkness longer?
				   God raised him up and opened the prison doors to him, because he
				   desired no more. And now surely there is free admittance for all
				   sinners into God's favour through this risen Saviour, there is enough
				   done, and God is satisfied; as he has declared and sealed to it by the
				   resurrection of Christ, who is alive, and lives for evermore, and is
				   making intercession for poor, distressed souls that come unto him.
				
				   7. Christ has the dispensation of safety and deliverance in his own
				   hands, so that we need not fear but that, if we are united to him, we
				   may be safe. God has given him all power in heaven and in earth, to
				   give eternal life to whomsoever comes to him. He is made head over all
				   things to the church, and the work of salvation is left with himself,
				   he may save whom he pleases, and defend those that are in him by his
				   own power. What greater ground of confidence could God have given us
				   than that the Mediator, who died for us, and intercedes for us, should
				   have committed to him the dispensation of the very thing which he died
				   to purchase and for which he intercedes?
				
				   8. Christ's love, and compassion, and gracious disposition, are such
				   that we may be sure he is inclined to receive all who come to him. If
				   he should not do it, he would fail of his own undertaking, and also of
				   his promise to the Father, and to us; and his wisdom and faithfulness
				   will not allow of that. But he is so full of love and kindness that he
				   is disposed to nothing but to receive and defend us, if we come to him.
				   Christ is exceedingly ready to pity us, his arms are open to receive
				   us, he delights to receive distressed souls that come to him, and to
				   protect them; he would gather them as a hen gathereth her chickens
				   under her wings; it is a work that he exceedingly rejoices in, because
				   he delights in acts of love, and pity, and mercy.
				
				   I shall take occasion from what now has been said, to invite those who
				   are afraid of God's wrath, to come to Christ Jesus. You are indeed in a
				   dreadful condition. It is dismal to have God's wrath impending over our
				   heads, and not to know how soon it will fall upon us. And you are in
				   some measure sensible that it is a dreadful condition, you are full of
				   fear and trouble, and you know not where to flee for help; your mind
				   is, as it were, tossed with a tempest. But how lamentable is it, that
				   you should spend your life in such a condition, when Christ would
				   shelter you, as a hen shelters her chickens under her wings, if you
				   were but willing; and that you should live such a fearful, distressed
				   life, when there is so much provision made for your safety in Christ
				   Jesus!
				
				   How happy would you be if your hearts were but persuaded to close with
				   Jesus Christ! Then you would be out of all danger: whatever storms and
				   tempests were without, you might rest securely within; you might hear
				   the rushing of the wind, and the thunder roar abroad, while you are
				   safe in this hiding-place. O be persuaded to hide yourself in Christ
				   Jesus! What greater assurance of safety can you desire? He has
				   undertaken to defend and save you, if you will come to him: he looks
				   upon it as his work; he engaged in it before the world was, and he has
				   given his faithful promise which he will not break; and if you will but
				   make your flight there, his life shall be for yours; he will answer for
				   you, you shall have nothing to do but rest quietly in him; you may
				   stand still and see what the Lord will do for you. If there be any
				   thing to suffer, the suffering is Christ's, you will have nothing to
				   suffer; if there be any thing to be done, the doing of it is Christ's,
				   you will have nothing to do but to stand still and behold it.
				
				   You will certainly be accepted of the Father if your soul lays hold of
				   Jesus Christ. Christ is chosen and anointed of the Father, and sent
				   forth for this very end, to save those that are in danger and fear; and
				   he is greatly beloved of God, even infinitely, and he will accept of
				   those that are in him. Justice and the law will not be against you, if
				   you are in Christ; that threatening, "in the day that thou eatest thou
				   shalt die," in the proper sense of it, will not touch you. The majesty
				   and honour of God are not against you. You need not be afraid but that
				   you shall be justified, if you come to him; there is an act of
				   justification already past and declared for all who come to Christ by
				   the resurrection of Christ, and as soon as ever you come, you are by
				   that declared free. If you come to Christ it will be a sure sign that
				   Christ loved you from all eternity, and that he died for you; and you
				   may be sure if he died for you, he will not lose the end of his death,
				   for the dispensation of life is committed unto him.
				
				   You need not, therefore, continue in so dangerous a condition; there is
				   help for you. You need not stand out in the storm so long, as there is
				   so good a shelter near you, whose doors are open to receive you. O make
				   haste, therefore, unto that man who is a hiding-place from the wind,
				   and a covert from the tempest!
				
				   Let this truth also cause believers more to prize the Lord Jesus
				   Christ. Consider that it is he, and he only, who defends you from
				   wrath, and that he is a safe defence; your defence is a high tower;
				   your city of refuge is impregnable. There is no rock like your rock.
				   There is none like Christ, "the God of Jeshurun, who rideth upon the
				   heaven in thy help, and in his excellency on the sky; the eternal God
				   is thy refuge, and underneath are everlasting arms." He in whom you
				   trust is a buckler to all that trust in him. O prize that Saviour, who
				   keeps your soul in safety, while thousands of others are carried away
				   by the fury of God's anger, and are tossed with raging and burning
				   tempests in hell! O, how much better is your case than theirs! and to
				   whom is it owing but to the Lord Jesus Christ? Remember what was once
				   your case, and what it is now, and prize Jesus Christ.
				
				   And let those christians who are in doubts and fears concerning their
				   condition, renewedly fly to Jesus Christ, who is a hiding-place from
				   the wind, and a covert from the tempest. Most Christians are at times
				   afraid whether they shall not miscarry at last. Such doubtings are
				   always through some want of the exercise of faith, and the best remedy
				   for them is a renewed resort of the soul to this hiding-place; the same
				   act which at first gave comfort and peace, will give peace again. They
				   that clearly see the sufficiency of Christ, and the safety of
				   committing themselves to him to save them from what they fear, will
				   rest in it that Christ will defend them; be directed therefore at such
				   times to do as the psalmist. Psalm 56:3, 4. "What time I am afraid, I
				   will trust in thee. In God I will praise his word; in God I have put my
				   trust: I will not fear what flesh can do unto me."
				
				   II. There is provision in Christ for the satisfaction and full
				   contentment of the needy and thirsty soul.
				
				   This is the sense of those words in the text, "as rivers of water in a
				   dry place," in a dry and parched wilderness, where there is a great
				   want of water, and where travellers are ready to be destroyed with
				   thirst, such as was that wilderness in which the children of Israel
				   wandered. This comparison is used elsewhere in the Scriptures. Psalm
				   63:1. "O God, thou art my God; early will I seek thee: my soul
				   thirsteth for thee, my flesh longeth for thee in a dry and thirsty
				   land, where no water is." Psalm 143:6. "I stretch forth my hands unto
				   thee; my soul thirsteth after thee, as a thirsty land." Those who
				   travel in such a land, who wander in such a wilderness, are in extreme
				   need of water; they are ready to perish for the want of it; and thus
				   they have a great thirst and longing for it.
				
				   It is said that Christ is a river of water, because there is such a
				   fulness in him, so plentiful a provision for the satisfaction of the
				   needy and longing soul. When one is extremely thirsty, though it is not
				   a small draught of water will satisfy him, yet when he comes to a
				   river, he finds a fulness, there he may drink full draughts. Christ is
				   like a river, in that he has a sufficiency not only for one thirsty
				   soul, but by supplying him the fountain is not lessened; there is not
				   the less afforded to those who come afterwards. A thirsty man does not
				   sensibly lessen a river by quenching his thirst.
				   Christ is like a river in another respect. A river is continually
				   flowing, there are fresh supplies of water coming from the
				   fountain-head continually, so that a man may live by it, and be
				   supplied with water all his life. So Christ is an ever-flowing
				   fountain; he is continually supplying his people, and the fountain is
				   not spent. They who live upon Christ, may have fresh supplies from him
				   to all eternity; they may have an increase of blessedness that is new,
				   and new still, and which never will come to an end.
				
				   In illustrating this second proposition, I shall inquire,
				
				   1. What it is that the soul of every man naturally and necessarily
				   craves.
				
				   First. The soul of every man necessarily craves happiness. This is an
				   universal appetite of human nature, that is alike in the good and the
				   bad; it is as universal as the very essence of the soul, because it
				   necessarily and immediately flows from that essence. It is not only
				   natural to all mankind, but to the angels; it is universal among all
				   reasonable, intelligent beings, in heaven, earth, or hell, because it
				   flows necessarily from an intelligent nature. There is no rational
				   being, nor can there be any, without a love and desire of happiness. It
				   is impossible that there should be any creature made that should love
				   misery, or not love happiness, since it implies a manifest
				   contradiction; for the very notion of misery is to be in a state that
				   nature abhors, and the notion of happiness, is to be in such a state as
				   is most agreeable to nature.
				
				   Therefore, this craving of happiness must be insuperable, and what
				   never can be changed; it never can be overcome, or in any way abated.
				   Young and old love happiness alike, and good and bad, wise and unwise;
				   though there is a great variety as to men's ideas of happiness. Some
				   think it is to be found in one thing, and some in another; yet, as to
				   the desire of happiness in general, there is no variety. There are
				   particular appetites that may be restrained, and kept under, and
				   conquered, but this general appetite for happiness nev-er can be.
				
				   Secondly. The soul of every man craves a happiness that is equal to the
				   capacity of his nature. The soul of man is like a vessel; the capacity
				   of the soul is as the largeness or contents of the vessel. And
				   therefore, if man has much pleasure and happiness, yet if the vessel is
				   not full, the craving will not cease. Every creature is restless till
				   it enjoys what is equal to the capacity of its nature. Thus we may
				   observe in the brutes; when they have that which is suitable to their
				   nature, and proportional to their capacity, they are contented. Man is
				   of such a nature, that he is capable of an exceedingly great degree of
				   happiness; he is made of a vastly higher nature than the brutes, and
				   therefore he must have vastly higher happiness to satisfy. The
				   pleasures of the outward senses which content the beasts, will not
				   content man. He has other faculties of a higher nature that stand in
				   need of something to fill them; if the sense be satiated, yet if the
				   faculties of the soul are not filled, man will be in a craving restless
				   state.
				
				   It is more especially by reason of the faculty of understanding that
				   the soul is capable of so great a happiness, and desires so much. The
				   understanding is an exceedingly extensive faculty; it extends itself
				   beyond the limits of earth, beyond the limits of the creation. As we
				   are capable of understanding immensely more than we do understand, who
				   can tell how far the understanding of men is capable of stretching
				   itself? and as the understanding enlarges, the desire will enlarge with
				   it. It must therefore be an incomprehensible object that must satisfy
				   the soul; it will never be contented with that, and that only, to which
				   it can see an end, it will never be satisfied with that happiness to
				   which it can find a bottom. A man may seem to take contentment for a
				   little while in a finite object, but after he has had a little
				   experience, he finds that he wants something besides. This is very
				   apparent from the experience of this restless craving world. Every one
				   is inquiring, Who will show us any good?
				
				   2. Men in their fallen state, are in very great want of this happiness.
				   They were once in the enjoyment of it, but mankind are sunk to a very
				   low estate; we are naturally poor, destitute creatures. We came naked
				   into the world, and our souls as well as our bodies are in a wretched,
				   miserable condition; we are so far from having food to eat suitable to
				   our nature, that we are greedy after the husks which the swine do eat.
				
				   The poverty of man in a natural condition, appears in his discontented,
				   craving spirit; it shows that the soul is very empty, when, like the
				   horse-leech, it cries, "Give, give, and saith not, It is enough." We
				   are naturally like the prodigal, for we once were rich, but we departed
				   from our father's house, and have squandered away our wealth, and are
				   become poor, hungry, famishing wretches. Men in a natural condition may
				   find something to gratify their senses, but there is nothing to feed
				   the soul; that more noble and more essential part perishes for lack of
				   food. They may fare sumptuously every day, they may pamper their
				   bodies, but the soul cannot be fed from a sumptuous table; they may
				   drink wine in bowls, yet the spiritual part is not refreshed. The
				   superior faculties want to be supplied as well as the inferior. True
				   poverty and true misery consist in the want of those things of which
				   our spiritual part stands in need.
				
				   3. Those sinners who are thoroughly awakened, are sensible of their
				   great want. Multitudes of men are not sensible of their miserable,
				   needy condition. There are many who are thus poor, and think themselves
				   rich, and increased in goods. Indeed there are no natural men that have
				   true contentment: they are all restless, and crying, "Who will show us
				   any good?" but multitudes are not sensible how exceedingly necessitous
				   is their condition. But the thoroughly awakened soul sees that he is
				   very far from true happiness, that those things which he possesses will
				   never make him happy; that for all his outward possessions he is
				   wretched, and miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked. He becomes
				   sensible of the short continuance and uncertainty of those things, and
				   their insufficiency to satisfy a troubled conscience. He wants
				   something else to give him peace and ease. If you would tell him that
				   he might have a kingdom, it would not quiet him; he desires to have his
				   sins pardoned, and to be at peace with his Judge. He is poor, and he
				   becomes as a beggar; he comes and cries for help. He does not thirst,
				   because he as yet sees where true happiness is to be found, but because
				   he sees that he has it not, and cannot find it. He is without comfort,
				   and does not know where to find it, but he longs for it. O, what would
				   he not give, if he could find some satisfying peace and comfort!
				
				   Such are those hungry, thirsty souls that Christ so often invites to
				   come to him. Isaiah 55:1, 2. "Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to
				   the waters, and he that hath no money, come ye, buy and eat; yea, come,
				   buy wine and milk without money and without price. Wherefore do ye
				   spend money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which
				   satisfieth not? hearken diligently unto me, and eat ye that which is
				   good, and let your soul delight itself in fatness." "If any man thirst,
				   let him come unto me and drink; and he that is athirst, let him come
				   and take of the water of life freely."
				
				   4. There is in Christ Jesus provision for the full satisfaction and
				   contentment of such as these.
				
				   First. The excellency of Christ is such, that the discovery of it is
				   exceedingly contenting and satisfying to the soul. The inquiry of the
				   soul is after that which is most excellent. The carnal soul imagines
				   that earthly things are excellent; one thinks riches most excellent,
				   another has the highest esteem of honour, and to another carnal
				   pleasure appears the most excellent; but the soul cannot find
				   contentment in any of these things, because it soon finds an end to
				   their excellency. Worldly men imagine, that there is true excellency
				   and true happiness in those things which they are pursuing. They think
				   that if they could but obtain them, they should be happy; and when they
				   obtain them, and cannot find happiness, they look for happiness in
				   something else, and are still upon the pursuit.
				
				   But Christ Jesus has true excellency, and so great excellency, that
				   when they come to see it they look no further, but the mind rests
				   there. It sees a transcendent glory and an ineffable sweetness in him;
				   it sees that till now it has been pursuing shadows, but that now it has
				   found the substance; that before it had been seeking happiness in the
				   stream, but that now it has found the ocean. The excellency of Christ
				   is an object adequate to the natural cravings of the soul, and is
				   sufficient to fill the capacity. It is an infinite excellency, such an
				   one as the mind desires, in which it can find no bounds; and the more
				   the mind is used to it, the more excellent it appears. Every new
				   discovery makes this beauty appear more ravishing, and the mind sees no
				   end; here is room enough for the mind to go deeper and deeper, and
				   never come to the bottom. The soul is exceedingly ravished when it
				   first looks on this beauty, and it is never weary of it. The mind never
				   has any satiety, but Christ's excellency is always fresh and new, and
				   tends as much to delight, after it has been seen a thousand or ten
				   thousand years, as when it was seen the first moment. The excellency of
				   Christ is an object suited to the superior faculties of man, it is
				   suited to entertain the faculty of reason and understanding, and there
				   is nothing so worthy about which the understanding can be employed as
				   this excellency; no other object is so great, noble, and exalted.
				
				   This excellency of Jesus Christ is the suitable food of the rational
				   soul. The soul that comes to Christ, feeds upon this, and lives upon
				   it; it is that bread which came down from heaven, of which he that eats
				   shall not die; it is angels' food, it is that wine and milk that is
				   given without money, and without price. This is that fatness in which
				   the believing soul delights itself; here the longing soul may be
				   satisfied, and the hungry soul may be filled with goodness. The delight
				   and contentment that is to be found here, passeth understanding, and is
				   unspeakable and full of glory. It is impossible for those who have
				   tasted of this fountain, and know the sweetness of it, ever to forsake
				   it. The soul has found the river of water of life, and it desires no
				   other drink; it has found the tree of life, and it desires no other
				   fruit.
				
				   Secondly. The manifestation of the love of Christ gives the soul
				   abundant contentment. This love of Christ is exceedingly sweet and
				   satisfying, it is better than life, because it is the love of a person
				   of such dignity and excellency. The sweetness of his love depends very
				   much upon the greatness of his excellency; so much the more lovely the
				   person, so much the more desirable is his love. How sweet must the love
				   of that person be, who is the eternal Son of God, who is of equal
				   dignity with the Father! How great a happiness must it be to be the
				   object of the love of him who is the Creator of the world, and by whom
				   all things consist, and who is exalted at God's right hand, and made
				   head over principalities and powers in heavenly places, who has all
				   things put under his feet, and is King of kings and Lord of lords, and
				   is the brightness of the Father's glory! Surely to be beloved by him,
				   is enough to satisfy the soul of a worm of the dust.
				
				   This love of Christ is also exceedingly sweet and satisfying from the
				   greatness of it; it is a dying love; such love as never was before
				   seen, and such as no other can parallel. There have been instances of
				   very great love between one earthly friend and another; there was a
				   surpassing love between David and Jonathan. But there never was any
				   such love as Christ has towards believers. The satisfying nature of
				   this love arises also from the sweet fruits of it. Those precious
				   benefits that Christ bestows upon his people, and those precious
				   promises which he has given them, are the fruit of this love; joy and
				   hope are the constant streams that flow from this fountain, from the
				   love of Christ.
				
				   Thirdly. There is provision for the satisfaction and contentment of the
				   thirsty longing soul in Christ, as he is the way to the Father; not
				   only from the fulness of excellency and grace which he has in his own
				   person, but as by him we may come to God, may be reconciled to him, and
				   may be made happy in his favour and love. The poverty and want of the
				   soul in its natural state consist in its being separated from God, for
				   God is the riches and the happiness of the creature. But we naturally
				   are alienated from God; and God is alienated from us, our Maker is not
				   at peace with us. But in Christ there is a way for a free communication
				   between God and us; for us to come to God, and for God to communicate
				   himself to us by his Spirit. John 14:6. "Jesus saith unto him, I am the
				   way, and the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father but by
				   me." Ephesians 2:13, 18, 19. "But now in Christ Jesus, ye who sometimes
				   were far off, are made nigh by the blood of Christ. For through him we
				   both have access by one Spirit unto the Father. Now, therefore, ye are
				   no more strangers and foreigners, but fellow-citizens with the saints,
				   and of the household of God." Christ by being thus the way to the
				   Father, is the way to true happiness and contentment. John 10:9. "I am
				   the door: by me, if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go
				   in and out, and find pasture." Hence I would take occasion to invite
				   needy, thirsty souls to come to Jesus. "In the last day, that great day
				   of the feast, Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any man thirst, let him
				   come unto me and drink." You that have not yet come to Christ, are in a
				   poor, necessitous condition; you are in a parched wilderness, in a dry
				   and thirsty land. And if you are thoroughly awakened, you are sensible
				   that you are in distress and ready to faint for want of something to
				   satisfy your souls. Come to him who is "as rivers of water in a dry
				   place." There are plenty and fulness in him; he is like a river that is
				   always flowing, you may live by it for ever, and never be in want. Come
				   to him who has such excellency as is sufficient to give full
				   contentment to your soul, who is a person of transcendent glory, and
				   ineffable beauty, where you may entertain the view of your soul for
				   ever without weariness, and without being cloyed. Accept of the offered
				   love of him who is the only-begotten Son of God, and his elect, in whom
				   his soul delighteth. Through Christ, come to God the Father, from whom
				   you have departed by sin. He is the way, the truth, and the life; he is
				   the door, by which if any man enters he shall be saved.
				
				   III. There are quiet rest and sweet refreshment in Christ Jesus, for
				   those that are weary. He is "as the shadow of a great rock in a weary
				   land."
				
				   The comparison that is used in the text is very beautiful and very
				   significative. The dry, barren, and scorched wilderness of Arabia is a
				   very lively representation of the misery that men have brought upon
				   themselves by sin. It is destitute of any inhabitants but lions and
				   tigers and fiery serpents; it is barren and parched, and without any
				   river or spring; it is a land of drought, wherein there is seldom any
				   rain, a land exceedingly hot and uncomfortable. The scorching sunbeams
				   that are ready to consume the spirits of travellers, are a fit
				   representation of terror of conscience, and the inward sense of God's
				   displeasure. And there being no other shade in which travellers may
				   rest, but only here and there that of a great rock, it is a fit
				   representation of Jesus Christ, who came to redeem us from our misery.
				   Christ is often compared to a rock, because he is a sure foundation to
				   builders, and because he is a sure bulwark and defence. They who dwell
				   upon the top of a rock, dwell in a most defensible place; we read of
				   those whose habitation is the munitions of rocks. He may also be
				   compared to a rock, as he is everlasting and unchangeable. A great rock
				   remains stedfast, unmoved, and unbroken by winds and storms from age to
				   age; and therefore God chose a rock to be an emblem of Christ in the
				   wilderness, when he caused water to issue forth for the children of
				   Israel; and the shadow of a great rock is a most fit representation of
				   the refreshment given to weary souls by Jesus Christ.
				
				   1. There is quiet rest and full refreshment in Christ for sinners that
				   are weary and heavy laden with sin. Sin is the most evil and odious
				   thing, as well as the most mischievous and fatal; it is the most mortal
				   poison; it, above all things, hazards life, and endangers the soul,
				   exposes to the loss of all happiness, and to the suffering of all
				   misery, and brings the wrath of God. All men have this dreadful evil
				   hanging about them, and cleaving fast to the soul, and ruling over it,
				   and keeping it in possession, and under absolute command: it hangs like
				   a viper to the heart, or rather holds it as a lion does his prey.
				
				   But yet there are multitudes, who are not sensible of their misery.
				   They are in such a sleep that they are not very unquiet in this
				   condition, it is not very burthensome to them, they are so sottish that
				   they do not know what is their state, and what is like to become of
				   them. But there are others who have their sense so far restored to them
				   that they feel the pain, and see the approaching destruction, and sin
				   lies like a heavy load upon their hearts; it is a load that lies upon
				   them day and night, they cannot lay it down to rest themselves, but it
				   continually oppresses them. It is bound fast unto them, and is ready to
				   sink them down; it is a continual labour of heart, to support itself
				   under this burden. Thus we read of them "that labour, and are heavy
				   laden." Or rather, it is like the scorching heat in a dry wilderness,
				   where the sun beats and burns all the day long; where they have nothing
				   to defend them; where they can find no shade to refresh themselves. If
				   they lay themselves down to rest, it is like lying down in the hot
				   sands, where there is nothing to keep off the heat.
				
				   Here it may be proper to inquire who are weary and heavy laden with
				   sin; and in what sense a sinner may be weary and burdened with sin.
				   Sinners are not wearied with sin from any dislike to it, or dislike of
				   it. There is no sinner that is burdened with sin in the sense in which
				   a godly man carries his indwelling sin, as his daily and greatest
				   burden, because he loathes it, and longs to get rid of it; he would
				   fain be at a great distance from it, and have nothing more to do with
				   it; he is ready to cry out as Paul did, "O wretched man that I am! who
				   shall deliver me from the body of this death?" The unregenerate man has
				   nothing of this nature, for sin is yet his delight, he dearly loves it.
				   If he be under convictions, his love to sin in general is not
				   mortified, he loves it as well as ever, he hides it still as a sweet
				   morsel under his tongue.
				   But there is a difference between being weary and burdened with sin,
				   and being weary of sin. Awakened sinners are weary with sin, but not
				   properly weary of it.
				
				   Therefore, they are only weary of the guilt of sin, the guilt that
				   cleaves to their consciences is that great burden. God has put the
				   sense of feeling into their consciences, that were before as seared
				   flesh, and it is guilt that pains them. The filthiness of sin and its
				   evil nature, as it is an offence to a holy, gracious, and glorious God,
				   is not a burden to them. But it is the connexion between sin and
				   punishment, between sin and God's wrath, that makes it a burden. Their
				   consciences are heavy laden with guilt, which is an obligation to
				   punishment; they see the threatening and curse of the law joined to
				   their sins, and see that the justice of God and his vengeance are
				   against them. They are burdened with their sins, not because there is
				   any odiousness in them, but because there is hell in them. This is the
				   sting of sin, whereby it stings the conscience, and distresses and
				   wearies the soul.
				
				   The guilt of such and such great sins is upon the soul, and the man
				   sees no way to get rid of it, but he has wearisome days and wearisome
				   nights; it makes him ready sometimes to say as the psalmist did, "O
				   that I had wings like a dove! for then would I fly away and be at rest.
				   Lo, then would I wander far off, and remain in the wilderness. I would
				   hasten my escape from the windy storm and tempest." But when sinners
				   come to Christ, he takes away that which was their burden, or their sin
				   and guilt, that which was so heavy upon their hearts, that so
				   distressed their minds.
				
				   First. He takes away the guilt of sin, from which the soul before saw
				   no way how it was possible to be freed, and which, if it was not
				   removed, led to eternal destruction. When the sinner comes to Christ,
				   it is all at once taken away, and the soul is left free, it is
				   lightened of its burden, it is delivered from its bondage, and is like
				   a bird escaped from the snare of the fowler. The soul sees in Christ a
				   way to peace with God, and a way by which the law may be answered, and
				   justice satisfied, and yet he may escape; a wonderful way indeed, but
				   yet a certain and a glorious one. And what rest does it give to the
				   weary soul to see itself thus delivered, that the foundation of its
				   anxieties and fears is wholly removed, and that God's wrath ceases,
				   that it is brought into a state of peace with God, and that there is no
				   more occasion to fear hell, but that it is for ever safe! How
				   refreshing is it to the soul to be at once thus delivered of that which
				   was so much its trouble and terror, and to be eased of that which was
				   so much its burden! This is like coming to a cool shade after one has
				   been travelling in a dry and hot wilderness, and almost fainting under
				   the scorching heat. And then Christ also takes away sin itself, and
				   mortifies that root of bitterness which is the cause of all the inward
				   tumults and disquietudes that are in the mind, that make it like the
				   troubled sea that cannot rest, and leaves it all calm. When guilt is
				   taken away and sin is mortified, then the foundation of fear, and
				   trouble, and pain is removed, and the soul is left in peace and
				   serenity.
				
				   Secondly. Christ puts strength and a principle of new life into the
				   weary soul that comes to him. The sinner, before he comes to Christ, is
				   as a sick man that is weakened and brought low, and whose nature is
				   consumed by some strong distemper: he is full of pain, and so weak that
				   he cannot walk nor stand. Therefore, Christ is compared to a physician.
				   "But when Jesus heard that, he said unto them, They that be whole, need
				   not a physician, but they that are sick." When he comes and speaks the
				   word, he puts a principle of life into him that was before as dead: he
				   gives a principle of spiritual life and the beginning of eternal life;
				   he invigorates the mind with a communication of his own life and
				   strength, and renews the nature and creates it again, and makes the man
				   to be a new creature.
				
				   So that the fainting, sinking spirits are now revived, and this
				   principle of spiritual life is a continual spring of refreshment, like
				   a well of living water. "Whosoever drinketh of the water that I shall
				   give him, shall never thirst; but the water that I shall give him shall
				   be in him a well of water springing up into everlasting life." Christ
				   gives his Spirit, that calms the mind, and is like a refreshing breeze
				   of wind. He gives that strength whereby he lifts up the hands that hang
				   down, and strengthens the feeble knees.
				
				   Thirdly. Christ gives to those who come to him such comfort and
				   pleasure as are enough to make them forget all their former labour and
				   travail. A little of true peace, a little of the joys of the manifested
				   love of Christ, and a little of the true and holy hope of eternal life,
				   are enough to compensate for all that toil and weariness, and to erase
				   the remembrance of it from the mind. That peace which results from true
				   faith passes understanding, and that joy is joy unspeakable. There is
				   something peculiarly sweet and refreshing in this joy, that is not in
				   other joys; and what can more effectually support the mind, or give a
				   more rational ground of rejoicing, than a prospect of eternal glory in
				   the enjoyment of God from God's own promise in Christ? If we come to
				   Christ, we may not only be refreshed by resting in his shadow, but by
				   eating his fruit: these things are the fruits of this tree. "I sat down
				   under his shadow with great delight, and his fruit was sweet to my
				   taste."
				   Before proceeding to the next particular of this proposition, I would
				   apply myself to those that are weary; to move them to repose themselves
				   under Christ's shadow.
				
				   The great trouble of such a state, one would think, should be a motive
				   to you to accept of an offer of relief, and remedy. You are weary, and
				   doubtless would be glad to be at rest; but here you are to consider,
				
				   First. That there is no remedy but in Jesus Christ; there is nothing
				   else will give you true quietness. If you could fly into heaven, you
				   would not find it there; if you should take the wings of the morning,
				   and dwell in the uttermost parts of the earth, in some solitary place
				   in the wilderness, you could not fly from your burden. So that if you
				   do not come to Christ, you must either continue still weary and
				   burdened, or, which is worse, you must return to your old dead sleep,
				   to a state of stupidity; and not only so, but you must be everlastingly
				   wearied with God's wrath.
				
				   Second. Consider that Christ is a remedy at hand. You need not wish for
				   the wings of a dove that you may fly afar off, and be at rest, but
				   Christ is nigh at hand, if you were but sensible of it. Romans 10:6, 7,
				   8. "But the righteousness which is of faith speaketh on this wise, Say
				   not in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring
				   Christ down from above:) or, Who shall descend into the deep? (that is,
				   to bring up Christ again from the dead.) But what saith it? The word is
				   nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart; that is, the word of
				   faith which we preach." There is no need of doing any great work to
				   come at this rest; the way is plain to it; it is but going to it, it is
				   but sitting down under Christ's shadow. Christ requires no money to
				   purchase rest of him, he calls to us to come freely, and for nothing.
				   If we are poor and have no money, we may come. Christ sent out his
				   servants to invite the poor, the maimed, the halt, and the blind.
				   Christ does not want to be hired to accept of you, and to give you
				   rest. It is his work as Mediator to give rest to the weary, it is the
				   work that he was anointed for, and in which he delights. "The Spirit of
				   the Lord God is upon me; because the Lord hath anointed me to preach
				   good tidings unto the meek; he hath sent me to bind up the
				   broken-hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the opening of
				   the prison to them that are bound."
				
				   Third. Christ is not only a remedy for your weariness and trouble, but
				   he will give you an abundance of the contrary, joy and delight. They
				   who come to Christ, do no only come to a resting-place after they have
				   been wandering in a wilderness, but they come to a banqueting-house
				   where they may rest, and where they may feast. They may cease from
				   their former troubles and toils, and they may enter upon a course of
				   delights and spiritual joys.
				
				   Christ not only delivers from fears of hell and of wrath, but he gives
				   hopes of heaven, and the enjoyment of God's love. He delivers from
				   inward tumults and inward pain from that guilt of conscience which is
				   as a worm gnawing within, and he gives delight and inward glory. He
				   brings us out of a wilderness of pits, and drought, and fiery flying
				   spirits; and he brings us into a pleasant land, a land flowing with
				   milk and honey. He delivers us out of prison, and lifts us off from the
				   dunghill, and he sets us among princes, and causes us to inherit the
				   throne of glory. Wherefore, if any one is weary, if any is in prison,
				   if any one is in captivity, if any one is in the wilderness, let him
				   come to the blessed Jesus, who is as the shadow of a great rock in a
				   weary land. Delay not, arise and come away.
				
				   2. There are quiet rest and sweet refreshment in Christ for God's
				   people that are weary.
				
				   The saints themselves, while they remain in this imperfect state, and
				   have so much remains of sin in their hearts, are liable still to many
				   troubles and sorrows, and much weariness, and have often need to resort
				   anew unto Jesus Christ for rest. I shall mention three cases wherein
				   Christ is a sufficient remedy.
				
				   First. There is rest and sweet refreshment in Christ for those that are
				   wearied with persecutions. It has been the lot of God's church in this
				   world for the most part to be persecuted. It has had now and then some
				   lucid intervals of peace and outward prosperity, but generally it has
				   been otherwise. This has accorded with the first prophecy concerning
				   Christ; "I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy
				   seed and her seed." Those two seeds have been at enmity ever since the
				   time of Abel. Satan has borne great malice against the church of God,
				   and so have those that are his seed. And oftentimes God's people have
				   been persecuted to an extreme degree, have been put to the most
				   exquisite torments that wit or art could devise, and thousands of them
				   have been tormented to death.
				
				   But even in such a case there are rest and refreshment to be found in
				   Christ Jesus. When their cruel enemies have given them no rest in this
				   world; when, as oftentimes has been the case, they could not flee, nor
				   in any way avoid the rage of their adversaries, but many of them have
				   been tormented gradually from day to day, that their torments might be
				   lengthened; still rest has been found even then in Christ. It has been
				   often found by experience; the martyrs have often showed plainly that
				   the peace and calm of their minds were undisturbed in the midst of the
				   greatest bodily torment, and have sometimes rejoiced and sung praises
				   upon the rack and in the fire. If Christ is pleased to send forth his
				   Spirit to manifest his love, and speaks friendly to the soul, it will
				   support it even in the greatest outward torment that man can inflict.
				   Christ is the joy of the soul, and if the soul be but rejoiced and
				   filled with divine light, such joy no man can take away; whatever
				   outward misery there be, the spirit will sustain it.
				
				   Secondly. There is in Christ rest for God's people, when exercised with
				   afflictions. If a person labour under great bodily weakness, or under
				   some disease that causes frequent and strong pains, such things will
				   tire out so feeble a creature as man. It may to such an one be a
				   comfort and an effectual support to think, that he has a Mediator, who
				   knows by experience what pain is; who by his pain has purchased eternal
				   ease and pleasure for him; and who will make his brief sufferings to
				   work out a far more exceeding delight, to be bestowed when he shall
				   rest from his labours and sorrows.
				
				   If a person be brought into great straits as to outward subsistence,
				   and poverty brings abundance of difficulties and extremities; yet it
				   may be a supporting, refreshing consideration to such an one to think,
				   that he has a compassionate Savior, who when upon earth, was so poor
				   that he had not where to lay his head, and who became poor to make him
				   rich, and purchased for him durable riches, and will make his poverty
				   work out an exceeding and eternal weight of glory.
				
				   If God in his providence calls his people to mourn over lost relations,
				   and if he repeats his stroke and takes away one after another of those
				   that were dear to him; it is a supporting, refreshing consideration to
				   think, that Christ has declared that he will be in stead of all
				   relations unto those who trust in him. They are as his mother, and
				   sister, and brother; he has taken them into a very near relation to
				   himself: and in every other afflictive providence, it is a great
				   comfort to a believing soul to think that he has an intercessor with
				   God, that by him he can have access with confidence to the throne of
				   grace, and that in Christ we have so many great and precious promises,
				   that all things shall work together for good, and shall issue in
				   eternal blessedness. God's people, whenever they are scorched by
				   afflictions as by hot sun-beams, may resort to him, who is as a shadow
				   of a great rock, and be effectually sheltered, and sweetly refreshed.
				
				   Thirdly. There is in Christ quiet rest and sweet refreshment for God's
				   people, when wearied with the buffetings of Satan. The devil, that
				   malicious enemy of God and man, does whatever lies in his power to
				   darken and hinder, and tempt God's people, and render their lives
				   uncomfortable. Often he raises needless and groundless scruples, and
				   casts in doubts, and fills the mind with such fear as is tormenting,
				   and tends to hinder them exceedingly in the christian course; and he
				   often raises mists and clouds of darkness, and stirs up corruption, and
				   thereby fills the mind with concern and anguish, and sometimes wearies
				   out the soul. So that they may say as the psalmist; "Many bulls have
				   compassed me: strong bulls of Bashan have beset me round. They gaped
				   upon me with their mouths, as a ravening and a roaring lion."
				
				   In such a case if the soul flies to Jesus Christ, they may find rest in
				   him, for he came into the world to destroy Satan, and to rescue souls
				   out of his hands. And he has all things put under his feet, whether
				   they be things in heaven, or things on earth, or things in hell, and
				   therefore he can restrain Satan when he pleases. And that he is
				   doubtless ready enough to pity us under such temptations, we may be
				   assured, for he has been tempted and buffeted by Satan as well as we.
				   He is able to succour those that are tempted, and he has promised that
				   the will subdue Satan under his people's feet. Let God's people
				   therefore, when they are exercised with any of those kinds of
				   weariness, make their resort unto Jesus Christ for refuge and rest.
				
				   REFLECTIONS
				
				   1. We may here see great reason to admire the goodness and grace of God
				   to us in our low estate, that he has so provided for our help and
				   relief. We are by our own sin against God plunged into all sort of
				   evil, and God has provided a remedy for us against every sort of evil,
				   he has left us helpless in no calamity. We by our sin have exposed
				   ourselves to wrath, to a vindictive justice; but God has done very
				   great things that we might be saved from that wrath; he has been at
				   infinite cost that the law might be answered without our suffering. We
				   by our sins have exposed ourselves to terror of conscience, in
				   expectation of the dreadful storm of God's wrath; but God has provided
				   for us a hiding-place from the storm, he bids us enter into his
				   chambers, and hide ourselves from indignation. We by sin have made
				   ourselves poor, needy creatures; but God has provided for us gold tried
				   in the fire. We by sin have made ourselves naked; and when he passed
				   by, he took notice of our want, and has provided us white raiment that
				   we may be clothed. We have made ourselves blind, and God in mercy to us
				   has provided eye-salve, that we may see. We have deprived ourselves of
				   all spiritual food; we are like the prodigal son that perished with
				   hunger, and would gladly have filled his belly with husks. God has
				   taken notice of this our condition, and has provided for us a feast of
				   fat things, and has sent forth his servants to invite the poor, the
				   maimed, the halt, and the blind. We by sin have brought ourselves into
				   a dry and thirsty wilderness; but God was merciful, and took notice of
				   our condition, and has provided for us rivers of water, water out of
				   the rock. We by sin have brought upon ourselves a miserable slavery and
				   bondage; God has made provision for our liberty. We have exposed
				   ourselves to weariness; God has provided a resting-place for us. We by
				   sin have exposed ourselves to many outward troubles and afflictions;
				   God has pitied us, and in Christ has provided true comfort for us. We
				   have exposed ourselves to our grand enemy, even Satan, to be tempted
				   and buffeted by him; God has pitied, and has provided for us a Savior
				   and Captain of salvation, who has overcome Satan, and is able to
				   deliver us. Thus God has in Christ provided sufficiently for our help
				   in all kinds of evils.
				
				   How ought we to bless God for this abundant provision he has made for
				   us, poor and sinful as we were, who were so undeserving and so
				   ungrateful. He made no such provision for the fallen angels, who are
				   left without remedy in all the woes and miseries into which they are
				   plunged.
				
				   2. We should admire the love of Christ to men, that he has thus given
				   himself to be the remedy for all their evil, and a fountain of all
				   good. Christ has given himself to us, to be all things to us that we
				   need. We want clothing, and Christ does not only give us clothing, but
				   he gives himself to be our clothing, that we might put him on.
				   Galatians 3:27. "For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ
				   have put on Christ." Romans 13:14. "But put ye on the Lord Jesus
				   Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts
				   thereof."
				
				   We want food, and Christ has given himself to be our food; he has given
				   his own flesh to be our meat, and his blood to be our drink, to nourish
				   our soul. Thus Christ tells us that he is the bread which came down
				   from heaven, and the bread of life. "I am that bread of life. Your
				   fathers did eat manna in the wilderness, and are dead. This is the
				   bread which cometh down from heaven, that a man may eat thereof, and
				   not die. I am the living bread which came down from heaven: if any man
				   eat of this bread, he shall live for ever; and the bread that I will
				   give is my flesh, which I will give for the life of the world." In
				   order to our eating of his flesh, it was necessary that he should be
				   slain, as the sacrifices must be slain before they could be eaten; and
				   such was Christ's love to us, that he consented to be slain, he went as
				   a sheep to the slaughter, that he might give us his flesh to be food
				   for our poor, famishing souls.
				
				   We are in need of a habitation; we by sin have, as it were, turned
				   ourselves out of house and home; Christ has given himself to be the
				   habitation of his people. Psalm 90:1. "Lord, thou has been our
				   dwelling-place in all generations." It is promised to God's people that
				   they should dwell in the temple of God for ever, and should go no more
				   out; and we are told that Christ is the temple of the new Jerusalem.
				
				   Christ gives himself to his people to be all things to them that they
				   need, and all things that make for their happiness. Colossians 3:11.
				   "Where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision,
				   barbarian, Scythian, bond, nor free; but Christ is all, and in all."
				   And that he might be so, he has refused nothing that is needful to
				   prepare him to be so.
				
				   When it was needful that he should be incarnate, he refused it not, but
				   became man, and appeared in the form of a servant. When it was needful
				   that he should be slain, he refused it not, but gave himself for us,
				   and gave himself to us upon the cross.
				
				   Here is love for us to admire, for us to praise, and for us to rejoice
				   in, with joy that is full of glory for ever.
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				PARDON FOR THE GREATEST SINNERS
				
				   Psalm 25:11 -- For thy name's sake, O Lord, pardon my iniquity; for it
				   is great.
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				   IT is evident by some passages in this psalm, that when it was penned,
				   it was a time of affliction and danger with David. This appears
				   particularly by the 15th and following verses: "Mine eyes are ever
				   towards the Lord; for he shall pluck my feet out of the net," etc. His
				   distress makes him think of his sins, and leads him to confess them,
				   and to cry to God for pardon, as is suitable in a time of affliction.
				   See ver. 7. "Remember not the sins of my youth, nor my transgressions;"
				   and verse 18. "Look upon mine affliction, and my pain, and forgive all
				   my sins."
				
				   It is observable in the text, what arguments the psalmist makes use of
				   in pleading for pardon.
				
				   1. He pleads for pardon for God's name's sake. He has no expectation of
				   pardon for the sake of any righteousness or worthiness of his for any
				   good deeds he had done, or any compensation he had made for his sins;
				   though if man's righteousness could be a just plea, David would have
				   had as much to plead as most. But he begs that God would do it for his
				   own name's sake, for his own glory, for the glory of his own free
				   grace, and for the honour of his own covenant-faithfulness.
				
				   2. The psalmist pleads the greatness of his sins as an argument for
				   mercy. He not only doth not plead his own righteousness, or the
				   smallness of his sins; he not only cloth not say, Pardon mine iniquity,
				   for I have done much good to counterbalance it; or, Pardon mine
				   iniquity, for it is small, and thou hast no great reason to be angry
				   with me; mine iniquity is not so great, that thou hast any just cause
				   to remember it against me; mine offence is not such but that thou
				   mayest well enough overlook i': but on the contrary he says, Pardon
				   mine iniquity, for it is great; he pleads the greatness of his sin, and
				   not the smallness of it; the enforces his prayer with this
				   consideration, that his sins are very heinous.
				
				   But how could he make this a plea for pardon? I answer, Because the
				   greater his iniquity was, the more need he had of pardon. It is as much
				   as if he had said, Pardon mine iniquity, for it is so great that I
				   cannot bear the punishment; my sin is so great that I am in necessity
				   of pardon; my case will be exceedingly miserable, unless thou be
				   pleased to pardon me. He makes use of the greatness of his sin, to
				   enforce his plea for pardon, as a man would make use of the greatness
				   of calamity in begging for relief. When a beggar begs for bread, he
				   will plead the greatness of his poverty and necessity. When a man in
				   distress cries for pity, what more suitable plea can be urged than the
				   extremity of his case?--And God allows such a plea as this: for he is
				   moved to mercy towards us by nothing in us but the miserableness of our
				   case. He doth not pity sinners because they are worthy, but because
				   they need his pity.
				
				  DOCTRINE
				
				   If we truly come to God for mercy, the greatness of our sin will be no
				   impediment to pardon.--If it were an impediment, David would never have
				   used it as a plea for pardon, as we find he does in the text.--The
				   following things are needful in order that we truly come to God for
				   mercy:
				
				   I. That we should see our misery, and be sensible of our need of mercy.
				   They who are not sensible of their misery cannot truly look to God for
				   mercy; for it is the very notion of divine mercy, that it is the
				   goodness and grace of God to the miserable. Without misery in the
				   object, there can be no exercise of mercy. To suppose mercy without
				   supposing misery, or pity without calamity, is a contradiction:
				   therefore men cannot look upon themselves as proper objects of mercy,
				   unless they first know themselves to be miserable; and so, unless this
				   be the case, it is impossible that they should come to God for mercy.
				   They must be sensible that they are the children of wrath; that the law
				   is against them, and that they are exposed to the curse of it: that the
				   wrath of God abideth on them; and that he is angry' with them every day
				   while they are under the guilt of sin.--They must be sensible that it
				   is a very dreadful thing to be the object of the wrath of God; that it
				   is a very awful thing to have him for their enemy; and that they cannot
				   bear his wrath. They must he sensible that the guilt of sin makes them
				   miserable creatures, whatever temporal enjoyments they have; that they
				   can be no other than miserable, undone creatures, so long as God is
				   angry with them; that they are without strength, and must perish, and
				   that eternally, unless God help them. They must see that their case is
				   utterly desperate, for any thing that any one else can do for them;
				   that they hang over the pit of eternal misery; and that they must
				   necessarily drop into it, if God have not mercy on them.
				
				   II. They must be sensible that they are not worthy that God should have
				   mercy on them. They who truly come to God for mercy, come as beggars,
				   and not as creditors: they come for mere mercy. for sovereign grace,
				   and not for any thing that is due. Therefore, they must see that the
				   misery under which they lie is justly brought upon them, and that the
				   wrath to which they are exposed is justly threatened against them; and
				   that they have deserved that God should be their enemy, and should
				   continue to be their enemy. They must be sensible that it would be just
				   with God to do as he hath threatened in his holy law, viz. make them
				   the objects of his wrath and curse in hell to all eternity.-- They who
				   come to God for mercy in a right manner are not disposed to find fault
				   with his severity; but they come in a sense of their own utter
				   unworthiness, as with ropes about their necks, and lying in the dust at
				   the foot of mercy.
				
				   III. They must come to God for mercy in and through Jesus Christ alone.
				   All their hope of mercy must be from the consideration of what he is,
				   what he hath done, and what he hath suffered; and that there is no
				   other name given under heaven, among men, whereby we can be saved, but
				   that of Christ; that he is the Son of God, and the Saviour of the
				   world; that his blood cleanses from all sin, and that he is so worthy,
				   that all sinners who are in him may well be pardoned and accepted.--It
				   is impossible that any should come to God for mercy, and at the same
				   time have no hope of mercy. Their coming to God for it, implies that
				   they have some hope of obtaining, otherwise they would not think it
				   worth the while to come. But they that come in a right manner have all
				   their hope through Christ, or from the consideration of his redemption,
				   and the sufficiency of it.--If persons thus come to God for mercy, the
				   greatness of their sins will be no impediment to pardon. Let their sins
				   be ever so many, and great, and aggravated, it will not make God in the
				   least degree more backward to pardon them. This may be made evident by
				   the following considerations:
				
				   1. The mercy of God is as sufficient for the pardon of the greatest
				   sins, as for the least; and that because his mercy is infinite. That
				   which is infinite, is as much above what is great, as it is above what
				   is small. Thus God being infinitely great, he is as much above kings as
				   he is above beggars; he is as much above the highest angel, as he is
				   above the meanest worm. One finite measure doth not come any nearer to
				   the extent of what is infinite than another.--So the mercy of God being
				   infinite, it must be as sufficient for the pardon of all sin, as of
				   one. If one of the least sins be not beyond the mercy of God, so
				   neither are the greatest, or ten thousand of them.--However, it must be
				   acknowledged, that this alone doth not prove the doctrine. For though
				   the mercy of God may be as sufficient for the pardon of great sins as
				   others; yet there may be other obstacles, besides the want of mercy.
				   The mercy of God may be sufficient, and yet the other attributes may
				   oppose the dispensation of mercy in these cases.-- Therefore I observe,
				
				   2. That the satisfaction of Christ is as sufficient for the removal of
				   the greatest guilt, as the least: 1 John i. 7. " The blood of Christ
				   cleanseth from all sin." Acts xiii. 39. " By him all that believe are
				   justified from all things from which ye could not be justified by the
				   law of Moses." All the sins of those who truly come to God for mercy,
				   let them be what they will, are satisfied for, if God be true who tells
				   us so; and if they be satisfied for, surely it is not incredible, that
				   God should be ready to pardon them. So that Christ having fully
				   satisfied for all sin, or having wrought out a satisfaction that is
				   sufficient for all, it is now no way inconsistent with the glory of the
				   divine attributes to pardon the greatest sins of those who in a right
				   manner come unto him for it. God may now pardon the greatest sinners
				   without any prejudice to the honour of his holiness. The holiness of
				   God will not suffer him to give the least countenance to sin, but
				   inclines him to give proper testimonies of his hatred of it. But Christ
				   having satisfied for sin, God can now love the sinner, and give no
				   countenance at all to sin, however great a sinner he may have been. It
				   was a sufficient testimony of God's abhorrence of sin, that he poured
				   out his wrath on his own dear Son, when he took the guilt of it upon
				   himself. Nothing can more show God's abhorrence of sin than this. If
				   all mankind had been eternally damned, it would not have been so great
				   a testimony of it.
				
				   God may, through Christ, pardon the greatest sinner without any
				   prejudice to the honour of his majesty. The honour of the divine
				   majesty indeed requires satisfaction; but the sufferings of Christ
				   fully repair the injury. Let the contempt be ever so great, yet if so
				   honourable a person as Christ undertakes to be a Mediator for the
				   offender, and suffers so much for him, it fully repairs the injury done
				   to the Majesty of heaven and earth. The sufferings of Christ fully
				   satisfy justice. The justice of God, as the supreme Govemor and Judge
				   of the world, requires the punishment of sin. The supreme Judge must
				   judge the world according to a rule of justice. God doth not show mercy
				   as a judge, but as a sovereign; therefore his exercise of mercy as a
				   sovereign, and his justice as a judge, must be made consistent one with
				   another; and this is done by the sufferings of Christ, in which sin is
				   punished fully, and justice answered. Rom. iii. 25, 26. " Whom God hath
				   set forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, to declare
				   his righteousness for the remission of sins that are past, through the
				   forbearance of God; to declare, I say, at this time, his righteousness;
				   that he might be just, and the justifier of him which believeth in
				   Jesus."--The law is no impediment in the way of the pardon of the
				   greatest sin, if men do but truly come to God for mercy: for Christ
				   hath fulfilled the law, he hath borne the curse of it, in his
				   sufferings; Gal. iii. 13. " Christ hath redeemed us from the curse of
				   the law, being made a curse for us; for it is written, Cursed is every
				   one that hangeth on a tree."
				
				   3. Christ will no! refuse to save the greatest sinners, who in a right
				   manner come to God for mercy; for this is his work. It is his business
				   to be a Saviour of sinners; it is the work upon which he came into the
				   world; and therefore he will not object to it. He did not come to call
				   the righteous, but sinners to repentance, Matt. ix. 13. Sin is the very
				   evil which he came into the world to remedy: therefore he will not
				   object to any man that he is very sinful. The more sinful he is, the
				   more need of Christ.--The sinfulness of man was the reason of Christ's
				   coming into the world; this is the very misery from which he came to
				   deliver men. The more they have of it, the more need they have of being
				   delivered; " They that are whole need not a physician, but they that
				   are sick," Matt. ix. 12. The physician will not make it an objection
				   against healing a man who applies to him, that he stands in great need
				   of his help. If a physician of compassion comes among the sick and
				   wounded, surely he will not refuse to heal those that stand in most
				   need of healing, if he be able to heal them.
				
				   4. Herein cloth the glory of grace by the redemption of Christ much
				   consist, viz. in its sufficiency for the pardon of the greatest
				   sinners. The whole contrivance of the way of salvation is for this end,
				   to glorify the free grace of God. God had it on his heart from all
				   eternity to glorify this attribute; and therefore it is, that the
				   device of saving sinners by Christ was conceived. The greatness of
				   divine grace appears very much in this, that God by Christ saves the
				   greatest offenders. The greater the guilt of any sinner is, the more
				   glorious and wonderful is the grace manifested in his pardon: Rom.
				   4:20. " Where sin abounded, grace did much more abound." The apostle,
				   when telling how great a sinner he had been, takes notice of the
				   abounding of grace in his pardon, of which his great guilt was the
				   occasion: 1 Tim. i. 13. " Who was before a blasphemer, and a
				   persecutor, and injurious. But I obtained mercy; and the grace of our
				   Lord was exceeding abundant, with faith and love which is in Christ
				   Jesus." The Redeemer is glorified, in that he proves sufficient to
				   redeem those who are exceeding sinful, in that his blood proves
				   sufficient to wash away the greatest guilt, in that he is able to save
				   men to the uttermost, and in that he redeems even from the greatest
				   misery. It is the honour of Christ to save the greatest sinners, when
				   they come to him, as it is the honour of a physician that he cures the
				   most desperate diseases or wounds. Therefore, no doubt, Christ will be
				   willing to save the greatest sinners, if they come to him; for he will
				   not be backward to glorify himself, and to commend the value and virtue
				   of his own blood. Seeing he hath so laid out himself to redeem sinners,
				   he will not be unwilling to show, that he is able to redeem to the
				   uttermost.
				
				   5. Pardon is as much offered and promised to the greatest sinners as
				   any, if they will come aright to God for mercy. The invitations of the
				   gospel are always in universal terms: as, Ho, every one that thirsteth;
				   Come unto me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden; and, Whosoever
				   will, let him come. And the voice of Wisdom is to men in general: Prov.
				   viii. 4. " Unto you, O men, I call, and my voice is to the sons of
				   men." Not to moral men, or religious men, but to you, O men. So Christ
				   promises, John vi. 37. " Him that cometh to me, I will in no wise cast
				   out." This is the direction of Christ to his apostles, after his
				   resurrection, Mark xvi. 15, 16. " Go ye into all the world, and preach
				   the gospel to every creature: he that believeth, and is baptized, shall
				   be saved." Which is agreeable to what the apostle saith, that "the
				   gospel was preached to every creature which is under heaven," Col. i.
				   23.
				
				   APPLICATION
				
				   The proper use of this subject is, to encourage sinners whose
				   consciences are burdened with a sense of guilt, immediately to go to
				   God through Christ for mercy. If you go in the manner we have
				   described, the arms of mercy are open to embrace you. You need not be
				   at all the more fearful of coming because of your sins, let them be
				   ever so black. If you had as much guilt lying on each of your souls as
				   all the wicked men in the world, and all the damned souls in hell; yet
				   if you come to God for mercy, sensible of your own vileness, and
				   seeking pardon only through the free mercy of God in Christ, you would
				   not need to be afraid; the greatness of your sins would be no
				   impediment to your pardon. Therefore, if your souls be burdened, and
				   you are distressed for fear of hell, you need not bear that burden and
				   distress any longer. If you are but willing, you may freely come and
				   unload yourselves, and cast all your burdens on Christ, and rest in
				   him.
				
				   But here I shall speak to some OBJECTIONS which some awakened sinners
				   may be ready to make against what I now exhort them to.
				
				   I. Some may be ready to object, I have spent my youth and all the best
				   of my life in sin, and I am afraid God will not accept of me, when I
				   offer him only mine old age.--To this I would answer, 1. Hath God said
				   any where, that he will not accept of old sinners who come to him? God
				   hath often made offers and promises in universal terms; and is there
				   any such exception put in? Doth Christ say, All that thirst, let them
				   come to me and drink, except old sinners? Come to me, all ye that
				   labour and are heavy laden, except old sinners, and I will give you
				   rest? Him that cometh to me, I will in no wise cast out, if he be not
				   an old sinner? Did you ever read any such exception any where in the
				   Bible? and why should you give way to exceptions which you make out of
				   your own heads, or rather which the devil puts into your heads, and
				   which have no foundation in the word of God?--Indeed it is more rare
				   that old sinners are willing to come, than others; but if they do come,
				   they are as readily accepted as any whatever.
				
				   2. When God accepts of young persons, it is not for the sake of the
				   service which they are like to do him afterwards, or because youth is
				   better worth accepting than old age. You seem entirely to mistake the
				   matter, in thinking that God will not accept of you because you are
				   old; as though he readily accepted of persons in their youth, because
				   their youth is better worth his acceptance; whereas it is only for the
				   sake of Jesus Christ, that God is willing to accept of any.
				
				   You say, your life is almost spent, and you are afraid that the best
				   time for serving God is past; and that therefore God will not now
				   accept of you; as if it were for the sake of the service which persons
				   are like to do him, after they are converted, that he accepts of them.
				   But a self-righteous spirit is at the bottom of such objections. Men
				   cannot get off from the notion, that it is for some goodness or service
				   of their own, either done or expected to be done, that God accepts of
				   persons, and receives them into favour.--Indeed they who deny God their
				   youth, the best part of their lives, and spend it in the service of
				   Satan, dreadfully sin and provoke God; and he very often leaves them to
				   hardness of heart when they are grown old. But if they are willing to
				   accept of Christ when old, he is as ready to receive them as any
				   others; for in that matter God hath respect only to Christ and his
				   worthiness.
				
				   II. But, says one, I fear I have committed sins that are peculiar to
				   reprobates. I have sinned against light, and strong convictions of
				   conscience; I have sinned presumptuously; and have so resisted the
				   strivings of the Spirit of God, that I am afraid I have committed such
				   sins as none of God's elect ever commit. I cannot think that God will
				   ever leave one whom he intends to save, to go on and commit sins
				   against so much light and conviction, and with such horrid
				   presumption.--Others may say, I have had risings of heart against God;
				   blasphemous thoughts, a spiteful and malicious spirit; and have abused
				   mercy and the strivings of the Spirit, trampled upon the Saviour, and
				   my sins are such as are peculiar to those who are reprobated to eternal
				   damnation. To all this I would answer,
				
				   1. There is no sin peculiar to reprobates but the sin against the Holy
				   Ghost. Do you read of any other in the word of God? And if you do not
				   read of any there, what ground have you to think any such thing? What
				   other rule have we, by which to judge of such matters, but the divine
				   word? If we venture to go beyond that, we shall be miserably in the
				   dark. When we pretend to go further in our determinations than the word
				   of God, Satan takes us up, and leads us. It seems to you that such sins
				   are peculiar to the reprobate, and such as God never forgives. But what
				   reason can you give for it, if you have no word of God to reveal it? Is
				   it because you cannot see how the mercy of God is sufficient to pardon,
				   or the blood of Christ to cleanse from such presumptuous sins? If so,
				   it is because you never yet saw how great the mercy of God is; you
				   never saw the sufficiency of the blood of Christ, and you know not how
				   far the virtue of it extends. Some elect persons have been guilty of
				   all manner of sins, except the sin against the Holy Ghost; and unless
				   you have been guilty of this, you have not been guilty of any that are
				   peculiar to reprobates.
				
				   2. Men may be less likely to believe, for sins which they have
				   committed, and not the less readily pardoned when they do believe. It
				   must be acknowledged that some sinners are in more danger of hell than
				   others. Though all are in great danger, some are less likely to be
				   saved. Some are less likely ever to be converted and to come to Christ:
				   but all who do come to him are alike readily accepted; and there is as
				   much encouragement for one man to come to Christ as another.--Such sins
				   as you mention are indeed exceeding heinous and provoking to God, and
				   do in an especial manner bring the soul into danger of damnation, and
				   into danger of being given to final hardness of heart; and God more
				   commonly gives men up to the judgment of final hardness for such sins,
				   than for others. Yet they are not peculiar to reprobates; there is but
				   one sin that is so, viz. that against the Holy Ghost. And
				   notwithstanding the sins which you have committed, if you can find it
				   in your hearts to come to Christ, and close with him, you will be
				   accepted not at all the less readily because you have committed such
				   sins.--Though God cloth more rarely cause some sorts of sinners to come
				   to Christ than others, it is not because his mercy or the redemption of
				   Christ is not as sufficient for them as others, but because in wisdom
				   he sees fit so to dispense his grace, for a restraint upon the
				   wickedness of men; and because it is his will to give converting grace
				   in the use of means, among which this is one, viz. to lead a moral and
				   religious life, and agreeable to our light, and the convictions of our
				   consciences. But when once any sinner is willing to come to Christ,
				   mercy is as ready for him as for any. There is no consideration at all
				   had of his sins; let him have been ever so sinful, his sins are not
				   remembered; God doth not upbraid him with them.
				
				   III. But had I not better stay till I shall have made myself better,
				   before I presume to come to Christ. I have been, and see myself to be
				   very wicked now; but am in hopes of mending myself, and rendering
				   myself at least not so wicked: then I shall have more courage to come
				   to God for mercy.--In answer to this,
				
				   1. Consider how unreasonably you act. You are striving to set up
				   yourselves for your own saviours; you are striving to get something of
				   your own, on the account of which you may the more readily be accepted.
				   So that by this it appears that you do not seek to be accepted only on
				   Christ's account. And is not this to rob Christ of the glory of being
				   your only Saviour? Yet this is the way in which you are hoping to make
				   Christ willing to save you.
				
				   2. You can never come to Christ at all, unless you first see that he
				   will not accept of you the more readily for any thing that you can do.
				   You must first see, that it is utterly in vain for you to try to make
				   yourselves better on any such account. You must see that you can never
				   make yourselves any more worthy, or less unworthy, by any thing which
				   you can perform.
				
				   3. If ever you truly come to Christ, you must see that there is enough
				   in him for your pardon, though you be no better than you are. If you
				   see not the sufficiency of Christ to pardon you, without any
				   righteousness of your own to recommend you, you never will come so as
				   to be accepted of him. The way to be accepted is to come--not on any
				   such encouragement, that now you have made yourselves better, and more
				   worthy, or not so unworthy, but--on the mere encouragement of Christ's
				   worthiness, and God's mercy.
				
				   4. If ever you truly come to Christ, you must come to him to make you
				   better. You must come as a patient comes to his physician, with his
				   diseases or wounds to be cured. Spread all your wickedness before him,
				   and do not plead your goodness; but plead your badness, and your
				   necessity on that account: and say, as the psalmist in the text, not
				   Pardon mine iniquity, for it is not so great as it was, but, " Pardon
				   mine iniquity, for it is Great."
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				PRESSING INTO THE KINGDOM OF GOD
				
				    Luke 16:16 -- The law and the prophets were until John; since that time the
				    kingdom of God is preached, and every man presseth into it.
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				   In these words two things may be observed: First, Wherein the work and
				   office of John the Baptist consisted, viz. in preaching the kingdom of
				   God, to prepare the way for its introduction to succeed the law and the
				   prophets. By the law and the prophets, in the text, seems to be
				   intended the ancient dispensation under the Old Testament, which was
				   received from Moses and the prophets. These are said to be until John;
				   not that the revelations given by them are out of use since that time,
				   but that the state of the church, founded and regulated under God by
				   them, the dispensation of which they were the ministers, and wherein
				   the church depended mainly on light received from them, fully continued
				   till John. He first began to introduce the New Testament dispensation,
				   or gospel-state of the church; which, with its glorious, spiritual, and
				   eternal privileges and blessings, is often called the kingdom of
				   heaven, or kingdom of God. John the Baptist preached, that the kingdom
				   of God was at hand. "Repent" says he, "for the kingdom of heaven is at
				   hand:"-"Since that time," says Christ, "the kingdom of God is
				   preached." John the Baptist first began to preach it; and then, after
				   him, Christ and his disciples preached the same.
				
				   Thus Christ preached, Matthew 4:17. "From that time Jesus began to
				   preach, and to say, Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand." So
				   the disciples were directed to preach, Matthew 10:7. "And, as ye go,
				   preach, saying, The kingdom of heaven is at hand." It was not John the
				   Baptist, but Christ, that fully brought in, and actually established,
				   this kingdom of God; but he, as Christ's forerunner to prepare his way
				   before him, did the first thing that was done towards introducing it.
				   The old dispensation was abolished, and the new brought in by degrees;
				   as the night gradually ceases, and gives place to the increasing day
				   which succeeds in its room.
				
				   First the day-star arises; next follows the light of the sun itself,
				   but dimly reflected, in the dawning of the day; but this light
				   increases, and shines more and more, and the stars that served for
				   light during the foregoing night, gradually go out, and their light
				   ceases, as being now needless, till at length the sun rises, and
				   enlightens the world by his own direct light, which increases as he
				   ascends higher above the horizon, till the day-star itself gradually
				   disappears; agreeable to what John says of himself, John 3:30. "He must
				   increase, but I must decrease." John was the forerunner of Christ, and
				   harbinger of the gospel-day; much as the morning-star is the forerunner
				   of the sun. He had the most honorable office of any of the prophets;
				   the other prophets foretold Christ to come, he revealed him as already
				   come, and had the honour to be that servant who should come immediately
				   before him, and actually introduce him, and even to be the instrument
				   concerned in his solemn inauguration, as he was in baptizing him. He
				   was the greatest of the prophets that came before Christ, as the
				   morning-star is the brightest of all the stars, Matthew 11:11. He came
				   to prepare men's hearts to receive that kingdom of God which Christ was
				   about more fully to reveal and erect. Luke 1:17. "To make ready a
				   people prepared for the Lord."
				
				   Secondly, We may observe wherein his success appeared, viz. in that
				   since he began his ministry, every man pressed into that kingdom of God
				   which he preached. The greatness of his success appeared in two things:
				
				   1. In the generalness of it, with regard to the subject, or the persons
				   in whom the success appeared; every man. Here is a term of
				   universality; but it is not to be taken as universal with regard to
				   individuals, but kinds; as such universal terms are often used in
				   Scripture. When John preached, there was an extraordinary pouring out
				   of the Spirit of God that attended his preaching. An uncommon
				   awakening, and concern for salvation, appeared on the minds of all
				   sorts of persons; and even in the most unlikely persons, and those from
				   whom such a thing might least be expected; as the Pharisees, who were
				   exceeding proud, and self-sufficient, and conceited of their own wisdom
				   and righteousness, and looked on themselves fit to be teachers of
				   others, and used to scorn to be taught; and the Sadducees, who were a
				   kind of infidels, that denied any resurrection, angel, spirit, or any
				   future state. So that John himself seems to be surprised to see them
				   come to him, under such concern for their salvation; as in Matthew 3:7.
				   "But when he saw many of the Pharisees come to his baptism, he said to
				   them, O generation of vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the
				   wrath to come?" And besides these, the publicans, who were some of the
				   most infamous sort of men, came to him, inquiring what they should do
				   to be saved. And the soldiers, who were doubtless a very profane,
				   loose, and prolifigate sort of persons, made the same inquiry, Luke
				   3:12, and 14. "Then came also publicans to be baptized, and said unto
				   him, Master, what shall we do? And the soldiers likewise demanded of
				   him, saying, And what shall we do?
				
				   2. His success appeared in the manner in which his hearers sought the
				   kingdom of God; they pressed into it. It is elsewhere set forth by
				   their being violent for the kingdom of heaven, and taking it by force.
				   Matthew 11:12. "From the days of John the Baptist until now, the
				   kingdom of heaven suffers violence, and the violent take it by force."
				
				   The Doctrine that I observe from the words is this,- "It concerns every
				   one that would obtain the kingdom of God, to be pressing into it." -In
				   discoursing of this subject, I would,
				
				   First, Show what is that way of seeking salvation that seems to be
				   pointed forth in the expression of pressing into the kingdom of God.
				
				   Secondly, Give the reasons why it concerns every one that would obtain
				   the kingdom of God, to seek it in this way.- And then make application.
				
				   I. I would show what manner of seeking salvation seems to be denoted by
				   "pressing into the kingdom of God."
				
				   1. This expression denotes strength of desire. Men in general who live
				   under the light of the gospel, and are not atheists, desire the kingdom
				   of God; that is, they desire to go to heaven rather than to hell. Most
				   of them indeed are not much concerned about it; but on the contrary,
				   live a secure and careless life. And some who are many degrees above
				   these, being under some degrees of the awakenings of God's Spirit, yet
				   are not pressing into the kingdom of God. But they that may be said to
				   be truly so, have strong desires to get out of a natural condition, and
				   to get an interest in Christ. They have such a conviction of the misery
				   of their present state, and of the extreme necessity of obtaining a
				   better, that their minds are as it were possessed with and wrapped up
				   in concern about it.
				
				   To obtain salvation is desired by them above all things in the world.
				   This concern is so great that it very much shuts out other concerns.
				   They used before to have the stream of their desires after other
				   things, or, it may be, had their concern divided between this and them;
				   but when they come to answer the expression of the text, of pressing
				   into the kingdom of God, this concern prevails above all others; it
				   lays other things low, and does in a manner engross the care of the
				   mind. This seeking eternal life should not only be one concern that our
				   souls are taken up about with other things; but salvation should be
				   sought as the one thing needful, Luke 10:42. And as the one thing that
				   is desired, Psalm 27:4.
				
				   2. Pressing into the kingdom of heaven denotes earnestness and firmness
				   of resolution. There should be strength of resolution, accompanying
				   strength of desire, as it was in the psalmist, in the place just now
				   referred to: "one thing have I desired, and that will I seek after." In
				   order to a thorough engagedness of the mind in this affair, both these
				   must meet together. Besides desires after salvation, there should be an
				   earnest resolution in persons to pursue this good as much as lies in
				   their power; to do all that in the use of their utmost strength they
				   are able to do, in an attendance on every duty, and resisting and
				   militating against all manner of sin, and to continue in such a
				   pursuit.
				
				   There are two things needful in a person, in order to these strong
				   resolutions; there must be a sense of the great importance and
				   necessity of the mercy sought, and there must also be a sense of
				   opportunity to obtain it, or the encouragement there is to seek it. The
				   strength of resolution depends on the sense which God gives to the
				   heart of these things. Persons without such a sense, may seem to
				   themselves to take up resolutions; they may, as it were, force a
				   promise to themselves, and say within themselves, "I will seek as long
				   as I live, I will not give up till I obtain," when they do but deceive
				   themselves. Their hearts are not in it; neither do they indeed take up
				   any such resolution as they seem to themselves to do. It is the
				   resolution of the mouth more than of the heart; their hearts are not
				   strongly bent to fulfill what their mouth says. The firmness of the
				   resolution lies in the fulness of the disposition of the heart to do
				   what is resolved to be done. Those who are pressing into the kingdom of
				   God, have a disposition of heart to do everything that is required, and
				   that lies in their power to do, and to continue in it. They have not
				   only earnestness, but steadiness of resolution: they do not seek with a
				   wavering unsteady heart, by turns or fits, being off and on; but it is
				   the constant bent of the soul, if possible, to obtain the kingdom of
				   God.
				
				   3. By pressing into the kingdom of God is signified greatness of
				   endeavor. It is expressed in Ecclesiastes 10:10. by doing what our hand
				   finds to do with our might. And this is the natural and necessary
				   consequence of the two forementioned things. Where there is strength of
				   desire, and firmness of resolution, there will be answerable endeavors.
				   Persons thus engaged in their hearts will "strive to enter in at the
				   strait gate," and will be violent for heaven; their practice will be
				   agreeable to the counsel of the wise man, in Proverbs 2 at the
				   beginning, "My son, if thou wilt receive my words, and hide my
				   commandments with thee; so that thou incline thine ear unto wisdom, and
				   apply thine heart to understanding; yea, if thou criest after
				   knowledge, and liftest up thy voice for understanding; if thou seekest
				   her as silver, and searchest for her as for hid treasures; then shalt
				   thou understand the fear of the Lord, and find the knowledge of God."
				   Here the earnestness of desire and strength of resolution is signified
				   by inclining the ear to wisdom, and applying the heart to
				   understanding; and the greatness of endeavor is denoted by crying after
				   knowledge, and lifting up the voice for understanding; seeking her as
				   silver, and searching for her as for hid treasures: such desires and
				   resolutions, and such endeavors go together.
				
				   4. Pressing into the kingdom of God denotes an engagedness and
				   earnestness, that is directly about that business of getting into the
				   kingdom of God. Persons may be in very great exercise and distress of
				   mind, and that about the condition of their souls; their thoughts and
				   cares may be greatly engaged and taken up about things of a spiritual
				   nature, and yet not be pressing into the kingdom of God, nor towards
				   it. The exercise of their minds is not directly about the work of
				   seeking salvation, in a diligent attendance on the means that God hath
				   appointed in order to it, but something else that is beside their
				   business; it may be God's decrees and secret purposes, prying into
				   them, searching for signs whereby they may determine, or at least
				   conjecture, what they are before God makes them known by their
				   accomplishment. They distress their minds with fears that they be not
				   elected, or that they have committed the unpardonable sin, or that
				   their day is past, and that God has given them up to judicial and final
				   hardness, and never intends to show them mercy; and therefore, that it
				   is in vain for them to seek salvation. Or they entangle themselves
				   about the doctrine of original sin, and other mysterious doctrines of
				   religion that are above their comprehension.
				
				   Many persons that seem to be in great distress about a future eternal
				   state, get much into a way of perplexing themselves with such things as
				   these. When it is so, let them be never so much concerned and engaged
				   in their minds, they cannot be said to be pressing towards the kingdom
				   of God: because their exercise is not in their work, but rather that
				   which tends to hinder them in their work. If they are violent, they are
				   only working violently to entangle themselves, and lay blocks in their
				   own way; their pressure is not forwards. Instead of getting along, they
				   do but lose their time, and worse than merely lose it; instead of
				   fighting with the giants that stand in the way to keep them out of
				   Canaan, they spend away their time and strength in conflicting with
				   shadows that appear by the wayside.
				
				   Hence we are not to judge of the hopefulness of the way that persons
				   are in, or of the probability of their success in seeking salvation,
				   only by the greatness of the concern and distress that they are in; for
				   many persons have needless distresses that they had much better be
				   without. It is thus very often with persons overrun with the distemper
				   of melancholy: whence the adversary of souls is wont to take great
				   advantage. But then are persons in the most likely way to obtain the
				   kingdom of heaven, when the intent of their minds, and the engagedness
				   of their spirits, be about their proper work and business, and all the
				   bent of their souls is to attend on God's means, and to do what he
				   commands and directs them to. The apostle tells us, I Corinthians 9:26.
				   "that he did not fight as those that beat the air." Our time is short
				   enough; we had not need to spend it in that which is nothing to the
				   purpose. There are real difficulties and enemies enough for persons to
				   encounter, to employ all their strength; they had not need to waste it
				   in fighting with phantoms.
				
				   5. By pressing into the kingdom of God is denoted a breaking through
				   opposition and difficulties. There is in the expression a plain
				   intimation of difficulty. If there were no opposition, but the way was
				   all clear and open, there would be no need of pressing to get along.
				   They therefore that are pressing into the kingdom of God, go on with
				   such engagedness, that they break through the difficulties that are in
				   the way. They are so set for salvation, that those things by which
				   others are discouraged, and stopped, and turned back, do not stop them,
				   but they press through them. Persons ought to be so resolved for
				   heaven, that if by any means they can obtain, they will obtain. Whether
				   those means be difficult or easy, cross or agreeable, if they are
				   requisite means of salvation, they should be complied with. When
				   anything is presented to be done, the question should not be, Is it
				   easy or hard? is it agreeable to my carnal inclinations or interest, or
				   against them? But is it a required means of my obtaining an interest in
				   Jesus Christ, and eternal salvation? Thus the apostle, Philippians
				   3:11. "If by any means I might attain unto the resurrection of the
				   dead." He tells us there in the context what difficulties he broke
				   through, that he suffered the loss of all things, and was willingly
				   made conformable even to Christ's death, though that was attended with
				   such extreme torment and ignominy.
				
				   He that is pressing into the kingdom of God, commonly finds many things
				   in the way that are against the grain; but he is not stopped by the
				   cross that lies before him, but takes it up, and carries it. Suppose
				   there be something incumbent on him to do, that is cross to his natural
				   temper, and irksome to him on that account; suppose something that he
				   cannot do without suffering in his estate, or that he apprehends will
				   look odd and strange in the eyes of others, and expose him to ridicule
				   and reproach, or any thing that will offend a neighbor, and get his
				   ill-will, or something that will be very cross to his own carnal
				   appetite-he will press through such difficulties. Everything that is
				   found to be a weight that hinders him in running this race he casts
				   from him, though it be a weight of gold or pearls; yea, if it be a
				   right hand or foot that offends him, he will cut them off, and will not
				   stick at plucking out a right eye with his own hands. These things are
				   insuperable difficulties to those who are not thoroughly engaged in
				   seeking their salvation; they are stumbling-blocks that they never get
				   over. But it is not so with him that presses into the kingdom of God.
				   Those things (before he was thoroughly roused from his security) about
				   which he was wont to have long parleyings and disputings with his own
				   conscience-employing carnal reason to invent arguments and pleas of
				   excuse-he now sticks at no longer; he has done with this endless
				   disputing and reasoning, and presses violently through all
				   difficulties.
				
				   Let what will be in the way, heaven is what he must and will obtain,
				   not if he can without difficulty, but if it be possible. He meets with
				   temptation: the devil is often whispering in his ear, setting
				   allurements before him, magnifying the difficulties of the work he is
				   engaged in, telling him that they are insuperable, and that he can
				   never conquer them, and trying all ways in the world to discourage him;
				   but still he presses forward. God has given and maintains such an
				   earnest spirit for heaven, that the devil cannot stop him in his
				   course; he is not at leasure to lend an ear to what he has to say.-I
				   come now,
				    1. To show why the kingdom of heaven should be sought in this
				       manner.-It should be thus sought,
				
				   1. On account of the extreme necessity we are in of getting into the
				   kingdom of heaven. We are in a perishing necessity of it; without it we
				   are utterly and eternally lost. Out of the kingdom of God is no safety;
				   there is no other hiding-place; this is the only city of refuge, in
				   which we can be secure from the avenger that pursues all the ungodly.
				   The vengeance of God will pursue, overtake, and eternally destroy, them
				   that are not in this kingdom. All that are without this enclosure will
				   be swallowed up in an overflowing fiery deluge of wrath. They may stand
				   at the door and knock, and cry, Lord, Lord, open to us, in vain; they
				   will be thrust back; and God will have no mercy on them; they shall be
				   eternally left of him. His fearful vengence will seize them; the devils
				   will lay hold of them; and all evil will come upon them; and there will
				   be none to pity or help; their case will be utterly desperate, and
				   infinitely doleful. It will be a gone case with them; all offers of
				   mercy and expressions of divine goodness will be finally withdrawn, and
				   all hope will be lost. God will have no kind of regard to their
				   well-being; will take no care of them to save them from any enemy, or
				   any evil; but himself will be their dreadful enemy, and will execute
				   wrath with fury, and will take vengeance in an inexpressibly dreadful
				   manner. Such as shall be in this case will be lost and undone indeed!
				   They will be sunk down into perdition, infinitely below all that we can
				   think. For who knows the power of God's anger? And who knows the misery
				   of that poor worm, on whom that anger is executed without mercy?
				
				   2. On account of the shortness and uncertainty of the opportunity for
				   getting into this kingdom. When a few days are past, all our
				   opportunity for it will be gone. Our day is limited. God has set our
				   bounds, and we know not where. While persons are out of this kingdom,
				   they are in danger every hour of being overtaken with wrath. We know
				   not how soon we shall get past that line, beyond which there is no
				   work, device, knowledge, nor wisdom; and therefore we should do what we
				   have to do with our might, Ecclesiastes 9:10.
				
				   3. On account of the difficulty of getting into the kingdom of God.
				   There are innumerable difficulties in the way; such as few conquer:
				   most of them that try have not resolution, courage, earnestness, and
				   constancy enough; but they fail, give up, and perish. The difficulties
				   are too many and too great for them that do not violently press
				   forward. They never get along, but stick by the way; are turned aside,
				   or turned back, and ruined. Matthew 7:14. "Strait is the gate, and
				   narrow is the way, which leadeth unto life, and few there be that find
				   it." Luke 13:24. "Strive to enter in at the strait gate; for many, I
				   say unto you, will seek to enter in, and shall not be able."
				
				   4. The possibility of obtaining. Though it be attended with so much
				   difficulty, yet it is not a thing impossible. Acts 8:22. "If perhaps
				   the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee." II Timothy 2:25. "If
				   peradventure God will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the
				   truth." However sinful a person is, and whatever his circumstances are,
				   there is, notwithstanding, a possibility of his salvation. He himself
				   is capable of it, and God is able to accomplish it, and has mercy
				   sufficient for it; and there is sufficient provision made through
				   Christ, that God may do it consistent with the honour of his majesty,
				   justice, and truth. So that there is no want either of sufficiency in
				   God, or capacity in the sinner, in order to this. The greatest and
				   vilest most blind, dead, hard-hearted sinner living, is a subject
				   capable of saving light and grace. Seeing therefore there is such a
				   necessity of obtaining the kingdom of God, and so short a time, and
				   such difficulty, and yet such a possibility, it may well induce us to
				   press into it. Jonah 3:8, 9.
				
				   5. It is meet that the kingdom of heaven should be thus sought, because
				   of the great excellency of it. We are willing to seek earthly things,
				   of trifling value, with great diligence, and through much difficulty;
				   it therefore certainly becomes us to seek that with great earnestness
				   which is of infinitely greater worth and excellence. And how well may
				   God expect and require it of us, that we should seek it in such a
				   manner, in order to our obtaining it!
				
				   6. Such a manner of seeking is needful to prepare persons for the
				   kingdom of God. Such earnestness and thoroughness of endeavors, is the
				   ordinary means that God makes use of to bring persons to an
				   acquaintance with themselves, to a sight of their own hearts, to a
				   sense of their own helplessness, and to a despair in their own strength
				   and righteousness. And such engagedness and constancy in seeking the
				   kingdom of heaven, prepare the soul to receive it the more joyfully and
				   thankfully, and the more highly to prize and value it when obtained. So
				   that it is in mercy to us, as well as for the glory of his own name,
				   that God has appointed such earnest seeking, to be the way in which he
				   will bestow the kingdom of heaven.
				
				  APPLICATION
				
				   The use I would make of this doctrine, is of exhortation to all
				   Christless persons to press into the kingdom of God. Some of you are
				   inquiring what you shall do? You seem to desire to know what is the way
				   wherein salvation is to be sought, and how you may be likely to obtain
				   it. You have now heard the way that the holy word of God directs to.
				   Some are seeking, but it cannot be said of them that they are pressing
				   into the kingdom of heaven. There are many that in time past have
				   sought salvation, but not in this manner, and so they never obtained,
				   but are now gone to hell. Some of them sought it year after year, but
				   failed of it, and perished at last. They were overtaken with divine
				   wrath, and are now suffering the fearful misery of damnation, and have
				   no rest day nor night, having no more opportunity to seek, but must
				   suffer and be miserable throughout the never-ending ages of eternity.
				   Be exhorted, therefore, not to seek salvation as they did, but let the
				   kingdom of heaven suffer violence from you.
				
				   Here I would first answer an objection or two, and then proceed to give
				   some directions how to press into the kingdom of God.
				
				   Objection. 1. Some may be ready to say, We cannot do this of ourselves;
				   that strength of desire, and firmness of resolution, that have been
				   spoken of, are out of our reach. If I endeavor to resolve and to seek
				   with engagedness of spirit, I find I fail; my thoughts are presently
				   off from the business, and I feel myself dull, and my engagedness
				   relaxed, in spite of all I can do.
				
				   Answer. 1. Though earnestness of mind be not immediately in your power,
				   yet the consideration of what has been now said of the need of it, may
				   be a means of stirring you up to it. It is true, persons never will be
				   thoroughly engaged in this business, unless it be by God's influence;
				   but God influences persons by means. Persons are not stirred up to a
				   thorough earnestness without some considerations that move them to it.
				   And if persons can but be made sensible of the necessity of salvation,
				   and also duly consider the exceeding difficuly of it, and the greatness
				   of the opposition, and how short and uncertain the time is, but yet are
				   sensible that they have an opportunity, and that there is a possibility
				   of their obtaining, they will need no more in order to their being
				   thoroughly engaged and resolved in this matter. If we see persons slack
				   and unresolved, and unsteady, it is because they do not enough consider
				   these things.
				
				   2. Though strong desires and resolutions of mind be not in your power,
				   yet painfulness of endeavors is in your power. It is in your power to
				   take pains in the use of means, yea very great pains. You can be very
				   painful and diligent in watching your own heart, and striving against
				   sin. Though there is all manner of corruption in the heart continually
				   ready to work, yet you can very laboriously watch and strive against
				   these corruptions; and it is in your power, with great diligence to
				   attend the matter of your duty towards God and towards your neighbour.
				   It is in your power to attend all ordinances, and all public and
				   private duties of religion, and to do it with your might. It would be a
				   contradiction to suppose that a man cannot do these things with all the
				   might he has, though he cannot do them with more might than he has. The
				   dullness and deadness of the heart, and slothfulness of disposition, do
				   not hinder men being able to take pains, though it hinders their being
				   willing. That is one thing wherein your laboriousness may appear, even
				   striving against your own dullness. That men have a dead and sluggish
				   heart, does not argue that they be not able to take pains; it is so far
				   from that, that it gives occasion for pains. It is one of the
				   difficulties in the way of duty, that persons have to strive with, and
				   that gives occasion for struggling and labour. If there were no
				   difficulties attended seeking salvation, there would be no occasion for
				   striving; a man would have nothing to strive about. There is indeed a
				   great deal of difficulty attending all duties required of those that
				   would obtain heaven. It is an exceeding difficult thing for them to
				   keep their thoughts; it is a difficult thing seriously, or to any good
				   purpose, to consider matters of greatest importance; it is a difficult
				   thing to hear, or read, or pray attentively. But it does not argue that
				   a man cannot strive in these things because they are difficult; nay, he
				   could not strive therein if there were not difficulty in them. For what
				   is there excepting difficulties that any can have to strive or struggle
				   with in any affair or business? Earnestness of mind, and diligence of
				   endeavor, tend to promote each other. He that has a heart earnestly
				   engaged, will take pains; and he that is diligent and painful in all
				   duty, probably will not be so long before he finds the sensibleness of
				   his heart and earnestness of his spirit greatly increased.
				
				   Objection 2. Some may object, that if they are earnest, and take a
				   great deal of pains, they shall be in danger of trusting to what they
				   do; they are afraid of doing their duty for fear of making a
				   righteousness of it.
				
				   Answer. There is ordinarily no kind of seekers that trust so much to
				   what they do, as slack and dull seekers. Though all seeking salvation,
				   that have never been the subjects of a thorough humiliation, do trust
				   in their own righteousness; yet some do it much more fully than others.
				   Some though they trust in their own righteousness, yet are not quiet in
				   it. And those who are most disturbed in their self-confidence, (and
				   therefore in the likeliest way to be wholly brought off from it,) are
				   not such as go on in a remiss way of seeking, but such as are most
				   earnest and thoroughly engaged; partly because in such a way conscience
				   is kept more sensible. A more awakened conscience will not rest so
				   quietly in moral and religious duties, as one that is less awakened. A
				   dull seeker's conscience will be in a great measure satisfied and
				   quieted with his own works and performances; but one that is thoroughly
				   awakened cannot be stilled or pacified with such things as these. In
				   this way persons gain much more knowledge of themselves, and
				   acquaintance with their own hearts, than in a negligent, slight way of
				   seeking; for they have a great deal more experience of themselves. It
				   is experience of ourselves, and finding what we are, that God commonly
				   makes use of as the means of bringing us off from all dependence on
				   ourselves. But men never get acquaintance with themselves so fast, as
				   in the most earnest way of seeking. They that are in this way have more
				   to engage them to think of their sins, and strictly to observe
				   themselves, and have much more to do with their own hearts, than
				   others. Such a one has much more experience of his own weakness, than
				   another that does not put forth and try his strength; and will
				   therefore sooner see himself dead in sin. Such a one, though he hath a
				   disposition continually to be flying to his own righteousness, yet
				   finds rest in nothing; he wanders about from one thing to another,
				   seeking something to ease his disquieted conscience; he is driven from
				   one refuge to another, goes from mountain to hill, seeking rest and
				   finding none; and therefore will the sooner prove that there is no rest
				   to be found, nor trust to be put, in any creature whatsoever.
				
				   It is therefore quite a wrong notion that some entertain, that the more
				   they do, the more they shall depend on it. Whereas the reverse is true;
				   the more they do, or the more thorough they are in seeking, the less
				   will they be likely to rest in their doings, and the sooner will they
				   see the vanity of all that they do. So that persons will exceedingly
				   miss it, if ever they neglect to do any duty either to God or man,
				   whether it be any duty of religion, justice, or charity, under a notion
				   of its exposing them to trust in their own righteousness. It is very
				   true, that it is a common thing for persons, when they earnestly seek
				   salvation, to trust in the pains that they take: but yet commonly those
				   that go on in a more slight way, trust a great deal more securely to
				   their dull services, than he that is pressing into the kingdom of God
				   does to his earnestness. Men's slackness in religion, and their trust
				   in their own righteousness, strengthen and establish one another. Their
				   trust in what they have done, and what they now do, settles them in a
				   slothful rest and ease, and hinders their being sensible of their need
				   of rousing up themselves and pressing forward. And on the other hand,
				   their negligence tends so to benumb them in such ignorance of
				   themselves, that the most miserable refuges are stupidly rested in as
				   sufficient. Therefore we see, that when persons have been going on for
				   a long time in such a way, and God afterwards comes more thoroughly to
				   awaken them, and to stir them up to be in good earnest, he shakes all
				   their old foundations, and rouses them out of their old resting places;
				   so that they cannot quiet themselves with those things that formerly
				   kept them secure. I would now proceed to give some directions how you
				   should press into the kingdom of God.
				
				   1. Be directed to sacrifice every thing to your soul's eternal
				   interest. Let seeking this be so much your bent, and what you are so
				   resolved in, that you will make every thing give place to it. Let
				   nothing stand before your resolution of seeking the kingdom of God.
				   Whatever it be that you used to look upon as a convenience, or comfort,
				   or ease, or thing desirable on any account, if it stands in the way of
				   this great concern, let it be dismissed without hesitation; and if it
				   be of that nature that it is likely always to be a hinderance, then
				   wholly have done with it, and never entertain any expectation from it
				   more. If in time past you have, for the sake of worldly gain, involved
				   yourself in more care and business than you find to be consistent with
				   your being so thorough in the business of religion as you ought to be,
				   then get into some other way, though you suffer in your worldly
				   interest by it. Or if you have heretofore been conversant with company
				   that you have reason to think have been and will be a snare to you, and
				   a hinderance to this great design in any wise, break off from their
				   society, however it may expose you to reproach from your old
				   companions, or let what will be the effect of it. Whatever it be that
				   stands in the way of your most advantageously seeking salvation-whether
				   it be some dear sinful pleasure, or strong carnal appetite, or credit
				   and honour, or the good-will of some persons whose friendship you
				   desire, and whose esteem and liking you have highly valued-and though
				   there be danger, if you do as you ought, that you shall looked upon by
				   them as odd and ridiculous, and become contemptible in their eyes-or if
				   it be your ease and indolence and aversion to continual labour; or your
				   outward convenience in any respect, whereby you might avoid
				   difficulties of one kind or other-let all go; offer up all such things
				   together, as it were, in one sacrifice, to the interest of your soul.
				   Let nothing stand in competition with this, but make every thing to
				   fall before it. If the flesh must be crossed, then cross it, spare it
				   not, crucify it, and do not be afraid of being too cruel to it.
				   Galatians 5:24. "They that are Christ's have crucified the flesh, with
				   the affections and lusts." Have no dependence on any worldly enjoyment
				   whatsoever. Let salvation be the one thing with you. This is what is
				   certainly required of you: and this is what many stick at; this giving
				   up other things for salvation, is a stumbling-block that few get over.
				   While others pressed into the kingdom of God at the preaching of John
				   the Baptist, Herod was pretty much stirred up by his preaching. It is
				   said, he heard him, and observed him, and did many things; but when he
				   came to tell him that he must part with his beloved Herodias, here he
				   stuck; this he never would yield to, Mark 7:18-20. The rich young man
				   was considerably concerned for salvation; and accordingly was a very
				   strict liver in many things: but when Christ came to direct him to go
				   and sell all that he had, and give to the poor, and come and follow
				   him, he could not find in his heart to comply with it, but went away
				   sorrowful. He had great possessions, and set his heart much on his
				   estate, and could not bear to part with it. It may be, if Christ had
				   directed him only to give away a considerable part of his estate, he
				   would have done it; yea, perhaps, if he had bid him part with half of
				   it, he would have complied with it: but when he directed him to throw
				   up all, he could not grapple with such a proposal. Herein the
				   straitness of the gate very much consists; and it is on this account
				   that so many seek to enter in, and are not able. There are many that
				   have a great mind to salvation, and spend great part of their time in
				   wishing they had it, but they will not comply with the necessary means.
				
				   2. Be directed to forget the things that are behind: that is, not to
				   keep thinking and making much of what you have done, but let your mind
				   be wholly intent on what you have to do. In some sense you ought to
				   look back; you should look back to your sins. Jeremiah 2:23. "See thy
				   way in the valley, know what thou hast done." You should look back on
				   the wretchedness of your religious performances, and consider how you
				   have fallen short in them; how exceedingly polluted all your duties
				   have been, and how justly God might reject and loathe them, and you for
				   them. But you ought not to spend your time in looking back, as many
				   persons do, thinking how much they have done for their salvation; what
				   great pains they have taken, how that they have done what they can, and
				   do not see how they can do more; how long a time they have been
				   seeking, and how much more they have done than others, and even than
				   such and such who have obtained mercy. They think with themselves how
				   hardly God deals with them, that he does not extend mercy to them, but
				   turns a deaf ear to their cries; and hence discourage themselves, and
				   complain of God. Do not thus spend your time in looking back on what is
				   past, but look forward, and consider what is before you; consider what
				   it is that you can do, and what it is necessary that you should do, and
				   what God calls you still to do, in order to your own salvation. The
				   apostle, in the third chapter to the Philippians, tells us what things
				   he did while a Jew, how much he had to boast of, if any could boast;
				   but he tells us, that he forgot those things, and all other things that
				   were behind, and reached forth towards the things that were before,
				   pressing forwards towards the mark for the prize of the high calling of
				   God in Christ Jesus.
				
				   3. Labour to get your heart thoroughly disposed to go on and hold out
				   to the end. Many that seem to be earnest have not a heart thus
				   disposed. It is a common thing for persons to appear greatly affected
				   for a little while; but all is soon past away, and there is no more to
				   be seen of it. Labour therefore to obtain a thorough willingness and
				   preparation of spirit, to continue seeking, in the use of your utmost
				   endeavours, without limitation; and do not think your whole life too
				   long. And in order to this, be advised to two things,
				
				   (1.) Remember that if ever God bestows mercy upon you, he will use his
				   sovereign pleasure about the time when. He will bestow it on some in a
				   little time, and on others not till they have sought it long. If other
				   persons are soon enlightened and comforted, while you remain long in
				   darkness, there is no other way but for you to wait. God will act
				   arbitrarily in this matter, and you cannot help it. You must even be
				   content to wait, in a way of laborious and earnest striving, till his
				   time comes. If you refuse, you will but undo yourself; and when you
				   shall hereafter find yourself undone, and see that your case is past
				   remedy, how will you condemn yourself for foregoing a great probability
				   of salvation, only because you had not the patience to hold out, and
				   was not willing to be at the trouble of a persevering labour! And what
				   will it avail before God or your own conscience to say, that you could
				   not bear to be obliged to seek salvation so long, when God bestowed it
				   on others that sought it but for a very short time? Though God may have
				   bestowed the testimonies of his favour on others in a few days or hours
				   after they have begun earnestly to seek it, how does that alter the
				   case as to you, if there proves to be a necessity of your laboriously
				   seeking many years before you obtain them? Is salvation less worth
				   taking a great deal of pains for, because, through the sovereign
				   pleasure of God, others have obtained it with comparatively little
				   pains? If there are two persons, the one of which has obtained
				   converting grace with comparative ease, and another that has obtained
				   it after continuing for many years in the greatest and most earnest
				   labours after it, how little difference does it make at last, when once
				   salvation is obtained! Put all the labour and pains, the long-continued
				   difficulties and strugglings, of the one in the scale against
				   salvation, and how little does it subtract; and put the ease with which
				   the other has obtained in the scale with salvation, and how little does
				   it add! What is either added or subtracted is lighter than vanity, and
				   a thing worthy of no consideration, when compared with that infinite
				   benefit that is obtained. Indeed if you were ten thousand years, and
				   all that time should strive and press forward with as great earnestness
				   as ever a person did for one day, all this would bear no proportion to
				   the importance of the benefit; and it will doubtless appear little to
				   you, when once you come to be in actual possession of eternal glory,
				   and to see what that eternal misery is which you have escaped. You must
				   not think much of your pains, and of the length of time; you must press
				   towards the kingdom of God, and do your utmost, and hold out to the
				   end, and learn to make no account of it when you have done. You must
				   undertake the business of seeking salvation upon these terms, and with
				   no other expectations than this, that if ever God bestows mercy it will
				   be in his own time; and not only so, but also that when you have done
				   all, God will not hold himself obliged to show you mercy at last.
				
				   (2.) Endeavour now thoroughly to weigh in your mind the difficulty, and
				   to count the cost of perseverence in seeking salvation. You that are
				   now setting out in this business, (as there are many here who have very
				   lately set about it;-Praised be the name of God that he has stirred you
				   up to it!) be exhorted to attend this direction. Do not undertake in
				   this affair with any other thought but of giving yourself wholly to it
				   for the remaining part of your life, and going through many and great
				   difficulties in it. Take heed that you do not engage secretly upon this
				   condition, that you shall obtain in a little time, promising yourself
				   that it shall be within this present season of the pouring out of God's
				   Spirit, or with any other limitation of time whatsoever. Many, when
				   they begin, (seeming to set out very earnestly,) do not expect that
				   they shall need to seek very long, and so do not prepare themselves for
				   it. And therefore, when they come to find it otherwise, and meet with
				   unexpected difficulty, they are found unguarded, and easily overthrown.
				   But let me advise you all who are now seeking salvation, not to
				   entertain any self-flattering thoughts; but weigh the utmost
				   difficulties of perseverance, and be provided for them, having your
				   mind fixed in it to go through them, let them be what they will.
				   Consider now beforehand, how tedious it would be, with utmost
				   earnestness and labour, to strive after salvation for many years, in
				   the mean time receiving no joyful or comfortable evidence of your
				   having obtained. Consider what a great temptation to discouragement
				   there probably would be in it; how apt you would be to yield the case;
				   how ready to think that it is in vain for you to seek any longer, and
				   that God never intends to show you mercy, in that he has not yet done
				   it; how apt you would be to think with yourself, "What an uncomfortable
				   life do I live! How much more unpleasantly do I spend my time than
				   others that do not perplex their minds about the things of another
				   world, but are at ease, and take the comfort of their worldly
				   enjoyments!" Consider what a temptation there would probably be in it,
				   if you saw others brought in that began to seek the kingdom of heaven
				   long after you, rejoicing in a hope and sense of God's favour, after
				   but little pains and a short time of awakening; while you, from day to
				   day, and from year to year, seemed to labour in vain. Prepare for such
				   tempations now. Lay in beforehand for such trials and difficulties,
				   that you may not think any strange thing has happened when they come.
				
				   I hope that those who have given attention to what has been said, have
				   by this time conceived, in some measure, what is signified by the
				   expression in the text, and after what manner they ought to press into
				   the kingdom of God. Here is this to induce you to a compliance with
				   what you have been directed to; if you sit still, you die; if you go
				   backward, behold you shall surely die; if you go forward, you may live.
				   And though God has not bound himself to any thing that a person does
				   while destitute of faith, and out of Christ, yet there is great
				   probability, that in a way of hearkening to this counsel you will live;
				   and that by pressing onward, and persevering, you will at last, as it
				   were by violence, take the kingdom of heaven. Those of you who have not
				   only heard the directions given, but shall through God's merciful
				   assistance, practise according to them, are those that probably will
				   overcome. These we may well hope at last to see standing with the Lamb
				   on mount Sion, clothed in white robes, with palms in their hands; when
				   all your labour and toil will be abundantly compensated, and you will
				   not repent that you have taken so much pains, and denied yourself much,
				   and waited so long. This self-denial, this waiting, will then look
				   little, and vanish into nothing in your eyes, being all swallowed up in
				   the first minute's enjoyment of that glory that you will then possess,
				   and will uninterruptedly possess and enjoy to all eternity.
				
				   4th Direction. Improve the present season of the pouring out of the
				   Spirit of God on this town. Prudence is any affair whatsoever consists
				   very much in minding and improving our opportunities. If you would have
				   spiritual prosperity, you must exercise prudence in the concerns of
				   your souls, as well as in outward concerns when you seek outward
				   prosperity. The prudent husbandman will observe his opportunities; he
				   will improve seed-time and harvest; he will make his advantage of the
				   showers and shines of heaven. The prudent merchant will discern his
				   opportunities; he will not be idle on a market-day; he is careful not
				   to let slip his seasons for enriching himself: So will those who
				   prudently seek the fruits of righteousness, and the merchandise of
				   wisdom, improve their opportunities for their eternal wealth and
				   happiness.
				
				   God is pleased at this time, in a very remarkable manner, to pour out
				   his Spirit amongst us; (glory be to his name!) You that have a mind to
				   obtain converting grace, and to go to heaven when you die, now is your
				   season! Now, if you have any sort of prudence for your own salvation,
				   and have not a mind to go to hell, improve this season! Now is the
				   accepted time! Now is the day of salvation! You that in time past have
				   been called upon, and have turned a deaf ear to God's voice, and long
				   stood out and resisted his commands and counsels, hear God's voice
				   today, while it is called today! Do not harden your hearts at such a
				   day as this! Now you have a special and remarkable price put into your
				   hands to get wisdom, if you have but a heart to improve it.
				
				   God hath his certain days or appointed seasons of exercising both mercy
				   and judgment. There are some remarkable times of wrath, laid out by God
				   for his awful visitation, and the executions of his anger; which times
				   are called days of vengeance, Proverbs 6:34. Wherein God will visit
				   sin, Exodus 32:34. And so, on the contrary, God has laid out in his
				   sovereign counsels seasons of remarkable mercy, wherein he will
				   manifest himself in the exercises of his grace and loving-kindness,
				   more than at other times. Such times in Scripture are called by way of
				   eminency, accepted times, and days of salvation, and also days of God's
				   visitation; because they are days wherein God will visit in a way of
				   mercy; as in Luke 19:44. "And shall lay thee even with the ground, and
				   thy children within thee; and they shall not leave in thee one stone
				   upon another; because thou knewest not the time of thy visitation." It
				   is such a time now in this town; it is with us a day of God's gracious
				   visitation. It is indeed a day of grace with us as long as we live in
				   this world, in the enjoyment of the means of grace; but such a time as
				   this is especially, and in a distinguishing manner, a day of grace.
				   There is a door of mercy always standing open for sinners; but such a
				   day as this, God opens an extraordinary door.
				
				   We are directed to seek the Lord while he may be found, and to call
				   upon him while he is near, Isaiah 55:6. If you that are hitherto
				   Christless, be not strangely besotted and infatuated, you will by all
				   means improve such an opportunity as this to get heaven, when heaven is
				   brought so near, when the fountain is opened in the midst of us in so
				   extraordinary a manner. Now is the time to obtain a supply of the
				   necessities of your poor perishing souls! This is the day for sinners
				   that have a mind to be converted before they die, when God is dealing
				   forth so liberally and bountifully amongst us; when conversion and
				   salvation work is going on amongst us from sabbath to sabbath, and many
				   are pressing into the kingdom of God! Now do not stay behind, but press
				   in amongst the rest! Others have been stirred up to be in good earnest,
				   and have taken heaven by violence; be entreated to follow their
				   example, if you would have a part of the inheritance with them, and
				   would not be left at the great day, when they are taken!
				
				   How should it move you to consider that you have this opportunity now
				   in your hands! You are in the actual possession of it! If it were past,
				   it would not be in your power to recover it, or in the power of any
				   creature to bring it back for you; but it is not past; it is now, at
				   this day. Now is the accepted time, even while it is called today! Will
				   you sit still at such a time? Will you sleep in such a harvest? Will
				   you deal with a slack hand, and stay behind out of mere sloth, or love
				   to some lust, or lothness to grapple with some small difficulty, or to
				   put yourself a little out of your way, when so many are flowing to the
				   goodness of the Lord? You are behind still; and so you will be in
				   danger of being left behind, when the whole number is completed that
				   are to enter in, if you do not earnestly bestir yourself! To be left
				   behind at the close of such a season as this, will be awful-next to
				   being left behind on that day when God's saints shall mount up as with
				   wings to meet the Lord in the air-and will be what will appear very
				   threatening of it.
				
				   God is now calling you in an extraordinary manner: and it is agreeable
				   to the will and word of Christ, that I should now, in his name, call
				   you, as one set over you, and sent to you to that end; so it is his
				   will that you should hearken to what I say, as his voice. I therefore
				   beseech you in Christ's stead now to press into the kingdom of God!
				   Whoever you are, whether young or old, small or great; if you are a
				   great sinner, if you have been a backslider, if you have quenched the
				   Spirit, be who you will, do not stand making objections, but arise,
				   apply yourself to your work! Do what you have to do with your might.
				   Christ is calling you before, and holding forth his grace, and
				   everlasting benefits, and wrath is pursuing you behind; wherefore fly
				   for your life, and look not behind you! But here I would particularly
				   direct myself to several sorts of persons.
				
				   I. To those sinners who are in a measure awakened, and are concerned
				   for their salvation. You have reason to be glad that you have such an
				   opportunity, and to prize it above gold. To induce you to prize and
				   improve it, consider several things.
				
				   1. God has doubtless a design now to deal forth saving blessings to a
				   number. God has done it to some already, and it is not probable that he
				   has yet finished his work amongst us: we may well hope still to see
				   others brought out of darkness into marvellous light. And therefore,
				
				   2. God comes this day, and knocks at many persons' doors, and at your
				   door among the rest. God seems to be come in a very unusual manner
				   amongst us, upon a gracious and merciful design; a design of saving a
				   number of poor miserable souls out of a lost and perishing condition,
				   and of bringing them into a happy state and eternal glory! This is
				   offered to you, not only as it has always been in the word and
				   ordinances, but by the particular influences of the Spirit of Christ
				   awakening you! This special offer is made to many amongst us; and you
				   are not passed over. Christ has not forgot you; but has come to your
				   door; and there as it were stands waiting for you to open to him. If
				   you have wisdom and discretion to discern your own advantage, you will
				   know that now is your opportunity.
				
				   3. How much more easily converting grace is obtained at such a time,
				   than at other times! The work is equally easy with God at all times;
				   but there is far less difficulty in the way as to men at such a time,
				   than at other times. It is, as I said before, a day of God's gracious
				   visitation; a day that he has as it were set apart for the more
				   liberally and bountifully dispensing of his grace; a day wherein God's
				   hand is opened wide. Experience shows it. God seems to be more ready to
				   help, to give proper convictions, to help against temptations, and let
				   in divine light. He seems to carry on his work with a more glorious
				   discovery of his power, and Satan is more chained up than at other
				   times. Those difficulties and temptations that persons before struck
				   at, from year to year, they are soon helped over. The work of God is
				   carried on with greater speed and swiftness, and there are often
				   instances of sudden conversion at such a time. So it was in the
				   apostles' days, when there was a time of the most extraordinary pouring
				   out of the Spirit that ever was. How quick and sudden were conversions
				   in those days! Such instances as that of the jailer abounded then, in
				   fulfillment of that prophecy, Isaiah 66:7, 8. "Before she travailed,
				   she brought forth: before her pain came she was delivered of a
				   man-child. Who hath heard such a thing? Who hath seen such things? For
				   as soon as Zion travailed, she brought forth her children." So it is in
				   some degree, whenever there is an extraordinary pouring out of the
				   Spirit of God; more or less so, in proportion to the greatness of that
				   effusion. There is seldom such quick work made of it at other times.
				   Persons are not so soon delivered from their various temptations and
				   entanglements; but are much longer wandering in a wilderness, and
				   groping in darkness. And yet,
				
				   4. There are probably some here present that are now concerned about
				   their salvation, that will never obtain. It is not to be supposed that
				   all that are now moved and awakened, will ever be savingly converted.
				   Doubtless there are many now seeking that will not be able to enter.
				   When has it been so in times past, when there has been times of great
				   outpourings of God's Spirit, but that many who for a while have
				   inquired with others, what they should do to be saved, have failed, and
				   afterwards grown hard and secure? All of you that are now awakened,
				   have a mind to obtain salvation, and probably hope to get a title to
				   heaven, in the time of this present moving of God's Spirit: but yet,
				   (though it be awful to be spoken, and awful to be thought) we have no
				   reason to think any other, than that some of you will burn in hell to
				   all eternity. You all are afraid of hell, and seem at present disposed
				   to take pains to be delivered from it; and yet it would be unreasonable
				   to think any other, than that some of you will have your portion in the
				   lake that burns with fire and brimstone. Though there are so many that
				   seem to obtain so easily, having been but a little while under
				   convictions, yet, for all that, some never will obtain. Some will soon
				   lose the sense of things they now have; though their awakenings seem to
				   be very considerable for the present, they will not hold; they have not
				   hearts disposed to hold on through very many difficulties. Some that
				   have set out for heaven, and hope as much as others to obtain, are
				   indeed but slighty and slack, even now, in the midst of such a time as
				   this. And others, who for the present seem to be more in earnest, will
				   probably, before long, decline and fail, and gradually return to be as
				   they were before. The convictions of some seem to be great, while that
				   which is the occasion of their convictions is new; which, when that
				   begins to grow old, will gradually decay and wear off. Thus, it may be,
				   the occasion of your awakening has been the hearing of the conversion
				   of some person, or seeing so extraordinary a dispensation of Providence
				   as this in which God now appears amongst us; but by and by the newness
				   and freshness of these things will be gone, and so will not affect your
				   mind as now they do; and it may be your convictions will go away with
				   it.
				
				   Though this be a time wherein God doth more liberally bestow his grace,
				   and so a time of greater advantage for obtaining it; yet there seems to
				   be, upon some accounts, greater danger of backsliding, than when
				   persons are awakened at other times. For commonly such extraordinary
				   times do not last long; and then when they cease, there are multitudes
				   that lose their convictions as it were together.
				   We speak of it as a happy thing, that God is pleased to cause such a
				   time amongst us, and so it is indeed: but there are some to whom it
				   will be no benefit; it will be an occasion of their greater misery;
				   they will wish they had never seen this time; it will be more tolerable
				   for those that never saw it, or any thing like it, in the day of
				   judgment, than for them. It is an awful consideration, that there are
				   probably those here, whom the great Judge will hereafter call to a
				   strict account about this very thing, why they no better improved this
				   opportunity, when he set open the fountain of his grace, and so loudly
				   called upon them, and came and strove with them in particular, by the
				   awakening influences of his Spirit; and they will have no good account
				   to give to the Judge, but their mouths will be stopped, and they will
				   stand speechless before him.
				   You had need therefore to be earnest, and very resolved in this affair,
				   that you may not be one of those who shall thus fail, that you may so
				   fight, as not uncertainly, and so run, as that you may win the prize.
				
				   5. Consider in what sad circumstances times of extraordinary effusion
				   of God's Spirit commonly leave persons, when they leave them
				   unconverted. They find them in a doleful, because in a natural,
				   condition; but commonly leave them in a much more doleful condition.
				   They are left dreadfully hardened, and with a great increase of guilt,
				   and their souls under a more strong dominion and possession of Satan.
				   And frequently seasons of extraordinary advantage for salvation,when
				   they pass over persons, and they do not improve them, nor receive any
				   good in them, seal their damnation. As such seasons leave them, God for
				   ever leaves them, and gives them up to judicial hardness. Luke 19:41,
				   42. "And when he was come near, he beheld the city, and wept over it,
				   saying, If thou hadst known, even thou, the things which belong unto
				   thy peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes."
				
				   6. Consider, that it is very uncertain whether you will ever see such
				   another time as this. If there should be such another time, it is very
				   uncertain uncertain whether you will live to another time, it is very
				   uncertain whether you will eve whether you will live to see it. Many
				   that are now concerned for their salvation amongst us, will probably be
				   in their graves, and it may be in hell, before that time; and if you
				   should miss this opportunity, it may be so with you. And what good will
				   that do you, to have the Spirit of God poured out upon earth, in the
				   place where you once lived, while you are tormented in hell? What will
				   it avail you, that others are crying, What shall I do to be saved?
				   while you are shut up for ever in the bottomless pit, and are wailing
				   and gnashing your teeth in everlasting burnings?
				
				   Wherefore improve this opportunity, while God is pouring out his
				   Spirit, and you are on earth, and while you dwell in the place where
				   the Spirit of God is thus poured out, and you yourself have the
				   awakening influences of it, that you may never wail and gnash your
				   teeth in hell, but may sing in heaven for ever, with others that are
				   redeemed from amongst men, and redeemed amongst us.
				
				   7. If you should see another such time, it will be under far greater
				   disadvantages than now. You will probably then be much older, and will
				   have more hardened your heart; and so will be under less probability of
				   receiving good. Some persons are so hardened in sin, and so left of
				   God, that they can live through such a time as this, and not be much
				   awakened or affected by it; they can stand their ground, and be but
				   little moved. And so it may be with you, by another such time, if there
				   should be another amongst us, and you should live to see it. The case
				   in all probability will be greatly altered with you by that time.
				
				   If you should continue Christless and graceless till then, you will be
				   much further from the kingdom of God, and much deeper involved in
				   snares and misery; and the devil will probably have a vastly greater
				   advantage against you, to tempt and confound you.
				
				   8. We do not know but that God is now gathering in his elect, before
				   some great and sore judgment. It has been God's manner before he casts
				   off a visible people, or brings some great and destroying judgments
				   upon them, first to gather in his elect, that they may be secure. So it
				   was before the casting off the Jews from being God's people. There was
				   first a very remarkable pouring out of the Spirit, and gathering in of
				   the elect, by the preaching of the apostles and evangelists, as we read
				   in the beginning of the Acts: but after this the harvest and its
				   gleanings were over, the rest were blinded, and hardened; the gospel
				   had little success amongst them, and the nation was given up, and cast
				   off from being God's people, and their city and land was destroyed by
				   the Romans in a terrible manner; and they have been cast off by God now
				   for a great many ages, and still remain a hardened and rejected people.
				   So we read in the beginning of the 7th chapter of the Revelations, that
				   God, when about to bring destroying judgments on the earth, first
				   sealed his servants in the forehead. He set his seal upon the hearts of
				   the elect, gave them the saving influences and indwelling of his
				   Spirit, by which they were sealed to the day of redemption. Revelation
				   7:1-3. "And after these things, I saw four angels standing on the four
				   corners of the earth, holding the four winds of the earth, that the
				   wind should not blow on the earth, nor on the sea, nor on any tree. And
				   I saw another angel ascending from the east, having the seal of the
				   living God: and he cried with a loud voice to the four angels, to whom
				   it was given to hurt the earth and the sea, saying, Hurt not the earth,
				   neither the sea, nor the trees, till we have sealed the servants of our
				   God in their foreheads."
				
				   And this may be the case now, that God is about, in a great measure, to
				   forsake this land, and give up this people, and to bring most awful and
				   overwhelming judgments upon it, and that he is now gathering in his
				   elect, to secure them from the calamity. The state of the nation, and
				   of this land, never looked so threatening of such a thing as at this
				   day. The present aspect of things exceedingly threatens vital religion,
				   and even those truths that are especially the foundation of it, out of
				   this land. If it should be so, how awful will the case be with those
				   that shall be left, and not brought in, while God continues the
				   influences of his Spirit, to gather in those that are to be redeemed
				   from amongst us!
				
				   9. If you neglect the present opportunity, and be finally unbelieving,
				   those that are converted in this time of the pouring out of God's
				   Spirit will rise up in judgment against you. Your neighbors, your
				   relations, acquaintance, or companions that are converted, will that
				   day appear against you. They will not only be taken while you are left,
				   mounting up with joy to meet the Lord in the air-at his right hand with
				   glorious saints and angels, while you are at the left with devils-but
				   how they will rise up in judgment against you.
				
				   However friendly you have been together, and have taken pleasure in one
				   another's company, and have often familiarly conversed together, they
				   will then surely appear against you. They will rise up as witnesses,
				   and will declare what a precious opportunity you had, and did not
				   improve; how you continued unbelieving, and rejected the offers of a
				   Saviour, when those offers were made in so extraordinary a manner, and
				   when so many others were prevailed upon to accept of Christ; how you
				   was negligent and slack, and did not know the things that belonged to
				   your peace, in that your day. And not only so, but they shall be your
				   judges, as assessors with the great Judge; and as such will appear
				   against you; they will be with the Judge in passing sentence upon you.
				   I Corinthians 6:2. "Know ye not that the saints shall judge the world?"
				   Christ will admit them to the honour of judging the world with him:
				   "They shall sit with him in his throne," Revelation 3:21. "They shall
				   sit with Christ in his throne of government, and they shall sit with
				   him in his throne of judgment, and shall be judges with him when you
				   are judged, and as such shall condemn you.
				
				   10. And lastly, You do not know that you shall live through the present
				   time of the pouring out of God's Spirit. You may be taken away in the
				   midst of it, or you may be taken away in the beginning of it; as God in
				   his providence is putting you in mind, by the late instance of death in
				   a young person in the town.* God has of late been very awful in his
				   dealings with us, in the repeated deaths of young persons amongst us.
				   This should stir every one up to be in the more haste to press into the
				   kingdom of God, that so you may be safe whenever death comes. This is a
				   blessed season and opportunity; but you do not know how little of it
				   you may have. You may have much less of it than others; may by death be
				   suddenly snatched away from all advantages that are here enjoyed for
				   the good of souls. Therefore make haste, and escape for thy life. One
				   moment's delay is dangerous; for wrath is pursuing, and divine
				   vengeance hanging over every uncovered person.
				   Let these considerations move every one to be improving this
				   opportunity, that while others receive saving good, and are made heirs
				   of eternal glory, you may not be left behind, in the same miserable
				   doleful circumstances in which you came into the world, a poor captive
				   to sin and Satan, a lost sheep, a perishing, undone creature, sinking
				   down into everlasting perdition; that you may not be one of them spoken
				   of, Jeremiah 17:6. "That shall be like the heath in the desert, and
				   shall not see when good comes." If you do not improve this opportunity,
				   remember I have told you, you will hereafter lament it; and if you do
				   not lament it in this world, then I will leave it with you to remember
				   it throughout a miserable eternity.
				
				   II. I would address myself to such as yet remain unawakened. It is an
				   awful thing that there should be any one person remaining secure
				   amongst us at such a time as this; but yet it is to be feared that
				   there are some of this sort. I would here a little expostulate with
				   such persons.
				
				   * Joseph Clark's wife, a young woman lately married, that died suddenly
				   the week before this was delivered.
				
				   1. When do you expect that it will be more likely that you should be
				   awakened and wrought upon than now? You are in a Christless condition;
				   and yet without doubt intend to go to heaven; and therefore intend to
				   be converted some time before you die; but this is not to be expected
				   till you are first awakened, and deeply concerned about the welfare of
				   your soul, and brought earnestly to seek God's converting grace. And
				   when do you intend that this shall be? How do you lay things out in
				   your own mind, or what projection have you about this matter? Is it
				   ever so likely that a person will be awakened, as at such a time as
				   this? How do we see many, who before were secure, now roused out of
				   their sleep, and crying, What shall I do to be saved? But you are yet
				   secure! Do you flatter yourself that it will be more likely you should
				   be awakened when it is a dull and dead time? Do you lay matters out
				   thus in your own mind, that though you are senseless when others are
				   generally awakened, that yet you shall be awakened when others are
				   generally senseless? Or do you hope to see another such time of the
				   pouring out of God's Spirit hereafter? And do you think it will be more
				   likely that you should be wrought upon then, than now? And why do you
				   think so? Is it because then you shall be so much older than you are
				   now, and so that your heart will be grown softer and more tender with
				   age? or because you will then have stood out so much longer against the
				   calls of the gospel, and all means of grace? Do you think it more
				   likely that God will give you the needed influences of his Spirit then,
				   than now, because then you will have provoked him so much more, and
				   your sin and guilt will be so much greater? And do you think it will be
				   any benefit to you, to stand it out through the present season of
				   grace, as proof against the extraordinary means of awakening there are?
				   Do you think that this will be a good preparation for a saving work of
				   the Spirit hereafter?
				
				   2. What means do you expect to be awakened by? As to the awakening
				   awful things of the word of God, you have had those set before you
				   times without number, in the most moving manner that the dispensers of
				   the word have been capable of. As to particular solemn warnings,
				   directed to those that are in your circumstances, you have had them
				   frequently, and have them now from time to time. Do you expect to be
				   awakened by awful providences? Those also you have lately had, of the
				   most awakening nature, one after another. Do you expect to be moved by
				   the deaths of others? We have lately had repeated instances of these.
				   There have been deaths of old and young: the year has been remarkable
				   for the deaths of young persons in the bloom of life; and some of them
				   very sudden deaths. Will the conversion of others move you? There is
				   indeed scarce any thing that is found to have so great a tendency to
				   stir persons up as this: and this you have been tried with of late in
				   frequent instances; but are hitherto proof against it. Will a general
				   pouring out of the Spirit, and seeing a conern about salvation amongst
				   all sorts of people, do it? This means you now have, but without
				   effect. Yea, you have all these things together; you have the solemn
				   warnings of God's word, and awful instances of death, and the
				   conversion of others, and see a general concern about salvation: but
				   all together do not move you to any great concern about your own
				   precious, immortal, and miserable soul. Therefore consider by what
				   means it is that you expect ever to be awakened.
				
				   You have heard that it is probable some who are now awakened, will
				   never obtain salvation; how dark then does it look upon you that remain
				   stupidly unawakened! Those who are not moved at such a time as this,
				   come to adult age, have reason to fear whether they are not given up to
				   judicial hardness. I do not say they have reason to conclude it, but
				   they have reason to fear it. How dark doth it look upon you, that God
				   comes and knocks at so many persons' doors, and misses yours! that God
				   is giving the strivings of his Spirit so generally amongst us, while
				   you ar left senseless!
				
				   3. Do you expect to obtain salvation without ever seeking it? If you
				   are sensible that there is a necessity of your seeking in order to
				   obtaining, and ever intend to seek, one would think you could not avoid
				   it at such a time as this. Inquire therefore, whether you intend to go
				   to heaven, living all your days a secure, negligent, careless life.-Or,
				
				   4. Do you think you can bear the damnation of hell? Do you imagine that
				   you can tolerably endure the devouring fire, and everlasting burnings?
				   Do you hope that you shall be able to grapple with the vengeance of God
				   Almighty, when he girds himself with strength, and clothes himself with
				   wrath? Do you think to strengthen yourself against God, and to be able
				   to make your part good with him? I Corinthians 10:22. "Do we provoke
				   the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he?" Do you flatter yourself
				   that you shall find out ways for your ease and support, and to make it
				   out tolerably well, to bear up your spirit in those everlasting
				   burnings that are prepared for the devil and his angels? Ezekiel 22:14.
				   "Can thine heart endure, or can thine hands be strong, in the days that
				   I shall deal with thee?"-It is a difficult thing to conceive what such
				   Christless persons think, that are unconcerned at such a time.
				
				   III. I would direct myself to them who are grown considerably into
				   years, and are yet in a natural condition. I would now take occasion
				   earnestly to exhort you to improve this extraordinary opportunity, and
				   press into the kingdom of God. You have lost many advantages that once
				   you had, and now have not the same advantages that others have. The
				   case is very different with you from what it is with many of your
				   neighbours. You, above all, had need to improve such an opportunity.
				   Now is the time for you to bestir yourself, and take the kingdom of
				   heaven!-Consider,
				
				   1. Now there seems to be a door opened for old sinners. Now God is
				   dealing forth freely to all sorts: his hand is opened wide, and he does
				   not pass by old ones so much as he used to do. You are not under such
				   advantages as others who are younger; but yet, so wonderfully has God
				   ordered it, that now you are not destitute of great advantage. Though
				   old in sin, God has put a new and extraordinary advantage in your
				   hands. O! improve this price you have to get wisdom. You that have been
				   long seeking to enter in at the strait gate and yet remain without, now
				   take your opportunity and press in! You that have been long in the
				   wilderness, fighting with various temptations, labouring under
				   discouragements, ready to give up the case, and have been often tempted
				   to despair, now, behold the door that God opens for you! Do not give
				   way to discouragements now; this is not a time for it. Do not spend
				   time in thinking, that you have done what you can already, and that you
				   are not elected, and in giving way to other perplexing, weakening,
				   disheartening temptations. Do not waste away this precious opportunity
				   in such a manner. You have no time to spare for such things as these;
				   God calls you now to something else. Improve this time in seeking and
				   striving for salvation, and not in that which tends to hinder it.-It is
				   no time now for you to stand talking with the devil; but hearken to
				   God, and apply yourself to that which he does now so loudly call you
				   to.
				   Some of you have often lamented the loss of past opportunties,
				   particularly, the loss of the time of youth, and have been wishing that
				   you had so good an opportunity again; and have been ready to say, "O!
				   if I was young again, how would I improve such an advantage!" That
				   opportunity which you have had in time past is irrecoverable; you can
				   never have it again; but God can give you other advantages of another
				   sort, that are very great, and he is so doing at this day. He is now
				   putting a new opportunity into your hands; though not of the same kind
				   with that which you once had, and have lost, yet in some respects as
				   great of another kind. If you lament your folly in neglecting and
				   losing past opportunties, then do not be guilty of the folly of
				   neglecting the opportunity which God now gives you. This opportunity
				   you could not have purchased, if you would have given all that you had
				   in the world for it. But God is putting it into your hands himself, of
				   his own free and sovereign mercy, without your purchasing it. Therefore
				   when you have it, do not neglect it.
				
				   2. It is a great deal more likely with respect to such persons than
				   others, that this is their last time. There will be a last time of
				   special offer of salvation to impenitent sinners-"God's Spirit shall
				   not always strive with man," Genesis 6:3. God sometimes continues long
				   knocking at the doors of wicked men's hearts; but there are the last
				   knocks, and the last calls that ever they shall have. And sometimes
				   God's last calls are the loudest; and then if sinners do not hearken,
				   he finally leaves them. How long has God been knocking at many of your
				   doors that are old in sin! It is a great deal more likely that these
				   are his last knocks. You have resisted God's Spirit in times past, and
				   have hardened your heart once and again; but God will not be thus dealt
				   with always. There is danger, that if now, after so long a time, you
				   will not hearken, he will utterly desert you, and leave you to walk in
				   your own counsels.
				
				   It seems by God's providence, as though God had yet an elect number
				   amongst old sinners in this place, that perhaps he is now about to
				   bring in. It looks as though there were some that long lived under Mr.
				   Stoddard's ministry, that God has not utterly cast off, though they
				   stood it out under such great means as they then enjoyed. It is to be
				   hoped that God will now bring in a remnant from among them. But it is
				   more likely that God is now about finishing with them, one way or
				   other, for their having been so long the subjects of such extraordinary
				   means. You have seen former times of the pouring out of God's Spirit
				   upon the town, when others were taken and you left, others were called
				   out of darkness into marvelous light, and were brought into a glorious
				   and happy state, and you saw not good when good came. How dark will
				   your circumstances appear, if you shall also stand it out through this
				   opportunity, and still be left behind! Take heed that you be not of
				   those spoken of, Hebrews 6:7, 8. that are like the "earth that has rain
				   coming oft upon it, and only bears briers and thorns." As we see there
				   are some pieces of ground, the more showers of rain fall upon them, the
				   more fruitful seasons there are, the more do the briers, and other
				   useless and hurtful plants, that are rooted in them, grow and flourish.
				   Of such ground the apostle says, "It is rejected, and is nigh unto
				   cursing, whose end is to be burned." The way that the husbandman takes
				   with such ground, is, to set fire to it, to burn up the growth of
				   it.-If you miss this opportunity, there is danger that you will be
				   utterly rejected, and that your end will be to be burned. And if this
				   is to be, it is to be feared, that you are not far from, but nigh unto,
				   cursing.
				
				   Those of you that are already grown old in sin, and are now under
				   awakenings, when you feel your convictions begin to go off, if ever
				   that should be, then remember what you have now been told; it may well
				   then strike you to the heart!
				
				   IV. I would direct the advice to those that are young, and now under
				   their first special convictions. I would earnestly urge such to improve
				   this opportunity, and press into the kingdom of God.-Consider two
				   things,
				
				   1. You have all manner of advantages now centering upon you. It is a
				   time of great advantage for all; but your advantages are above others.
				   There is no other sort of persons that have now so great and happy an
				   opportunity as you have.-You have the great advantage that is common to
				   all who live in this place, viz. That now it is a time of the
				   extraordinary pouring out of the Spirit of God. And have you not that
				   great advantage, the awakening influences of the Spirit of God on you
				   in particular? and besides, you have this peculiar advantage, that you
				   are now in your youth. And added to this, you have another unspeakable
				   advantage, that you now are under your first convictions. Happy is he
				   that never has hardened his heart, and blocked up his own way to heaven
				   by backsliding, and has now the awakening influences of God's Spirit,
				   if God does but enable him thoroughly to improve them! Such above all
				   in the world bid fair for the kingdom of God. God is wont on such,
				   above any kind of persons, as it were easily and readily to bestow the
				   saving grace and comforts of his Spirit. Instances of speedy and sudden
				   conversion are most commonly found among such. Happy are they that have
				   the Spirit of God with them, and never have quenched it, if they did
				   but know the price they have in their hands!
				
				   If you have a sense of your necessity of salvation, and the great worth
				   and value of it, you will be willing to take the surest way to it, or
				   that which has the greatest probability of success; and that certainly
				   is, thoroughly to improve your first convictions. If you so go, it is
				   not likely that you will fail; there is the greatest probability that
				   you will succeed.-What is it not worth, to have such an advantage in
				   one's hands for obtaining eternal life? The present season of the
				   pouring out of God's Spirit, is the first that many of you who are now
				   under awakenings have ever seen, since you came to years of
				   understanding. On which account, it is the greatest opportunity that
				   ever you had, and probably by far the greatest that ever you will have.
				   There are many here present who wish they had such an opportunity, but
				   they never can obtain it; they cannot buy it for money; but you have it
				   in your possession, and can improve it if you will. But yet,
				
				   2. There is on some accounts greater danger that such as are in your
				   circumstances will fail of thoroughly improving their convictions, with
				   respect to stedfastness and perseverance, than others. Those that are
				   young are more unstable than elder persons. They who never had
				   convictions before, have less experience of the difficulty of the work
				   they have engaged in; they are more ready to think that they shall
				   obtain salvation easily, and are more easily discouraged by
				   disappointments; and young persons have less reason and consideration
				   to fortify them against temptations to backsliding. You should
				   therefore labour now the more to guard against such temptations. By all
				   means make but one work of seeking salvation! Make thorough work of it
				   the first time! There are vast disadvantages that they bring themselves
				   under, who have several turns of seeking with great intermissions. By
				   such a course, persons exceedingly wound their own souls, and entangle
				   themselves in many snares. Who are those that commonly meet with so
				   many difficulties, and are so long labouring in darkness and
				   perplexity, but those who have had several turns at seeking salvation;
				   who have one while had convictions, and then have quenched them, and
				   then have set about the work again, and have backslidden again, and
				   have gone on after that manner? The children of Israel would not have
				   been forty years in the wilderness, if they had held their courage, and
				   had gone on as they set out; but they were of an unstable mind, and
				   were for going back again into Egypt.-Otherwise, if they had gone right
				   forward without discouragement, as God would have led them, they would
				   have soon entered and taken possession of Canaan. They had got to the
				   very borders of it when they turned back, but were thirty-eight years
				   after that, before they got through the wilderness. Therefore, as you
				   regard the interest of your soul, do not run yourself into a like
				   difficulty, by unsteadiness, intermission, and backsliding; but press
				   right forward, from henceforth, and make but one work of seeking,
				   converting, and pardoning grace, however great, and difficult, and long
				   a work that may be.
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				Many Mansions
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				A Sermon
				
				  by
				
				Jonathan Edwards
				
				      [Sermon Date: "The Sabbath after the seating of the New Meeting House, Dec
				      25, 1737."]
				     __________________________________________________________________
				
				    John 14:2 -- In My Father's house are many mansions.
				
				   IN these words may be observed two things,
				
				   1. The thing described, viz., Christ's Father's house. Christ spoke to
				   his disciples in the foregoing chapter as one that was about to leave
				   them. He told 'em, verse 31, "Now is the Son of Man glorified, and God
				   is glorified in him," and then goes to giving of them counsel to live
				   in unity and love one another, as one that was going from them. By
				   which they seemed somewhat surprised and hardly knew what to make of
				   it. And one of them, viz., Peter, asked him where he was going; verse
				   36, "Simon Peter said unto him, Lord whither goest thou?" Christ did
				   not directly answer and tell him where he was going, but he signifies
				   where in these words afterwards, in the verse 12, he tells 'em plainly
				   that he was going to his Father.
				
				   2. We may observe the description given of it, viz., that in it there
				   are many mansions. The disciples seemed very sorrowful at the news of
				   Christ's going away, but Christ comforts 'em with that, that in his
				   Father's house where he was going there was not only room for him, but
				   room for them too. There were many mansions. There was not only a
				   mansion there for him, but there were mansions enough for them all;
				   there was room enough in heaven for them. When the disciples perceived
				   that Christ was going away, they manifested a great desire to go with
				   him, and particularly Peter. Peter in the latter part of the foregoing
				   chapter asked him whither he went to that end that he might follow him.
				   Christ told him that whither he went he could not follow him now, but
				   that he should follow him afterwards. But Peter, not content with
				   Christ, seemed to have a great mind to follow him now. "Lord," says he,
				   "why cannot I follow thee now?" So that the disciples had a great mind
				   still to be with Christ, and Christ in the words of the text intimates
				   that they shall be with him. Christ signifies to 'em that he was going
				   home to his Father's house, and he encourages 'em that they shall be
				   with him there in due time, in that there were many mansions there.
				   There was a mansion provided not only for him, but for them all (for
				   Judas was not then present), and not only for them, but for all that
				   should ever believe in him to the end of the world; and though he went
				   before, he only went to prepare a place for them that should follow.
				
				   The text is a plain sentence; 'tis therefore needless to press any
				   doctrine in other words from it: so that I shall build my discourse on
				   the words of the text. There are two propositions contained in the
				   words, viz.,
				
				   I. that heaven is God's house, and
				
				   II. that in this house of God there are many mansions.
				
				   Prop. I. Heaven is God's house. An house of public worship is an house
				   where God's people meet from time to time to attend on God's
				   ordinances, and that is set apart for that and is called God's house.
				   The temple of Solomon was called God's house. God was represented as
				   dwelling there. There he has his throne in the holy of holies, even the
				   mercy seat over the ark and between the cherubims.
				
				   Sometimes the whole universe is represented in Scripture as God's
				   house, built with various stories one above another: Amos 9:6, "It is
				   he that buildeth his stories in the heaven;" and Psalm 104:3, "Who
				   layeth the beams of his chambers in the waters." But the highest heaven
				   is especially represented in Scripture as the house of God. As to other
				   parts of the creation, God hath appointed them to inferior uses; but
				   this part he has reserved for himself for his own abode. We are told
				   that the heavens are the Lord's, but the earth he hath given to the
				   sons of men. God, though he is everywhere present, is represented both
				   in Old Testament and New as being in heaven is a special and peculiar
				   manner. Heaven is the temple of God. Thus we read of God's temple in
				   heaven, Revelation 15:5. Solomon's temple was a type of heaven. The
				   apostle Paul is his epistle to the Hebrews does from time to time call
				   heaven the holy of holies, as being the antitype not only of the temple
				   of Solomon, but of the most holy place in that temple, which was the
				   place of God's most immediate residence: Hebrews 9:12, "He entered in
				   once into the holy place;" verse 24, "For Christ is not entered into
				   the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but
				   into heaven itself." Houses where assemblies of Christians worship God
				   are in some respects figures of this house of God above. When God is
				   worshipped in them in spirit and truth, they become the outworks of
				   heaven and as it were its gates. As in houses of public worship here
				   there are assemblies of Christians meeting to worship God, so in heaven
				   there is a glorious assembly, or Church, continually worshipping God:
				   Hebrews 12:22,23, "But ye are come unto mount Sion, [and unto] the city
				   of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable
				   company of angels, to the general assembly and church of the firstborn,
				   that are written in heaven."
				
				   Heaven is represented in Scripture as God's dwelling-house; Psalm
				   113:5, "Who is like [unto] the Lord our God, who dwelleth on high," and
				   Psalm 123:1, "Unto thee I lift up mine eyes, O thou that dwellest in
				   the heavens." Heaven is God's palace. 'Tis the house of the great King
				   of the universe; there he has his throne, which is therefore
				   represented as his house or temple; Psalm 11:4, "The Lord is in his
				   holy temple; the Lord's throne is in heaven."
				
				   Heaven is the house where God dwells with his family. God is
				   represented in Scripture as having a family; and though some of this
				   family are now on earth, yet in so being they are abroad and not at
				   home, but all going home: Ephesians 3:15, "Of whom the whole family in
				   heaven and earth is named." Heaven is the place that God has built for
				   himself and his children. God has many children, and the place designed
				   for them is heaven; therefore the saints, being the children of God,
				   are said to be of the household of God, Ephesians 2:19: "Now therefore
				   ye are no more strangers and foreigners, but fellow-citizens with the
				   saints, and of the household of God." God is represented as a
				   householder or head of a family, and heaven is his house.
				
				   Heaven is the house not only where God hath his throne, but also where
				   he doth as it were keep his table, where his children sit down with him
				   at his table and where they are feasted in a royal manner becoming the
				   children of so great a King: Luke 22:30, "That ye may eat and drink at
				   my table in my kingdom;" Matthew 26:29, "But I say unto you, I will not
				   drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine until that day when I drink
				   it new with you in my Father's kingdom."
				
				   God is the King of kings, and heaven is the place where he keeps his
				   court. There are his angels and archangels that as the nobles of his
				   court do attend upon him.
				
				   Prop. II. There are many mansions in the house of God. By many mansions
				   is meant many seats or places of abode. As it is a king's palace, there
				   are many mansions. Kings' houses are wont to be built very large, with
				   many stately rooms and apartments. So there are many mansions in God's
				   house.
				
				   When this is spoken of heaven, it is chiefly to be understood in a
				   figurative sense, and the following things seem to be taught us in it.
				
				   1. There is room in this house of God for great numbers. There is room
				   in heaven for a vast multitude, yea, room enough for all mankind that
				   are or ever shall be; Luke 14:22, "Lord it is done as thou hast
				   commanded, and yet there is room."
				
				   It is not with the heavenly temple as it often is with houses of public
				   worship in this world, that they fill up and become too small and
				   scanty for those that would meet in them, so that there is not
				   convenient room for all. There is room enough in our heavenly Father's
				   house. This is partly what Christ intended in the words of the text, as
				   is evident from the occasion of his speaking them. The disciples
				   manifested a great desire to be where Christ was, and Christ therefore,
				   to encourage them that it should be as they desired, tells them that in
				   his Father's house where he was going were many mansions, i.e., room
				   enough for them.
				
				   There is mercy enough in God to admit an innumerable multitude into
				   heaven. There is mercy enough for all, and there is merit enough in
				   Christ to purchase heavenly happiness for millions of millions, for all
				   men that ever were, are or shall be. And there is a sufficiency in the
				   fountain of heaven's happiness to supply and fill and satisfy all: and
				   there is in all respects enough for the happiness of all.
				
				   2. There are sufficient and suitable accommodations for all the
				   different sorts of persons that are in the world: for great and small,
				   for high and low, rich and poor, wise and unwise, bond and free,
				   persons of all nations and all conditions and circumstances, for those
				   that have been great sinners as well as for moral livers; for weak
				   saints and those that are babes in Christ as well as for those that are
				   stronger and more grown in grace. There is in heaven a sufficiency for
				   the happiness of every sort; there is a convenient accommodation for
				   every creature that will hearken to the calls of the Gospel. None that
				   will come to Christ, let his condition be what it will, need to fear
				   but that Christ will provide a place suitable for him in heaven.
				
				   This seems to be another thing implied in Christ's words. The disciples
				   were persons of very different condition from Christ: he was their
				   Master, and there were his disciples; he was their Lord, and there were
				   the servants; he was their Guide, and they were the followers; he was
				   their Captain, and they the soldiers; he was the Shepherd, and they the
				   sheep; [he was, as it were, the] Father, [and they the] children; he
				   was the glorious, holy Son of God, they were the poor, sinful, corrupt
				   men. But yet, though they were in such different circumstances from
				   him, yet Christ encourages them that there shall not only be room in
				   heaven for him, but for them too; for there were many mansions there.
				   There was not only a mansion to accommodate the Lord, but the disciples
				   also; not only the head, but the members; not only the Son of God, but
				   those that are naturally poor, sinful, corrupt men: as in a king's
				   palace there is not only a mansion or room of state built for the king
				   himself and for his eldest son and heir, but there are many rooms,
				   mansions for all his numerous household, children, attendants and
				   servants.
				
				   3. It is further implied that heaven is a house that was actually built
				   and prepared for a great multitude. When God made heaven in the
				   beginning of the world, he intended it for an everlasting
				   dwelling-place for a vast and innumerable multitude. When heaven was
				   made , it was intended and prepared for all those particular persons
				   that God had from eternity designed to save: Matthew 25:34, "Come, ye
				   blessed [of my Father, inherit the Kingdom] prepared for you [from the
				   foundation of the world]." And that is a very great and innumerable
				   multitude: Revelation 7:9, "After this I beheld, and, lo, a great
				   multitude which no man could number, of all nations, and kindreds, and
				   peoples, and tongues, stood before the throne and before the Lamb,
				   clothed with white robes." Heaven being built designedly for these was
				   built accordingly; it was built so as most conveniently to accommodate
				   all this multitude: as a house that is built for a great family is
				   built large and with many rooms in it; as a palace that is built for a
				   great king that keeps a great court with many attendants is built
				   exceeding great with a great many apartments; and as an house of public
				   worship that is built for a great congregation is built very large with
				   many seats in it.
				
				   4. When it is said, ["In my father's house are many mansions"], it is
				   meant that there are seats of various dignity and different degrees and
				   circumstances of honor and happiness. There are many mansions in God's
				   house because heaven is intended for various degrees of honor and
				   blessedness. Some are designed to sit in higher places there than
				   others; some are designed to be advanced to higher degrees of honor and
				   glory than others are; and, therefore, there are various mansions, and
				   some more honorable mansions and seats, in heaven than others. Though
				   they are all seats of exceeding honor and blessedness yet some are more
				   so than others.
				
				   Thus a palace is built. Though every part of the palace is magnificent
				   as becomes the palace of a king, yet there are many apartments of
				   various honor, and some are more stately and costly than others,
				   according to the degree of dignity. There is one apartment that is the
				   king's presence-chamber; there are other apartments for the next heir
				   to the crown; there are others for other children; and others for their
				   attendants and the great officers of the household: one for the high
				   steward, and another for the chamberlain, and others for meaner
				   officers and servants.
				
				   Another image of this was in Solomon's temple. There were many mansions
				   of different degrees of honor and dignity. There was the holy of
				   holies, where the ark was that was the place of God's immediate
				   residence, where the high priest alone might come; and there was
				   another apartment called the holy place, where the other priests might
				   come; and next to that was the inner court of the temple, where the
				   Levites were admitted: and there they had many chambers or mansions
				   built for lodging-rooms for the priests; and next to that was the court
				   of Israel where the people of Israel might come; and next to that was
				   the court of the Gentiles where the Gentiles, those that were called
				   the "Proselytes of the Gate," might come.
				
				   And we have an image of this in houses built for the worship of
				   Christian assemblies. In such houses of God there are many seats of
				   different honor and dignity, from the most honorable to the most
				   inferior of the congregation.
				
				   Not that we are to understand the words of Christ so much in a literal
				   sense, as that every saint in heaven was to have a certain seat or room
				   or place of abode where he was to be locally fixed. 'Tis not the design
				   of the Scriptures to inform us much about the external circumstances of
				   heaven or the state of heaven locally considered; but we are to
				   understand what Christ says chiefly in a spiritual sense. Persons shall
				   be set in different degrees of honor and glory in heaven, as is
				   abundantly manifested in Scripture: which may fitly be represented to
				   our imaginations by there being different seats of honor, as it was in
				   the temple, as it is in kings' courts. Some seats shall be nearer the
				   throne than others. Some shall sit next to Christ in glory: Matthew
				   20:23, "To sit on my right hand and on my left, is not mine to give,
				   but it shall be given to them for whom it is prepared of my Father."
				
				   Christ has doubtless respect to these different degrees of glory in the
				   text. When he was going to heaven and the disciples were sorrowful at
				   the thoughts of parting with their Lord, he lets them know that there
				   are seats or mansions of various degrees of honor in his Father's
				   house, that there was not only one for him, who was the Head of the
				   Church and the elder brother, but also for them that were his disciples
				   and younger brethren.
				
				   Christ also may probably have respect not only to different degrees of
				   glory in heaven, but different circumstances. Though the employment and
				   happiness of all the heavenly assembly shall in the general be the
				   same, yet 'tis not improbable that there may be circumstantial
				   difference. We know what their employment [is] in general, but not in
				   particular. We know not how one may be employed to subserve and promote
				   the happiness of another, and all to help one another. Some may there
				   be set in one place for one office or employment, and others [in]
				   another, as 'tis in the Church on earth. God hath set every one in the
				   body as it hath pleased him; one is the eye, another the ear, another
				   the head, etc. But because God has not been pleased expressly to reveal
				   how it shall be in this respect, therefore I shall not insist upon it,
				   but pass to make some
				
				IMPROVEMENT of what has been offered.
				
				   I. Here is encouragement for sinners that are concerned and exercised
				   for the salvation of their souls, such as are afraid that they shall
				   never go to heaven or be admitted to any place of abode there, and are
				   sensible that they are hitherto in a doleful state and condition in
				   that they are out of Christ, and so have no right to any inheritance in
				   heaven, but are in danger of going to hell and having their place of
				   eternal abode fixed there. You may be encouraged by what has been said,
				   earnestly to seek heaven; for there are many mansions there. There is
				   room enough there. Let your case be what it will, there is suitable
				   provision there for you; and if you come to Christ, you need not fear
				   that he will prepare a place for you; he'll see to it that you shall be
				   well accommodated in heaven.
				
				   But II. I would improve this doctrine in a twofold exhortation.
				
				   1. Let all be hence exhorted earnestly to seek that they may be
				   admitted to a mansion in heaven. You have heard that this is God's
				   house; it is his temple. If David, when he was in the wilderness of
				   Judah and in the land of Geshur and of the Philistines, so longed that
				   he might again return into the land of Israel that he might have a
				   place in the house of God here on earth, and prized a place there so
				   much, though it was but that of a door-keeper, how great a happiness
				   will it be to have a place in this heavenly temple of God! If they are
				   looked upon as enjoying a high privilege that have a seat appointed
				   them in kings' courts or in apartments in kings' palaces, especially
				   those that have an abode there in the quality of the king's children,
				   then how great a privilege will it be to have an apartment or mansion
				   assigned to us in God's heavenly palace, and to have a place there as
				   his children! How great is their glory and honor that are admitted to
				   be of the household of God!
				
				   And seeing there are many mansions there, mansions enough for us all,
				   our folly will be the greater if we neglect to seek a place in heaven,
				   having our minds foolishly taken up about the worthless, fading things
				   of this world. Here consider three things:
				
				   (1) How little a while you can have any mansion or place of abode in
				   this world. Now you have a dwelling amongst the living. You have a
				   house or mansion of your own, or at least one that is at present for
				   your use, and now you have a seat in the house of God; but how little a
				   while will this continue! In a very little while, and the place that
				   now knows you in this world will know you no more. The habitation you
				   have here will be empty of you; you will be carried dead out of it, or
				   shall die at a distance from it, and never enter into it any more, or
				   into any other abode in this world. Your mansion or place of abode in
				   this world, however convenient or commodious it may be, is but as a
				   tent that shall soon be taken down, but a lodge in a garden of
				   cucumbers. Your stay is as it were but for a night. Your body itself is
				   but a house of clay which will quickly moulder and tumble down, and you
				   shall have no other habitation here in this world but the grave.
				
				   Thus God in his providence is putting you in mind by the repeated
				   instances of death that have been in the town within the two weeks
				   past, both in one house: in which death he has shown his dominion over
				   old and young. The son was taken away first before the father, being in
				   his full strength and flower of his days; and the father, who was then
				   well and having no appearance of approaching death, followed in a few
				   days: and their habitation and their seat in the house of God in this
				   world will know them no more.
				
				   Take warning by these warnings of Providence to improve your time that
				   you may have a mansion in heaven. We have a house of worship newly
				   created amongst us which now you have a seat in, and probably are
				   pleased with the ornaments of it; and though you have a place in so
				   comely a house, yet you know not how little a while you shall have a
				   place in this house of God. Here are a couple snatched away by death
				   that had met in it but a few times, that have been snatched out of it
				   before it was fully finished and never will have any more a seat in it.
				   You know not how soon you may follow, and then of great importance will
				   it be to you to have a seat in God's house above. Both of the persons
				   lately deceased were much on their death-beds warning others to improve
				   their precious time. The first of them was much in expressing his sense
				   of the vast importance of an interest in Christ, as I was a witness,
				   and was earnest in calling on others to improve their time, to be
				   thorough, to get an interest in Christ, and seemed very desirous that
				   young people might receive council and warning from him, as the words
				   of a dying man, to do their utmost to make sure of conversion; and a
				   little before he died left a request to me that I would warn the young
				   people in his room. God had been warning of you in his death and the
				   death of his father that so soon followed. The words of dying persons
				   should be of special weight with us, for then they are in circumstances
				   wherein they are most capable to look on things as they are and judge
				   aright of 'em,--between both worlds as it were. Still that we must all
				   be in.
				
				   Let our young people, therefore, take warning from hence, and don't be
				   such fools as to neglect seeking a place and mansion in heaven. Young
				   persons are especially apt to be taken with the pleasing things of this
				   world. You are now, it may be, much pleased with hopes of your future
				   circumstances in this world; [and you are now, it may be, much] pleased
				   with the ornaments of that house of worship that you with others have a
				   place in. But, alas, do you not too little consider how soon you may be
				   taken away from all these things, and no more forever have any part in
				   any mansion or house or enjoyment or happiness under the sun? Therefore
				   let it be your main care to secure an everlasting habitation for
				   hereafter.
				
				   (2) Consider when you die, if you have no mansion in the house of God
				   in heaven, you must have your place of abode in the habitation of
				   devils. There is no middle place between them, and when you go hence,
				   you must go to one or the other of these. Some have a mansion prepared
				   for them in heaven from the foundation [of the world]; others are sent
				   away as cursed into everlasting burnings prepared for the [devil and
				   his angels]. Consider how miserable those must be that shall have their
				   habitation with devils to all eternity. Devils are foul spirits; God's
				   great enemies. Their habitation is the blackness of darkness; a place
				   of the utmost filthiness, abomination, darkness, disgrace and torment,
				   O, how would you rather ten thousand times have no place of abode at
				   all, have no being, than to have a place [with devils]!
				
				   (3) If you die unconverted, you will have the worse place in hell for
				   having had a seat or place in God's house in this world. As there are
				   many mansions, places of different degrees of honor in heaven, so there
				   are various abodes and places or degrees of torment and misery in hell;
				   and those will have the worst place there that [dying unconverted, have
				   had the best place in God's house here]. Solomon speaks of a peculiarly
				   awful sight that he had seen, that of a wicked man buried that had gone
				   [from the place of the holy], Ecclesiastes 8:10. Such as have had a
				   seat in God's house, have been in a sense exalted up to heaven, set on
				   the gate of heaven, [if they die unconverted, shall be] cast down to
				   hell.
				
				   2. The second exhortation that I would offer from what has been said is
				   to seek a high place in heaven. Seeing there are many mansions of
				   different degrees of honor and dignity in heaven, let us seek to obtain
				   a mansion of distinguished glory. 'Tis revealed to us that there are
				   different degrees of glory to that end that we might seek after the
				   higher degrees. God offered high degrees of glory to that end, that we
				   might seek them by eminent holiness and good works: 2 Corinthians 9:6,
				   "He that sows sparingly [shall reap also sparingly; and he that soweth
				   bountifully shall reap also bountifully]." It is not becoming persons
				   to be over anxious about an high seat in God's house in this world, for
				   that is the honor that is of men; but we can't too earnestly seek after
				   an high seat in God's house above, by seeking eminent holiness, for
				   that is the honor that is of God.
				
				   'Tis very little worth the while for us to pursue after honor in this
				   world, where the greatest honor is but a bubble and will soon vanish
				   away, and death will level all. Some have more stately houses than
				   others, and some are in higher office than others, and some are richer
				   than others and have higher seats in the meeting-house than others; but
				   all graves are upon a level. One rotting, putrefying corpse is as
				   ignoble as another; the worms are as bold with one carcass as another.
				
				   But the mansions in God's house above are everlasting mansions. Those
				   that have seats allotted 'em there, whether of greater or lesser
				   dignity, whether nearer or further from the throne, will hold 'em to
				   all eternity. This is promised, Revelation 3:12 :"Him that overcometh I
				   will make him a pillar in the temple [of my God, and he shall go no
				   more out]." If it be worth the while to desire and seek high seats in
				   the meeting-house, where you are one day in a week, and where you shall
				   never come but few days in all; if it be worth the while much to prize
				   one seat above another in the house of worship only because it is the
				   pew or seat that is ranked first in number, and to be seen here for a
				   few days, how will it be worth the while to seek an high mansion in
				   God's temple and in that glorious place that is the everlasting
				   habitation of God and all his children! You that are pleased with your
				   seats in this house because you are seated high or in a place that is
				   looked upon honorable by those that sit round about, and because many
				   can behold you, consider how short a time you will enjoy this pleasure.
				   And if there be any that are not suited in their seats because they are
				   too low for them, let them consider that it is but a very little while
				   before it will [be] all one to you whether you have sat high or low
				   here. But it will be of infinite and everlasting concern to you where
				   your seat is in another world. Let your great concern be while in this
				   world so to improve your opportunities in God's house in this world,
				   whether you sit high or low, as that you may have a distinguished and
				   glorious mansion in God's house in heaven, where you may be fixed in
				   your place in that glorious assembly in an everlasting rest.
				
				   Let the main thing that we prize in God's house be, not the outward
				   ornaments of it, or a high seat in it, but the word of God and his
				   ordinances in it. And spend your time here in seeking Christ, that he
				   may prepare a place for you in his Father's house, that when he comes
				   again to this world, he may take you to himself, that where he is,
				   there you may be also.
				
				      [From Selected Sermons of Jonathan Edwards, edited with introduction and
				      notes by H. Horman Gardiner, New York, The Macmillan Company, 1904.]
