<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<osis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace">

	<osisText osisRefWork="book" xml:lang="en" osisIDWork="JESermons">
		<header>
			<work osisWork="JESermons">
				<title>Jonathan Edwards Sermons</title>
				<creator role="aut">Jonathan Edwards</creator>
			</work>
			<work osisWork="Bible">
				<refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
			</work>
		</header>

		<div type="book" osisID="Jonathan Edwards Sermons">
			<title>Jonathan Edwards Sermons</title>
			<title type="x-author">Jonathan Edwards</title>

			<div type="chapter" osisID="Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God">
				<title>Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God</title>
				<p>
					Jonathan Edwards (1703-1758)
				</p><p>
				    Enfield, Connecticut
				    July 8, 1741
				</p><p>
					Their foot shall slide in due time. <reference osisRef="Deut.32.35">Deuteronomy 32:35</reference>
				</p><p>
				   In this verse is threatened the vengeance of God on the wicked
				   unbelieving Israelites, who were God's visible people, and who lived
				   under the means of grace; but who, notwithstanding all God's wonderful
				   works towards them, remained (as vers 28.) void of counsel, having no
				   understanding in them. Under all the cultivations of heaven, they
				   brought forth bitter and poisonous fruit; as in the two verses next
				   preceding the text. - The expression I have chosen for my text, their
				   foot shall slide in due time, seems to imply the following things,
				   relating to the punishment and destruction to which these wicked
				   Israelites were exposed.
				</p><p>
				    1. That they were always exposed to destruction; as one that stands or
				       walks in slippery places is always exposed to fall. This is implied
				       in the manner of their destruction coming upon them, being
				       represented by their foot sliding. The same is expressed, <reference osisRef="Ps.73.18">Psalms 73:18</reference>. "Surely thou didst set them in slippery places; thou
				       castedst them down into destruction."
				</p><p>
				    2. It implies, that they were always exposed to sudden unexpected
				       destruction. As he that walks in slippery places is every moment
				       liable to fall, he cannot foresee one moment whether he shall stand
				       or fall the next; and when he does fall, he falls at once without
				       warning: Which is also expressed in <reference osisRef="Ps.73.18 Ps.73.19">Psalms 73:18-19</reference>. "Surely thou
				       didst set them in slippery places; thou castedst them down into
				       destruction: How are they brought into desolation as in a moment!"
				</p><p>
				    3. Another thing implied is, that they are liable to fall of
				       themselves, without being thrown down by the hand of another; as he
				       that stands or walks on slippery ground needs nothing but his own
				       weight to throw him down.
				</p><p>
				    4. That the reason why they are not fallen already and do not fall now
				       is only that God's appointed time is not come. For it is said, that
				       when that due time, or appointed time comes, their foot shall
				       slide. Then they shall be left to fall, as they are inclined by
				       their own weight. God will not hold them up in these slippery
				       places any longer, but will let them go; and then, at that very
				       instant, they shall fall into destruction; as he that stands on
				       such slippery declining ground, on the edge of a pit, he cannot
				       stand alone, when he is let go he immediately falls and is lost.
				</p><p>
				   The observation from the words that I would now insist upon is this. -
				   "There is nothing that keeps wicked men at any one moment out of hell,
				   but the mere pleasure of God." - By the mere pleasure of God, I mean
				   his sovereign pleasure, his arbitrary will, restrained by no
				   obligation, hindered by no manner of difficulty, any more than if
				   nothing else but God's mere will had in the least degree, or in any
				   respect whatsoever, any hand in the preservation of wicked men one
				   moment. - The truth of this observation may appear by the following
				   consideration.
				</p><p>
				    1. There is no want of power in God to cast wicked men into hell at
				       any moment. Men's hands cannot be strong when God rises up. The
				       strongest have no power to resist him, nor can any deliver out of
				       his hands. - He is not only able to cast wicked men into hell, but
				       he can most easily do it. Sometimes an earthly prince meets with a
				       great deal of difficulty to subdue a rebel, who has found means to
				       fortify himself, and has made himself strong by the numbers of his
				       followers. But it is not so with God. There is no fortress that is
				       any defence from the power of God. Though hand join in hand, and
				       vast multitudes of God's enemies combine and associate themselves,
				       they are easily broken in pieces. They are as great heaps of light
				       chaff before the whirlwind; or large quantities of dry stubble
				       before devouring flames. We find it easy to tread on and crush a
				       worm that we see crawling on the earth; so it is easy for us to cut
				       or singe a slender thread that any thing hangs by: thus easy is it
				       for God, when he pleases, to cast his enemies down to hell. What
				       are we, that we should think to stand before him, at whose rebuke
				       the earth trembles, and before whom the rocks are thrown down?
				</p><p>
				    2. They deserve to be cast into hell; so that divine justice never
				       stands in the way, it makes no objection against God's using his
				       power at any moment to destroy them. Yea, on the contrary, justice
				       calls aloud for an infinite punishment of their sins. Divine
				       justice says of the tree that brings forth such grapes of Sodom,
				       "Cut it down, why cumbereth it the ground?" <reference osisRef="Luke.13.7">Luke 13:7</reference>. The sword of
				       divine justice is every moment brandished over their heads, and it
				       is nothing but the hand of arbitrary mercy, and God's mere will,
				       that holds it back.
				</p><p>
				    3. They are already under a sentence of condemnation to hell. They do
				       not only justly deserve to be cast down thither, but the sentence
				       of the law of God, that eternal and immutable rule of righteousness
				       that God has fixed between him and mankind, is gone out against
				       them, and stands against them; so that they are bound over already
				       to hell. <reference osisRef="John.3.18">John 3:18</reference>. "He that believeth not is condemned already."
				       So that every unconverted man properly belongs to hell; that is his
				       place; from thence he is, <reference osisRef="John.8.23">John 8:23</reference>. "Ye are from beneath:" And
				       thither he is bound; it is the place that justice, and God's word,
				       and the sentence of his unchangeable law assign to him.
				</p><p>
				    4. They are now the objects of that very same anger and wrath of God,
				       that is expressed in the torments of hell. And the reason why they
				       do not go down to hell at each moment, is not because God, in whose
				       power they are, is not then very angry with them; as he is with
				       many miserable creatures now tormented in hell, who there feel and
				       bear the fierceness of his wrath. Yea, God is a great deal more
				       angry with great numbers that are now on earth: yea, doubtless,
				       with many that are now in this congregation, who it may be are at
				       ease, than he is with many of those who are now in the flames of
				       hell.
				       So that it is not because God is unmindful of their wickedness, and
				       does not resent it, that he does not let loose his hand and cut
				       them off. God is not altogether such an one as themselves, though
				       they may imagine him to be so. The wrath of God burns against them,
				       their damnation does not slumber; the pit is prepared, the fire is
				       made ready, the furnace is now hot, ready to receive them; the
				       flames do now rage and glow. The glittering sword is whet, and held
				       over them, and the pit hath opened its mouth under them.
				</p><p>
				    5. The devil stands ready to fall upon them, and seize them as his
				       own, at what moment God shall permit him. They belong to him; he
				       has their souls in his possession, and under his dominion. The
				       scripture represents them as his goods, <reference osisRef="Luke.11.12">Luke 11:12</reference>. The devils
				       watch them; they are ever by them at their right hand; they stand
				       waiting for them, like greedy hungry lions that see their prey, and
				       expect to have it, but are for the present kept back. If God should
				       withdraw his hand, by which they are restrained, they would in one
				       moment fly upon their poor souls. The old serpent is gaping for
				       them; hell opens its mouth wide to receive them; and if God should
				       permit it, they would be hastily swallowed up and lost.
				</p><p>
				    6. There are in the souls of wicked men those hellish principles
				       reigning, that would presently kindle and flame out into hell fire,
				       if it were not for God's restraints. There is laid in the very
				       nature of carnal men, a foundation for the torments of hell. There
				       are those corrupt principles, in reigning power in them, and in
				       full possession of them, that are seeds of hell fire. These
				       principles are active and powerful, exceeding violent in their
				       nature, and if it were not for the restraining hand of God upon
				       them, they would soon break out, they would flame out after the
				       same manner as the same corruptions, the same enmity does in the
				       hearts of damned souls, and would beget the same torments as they
				       do in them. The souls of the wicked are in scripture compared to
				       the troubled sea, <reference osisRef="Isa.57.20">Isaiah 57:20</reference>. For the present, God restrains their
				       wickedness by his mighty power, as he does the raging waves of the
				       troubled sea, saying, "Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further;"
				       but if God should withdraw that restraining power, it would soon
				       carry all before it. Sin is the ruin and misery of the soul; it is
				       destructive in its nature; and if God should leave it without
				       restraint, there would need nothing else to make the soul perfectly
				       miserable. The corruption of the heart of man is immoderate and
				       boundless in its fury; and while wicked men live here, it is like
				       fire pent up by God's restraints, whereas if it were let loose, it
				       would set on fire the course of nature; and as the heart is now a
				       sink of sin, so if sin was not restrained, it would immediately
				       turn the soul into fiery oven, or a furnace of fire and brimstone.
				</p><p>
				    7. It is no security to wicked men for one moment, that there are no
				       visible means of death at hand. It is no security to a natural man,
				       that he is now in health, and that he does not see which way he
				       should now immediately go out of the world by any accident, and
				       that there is no visible danger in any respect in his
				       circumstances. The manifold and continual experience of the world
				       in all ages, shows this is no evidence, that a man is not on the
				       very brink of eternity, and that the next step will not be into
				       another world. The unseen, unthought-of ways and means of persons
				       going suddenly out of the world are innumerable and inconceivable.
				       Unconverted men walk over the pit of hell on a rotten covering, and
				       there are innumerable places in this covering so weak that they
				       will not bear their weight, and these places are not seen. The
				       arrows of death fly unseen at noon-day; the sharpest sight cannot
				       discern them. God has so many different unsearchable ways of taking
				       wicked men out of the world and sending them to hell, that there is
				       nothing to make it appear, that God had need to be at the expense
				       of a miracle, or go out of the ordinary course of his providence,
				       to destroy any wicked man, at any moment. All the means that there
				       are of sinners going out of the world, are so in God's hands, and
				       so universally and absolutely subject to his power and
				       determination, that it does not depend at all the less on the mere
				       will of God, whether sinners shall at any moment go to hell, than
				       if means were never made use of, or at all concerned in the case.
				</p><p>
				    8. Natural men's prudence and care to preserve their own lives, or the
				       care of others to preserve them, do not secure them a moment. To
				       this, divine providence and universal experience do also bear
				       testimony. There is this clear evidence that men's own wisdom is no
				       security to them from death; that if it were otherwise we should
				       see some difference between the wise and politic men of the world,
				       and others, with regard to their liableness to early and unexpected
				       death: but how is it in fact? <reference osisRef="Eccl.2.16">Ecclesiastes 2:16</reference>. "How dieth the wise
				       man? even as the fool."
				</p><p>
				    9. All wicked men's pains and contrivance which they use to escape
				       hell, while they continue to reject Christ, and so remain wicked
				       men, do not secure them from hell one moment. Almost every natural
				       man that hears of hell, flatters himself that he shall escape it;
				       he depends upon himself for his own security; he flatters himself
				       in what he has done, in what he is now doing, or what he intends to
				       do. Every one lays out matters in his own mind how he shall avoid
				       damnation, and flatters himself that he contrives well for himself,
				       and that his schemes will not fail. They hear indeed that there are
				       but few saved, and that the greater part of men that have died
				       heretofore are gone to hell; but each one imagines that he lays out
				       matters better for his own escape than others have done. He does
				       not intend to come to that place of torment; he says within
				       himself, that he intends to take effectual care, and to order
				       matters so for himself as not to fail.
				       But the foolish children of men miserably delude themselves in
				       their own schemes, and in confidence in their own strength and
				       wisdom; they trust to nothing but a shadow. The greater part of
				       those who heretofore have lived under the same means of grace, and
				       are now dead, are undoubtedly gone to hell; and it was not because
				       they were not as wise as those who are now alive: it was not
				       because they did not lay out matters as well for themselves to
				       secure their own escape. If we could speak with them, and inquire
				       of them, one by one, whether they expected, when alive, and when
				       they used to hear about hell, ever to be the subjects of misery: we
				       doubtless, should hear one and another reply, "No, I never intended
				       to come here: I had laid out matters otherwise in my mind; I
				       thought I should contrive well for myself - I thought my scheme
				       good. I intended to take effectual care; but it came upon me
				       unexpected; I did not look for it at that time, and in that manner;
				       it came as a thief - Death outwitted me: God's wrath was too quick
				       for me. Oh, my cursed foolishness! I was flattering myself, and
				       pleasing myself with vain dreams of what I would do hereafter; and
				       when I was saying, Peace and safety, then sudden destruction came
				       upon me."
				</p><p>
				   10. God has laid himself under no obligation, by any promise to keep
				       any natural man out of hell one moment. God certainly has made no
				       promises either of eternal life, or of any deliverance or
				       preservation from eternal death, but what are contained in the
				       covenant of grace, the promises that are given in Christ, in whom
				       all the promises are yea and amen. But surely they have no interest
				       in the promises of the covenant of grace who are not the children
				       of the covenant, who do not believe in any of the promises, and
				       have no interest in the Mediator of the covenant.
				</p><p>
				   So that, whatever some have imagined and pretended about promises made
				   to natural men's earnest seeking and knocking, it is plain and
				   manifest, that whatever pains a natural man takes in religion, whatever
				   prayers he makes, till he believes in Christ, God is under no manner of
				   obligation to keep him a moment from eternal destruction.
				</p><p>
				   So that, thus it is that natural men are held in the hand of God, over
				   the pit of hell; they have deserved the fiery pit, and are already
				   sentenced to it; and God is dreadfully provoked, his anger is as great
				   towards them as to those that are actually suffering the executions of
				   the fierceness of his wrath in hell, and they have done nothing in the
				   least to appease or abate that anger, neither is God in the least bound
				   by any promise to hold them up one moment; the devil is waiting for
				   them, hell is gaping for them, the flames gather and flash about them,
				   and would fain lay hold on them, and swallow them up; the fire pent up
				   in their own hearts is struggling to break out: and they have no
				   interest in any Mediator, there are no means within reach that can be
				   any security to them. In short, they have no refuge, nothing to take
				   hold of; all that preserves them every moment is the mere arbitrary
				   will, and uncovenanted, unobliged forbearance of an incensed God.
				</p><p>
				
				  Application
				</p><p>
				   The use of this awful subject may be for awakening unconverted persons
				   in this congregation. This that you have heard is the case of every one
				   of you that are out of Christ. - That world of misery, that lake of
				   burning brimstone, is extended abroad under you. There is the dreadful
				   pit of the glowing flames of the wrath of God; there is hell's wide
				   gaping mouth open; and you have nothing to stand upon, nor any thing to
				   take hold of; there is nothing between you and hell but the air; it is
				   only the power and mere pleasure of God that holds you up.
				</p><p>
				   You probably are not sensible of this; you find you are kept out of
				   hell, but do not see the hand of God in it; but look at other things,
				   as the good state of your bodily constitution, your care of your own
				   life, and the means you use for your own preservation. But indeed these
				   things are nothing; if God should withdraw his hand, they would avail
				   no more to keep you from falling, than the thin air to hold up a person
				   that is suspended in it.
				</p><p>
				   Your wickedness makes you as it were heavy as lead, and to tend
				   downwards with great weight and pressure towards hell; and if God
				   should let you go, you would immediately sink and swiftly descend and
				   plunge into the bottomless gulf, and your healthy constitution, and
				   your own care and prudence, and best contrivance, and all your
				   righteousness, would have no more influence to uphold you and keep you
				   out of hell, than a spider's web would have to stop a falling rock.
				   Were it not for the sovereign pleasure of God, the earth would not bear
				   you one moment; for you are a burden to it; the creation groans with
				   you; the creature is made subject to the bondage of your corruption,
				   not willingly; the sun does not willingly shine upon you to give you
				   light to serve sin and Satan; the earth does not willingly yield her
				   increase to satisfy your lusts; nor is it willingly a stage for your
				   wickedness to be acted upon; the air does not willingly serve you for
				   breath to maintain the flame of life in your vitals, while you spend
				   your life in the service of God's enemies. God's creatures are good,
				   and were made for men to serve God with, and do not willingly subserve
				   to any other purpose, and groan when they are abused to purposes so
				   directly contrary to their nature and end. And the world would spew you
				   out, were it not for the sovereign hand of him who hath subjected it in
				   hope. There are the black clouds of God's wrath now hanging directly
				   over your heads, full of the dreadful storm, and big with thunder; and
				   were it not for the restraining hand of God, it would immediately burst
				   forth upon you. The sovereign pleasure of God, for the present, stays
				   his rough wind; otherwise it would come with fury, and your destruction
				   would come like a whirlwind, and you would be like the chaff on the
				   summer threshing floor.
				</p><p>
				   The wrath of God is like great waters that are dammed for the present;
				   they increase more and more, and rise higher and higher, till an outlet
				   is given; and the longer the stream is stopped, the more rapid and
				   mighty is its course, when once it is let loose. It is true, that
				   judgment against your evil works has not been executed hitherto; the
				   floods of God's vengeance have been withheld; but your guilt in the
				   mean time is constantly increasing, and you are every day treasuring up
				   more wrath; the waters are constantly rising, and waxing more and more
				   mighty; and there is nothing but the mere pleasure of God, that holds
				   the waters back, that are unwilling to be stopped, and press hard to go
				   forward. If God should only withdraw his hand from the flood-gate, it
				   would immediately fly open, and the fiery floods of the fierceness and
				   wrath of God, would rush forth with inconceivable fury, and would come
				   upon you with omnipotent power; and if your strength were ten thousand
				   times greater than it is, yea, ten thousand times greater than the
				   strength of the stoutest, sturdiest devil in hell, it would be nothing
				   to withstand or endure it.
				</p><p>
				   The bow of God's wrath is bent, and the arrow made ready on the string,
				   and justice bends the arrow at your heart, and strains the bow, and it
				   is nothing but the mere pleasure of God, and that of an angry God,
				   without any promise or obligation at all, that keeps the arrow one
				   moment from being made drunk with your blood. Thus all you that never
				   passed under a great change of heart, by the mighty power of the Spirit
				   of God upon your souls; all you that were never born again, and made
				   new creatures, and raised from being dead in sin, to a state of new,
				   and before altogether unexperienced light and life, are in the hands of
				   an angry God. However you may have reformed your life in many things,
				   and may have had religious affections, and may keep up a form of
				   religion in your families and closets, and in the house of God, it is
				   nothing but his mere pleasure that keeps you from being this moment
				   swallowed up in everlasting destruction. However unconvinced you may
				   now be of the truth of what you hear, by and by you will be fully
				   convinced of it. Those that are gone from being in the like
				   circumstances with you, see that it was so with them; for destruction
				   came suddenly upon most of them; when they expected nothing of it, and
				   while they were saying, Peace and safety: now they see, that those
				   things on which they depended for peace and safety, were nothing but
				   thin air and empty shadows.
				</p><p>
				   The God that holds you over the pit of hell, much as one holds a
				   spider, or some loathsome insect over the fire, abhors you, and is
				   dreadfully provoked: his wrath towards you burns like fire; he looks
				   upon you as worthy of nothing else, but to be cast into the fire; he is
				   of purer eyes than to bear to have you in his sight; you are ten
				   thousand times more abominable in his eyes, than the most hateful
				   venomous serpent is in ours. You have offended him infinitely more than
				   ever a stubborn rebel did his prince; and yet it is nothing but his
				   hand that holds you from falling into the fire every moment. It is to
				   be ascribed to nothing else, that you did not go to hell the last
				   night; that you was suffered to awake again in this world, after you
				   closed your eyes to sleep. And there is no other reason to be given,
				   why you have not dropped into hell since you arose in the morning, but
				   that God's hand has held you up. There is no other reason to be given
				   why you have not gone to hell, since you have sat here in the house of
				   God, provoking his pure eyes by your sinful wicked manner of attending
				   his solemn worship. Yea, there is nothing else that is to be given as a
				   reason why you do not this very moment drop down into hell.
				</p><p>
				   O sinner! Consider the fearful danger you are in: it is a great furnace
				   of wrath, a wide and bottomless pit, full of the fire of wrath, that
				   you are held over in the hand of that God, whose wrath is provoked and
				   incensed as much against you, as against many of the damned in hell.
				   You hang by a slender thread, with the flames of divine wrath flashing
				   about it, and ready every moment to singe it, and burn it asunder; and
				   you have no interest in any Mediator, and nothing to lay hold of to
				   save yourself, nothing to keep off the flames of wrath, nothing of your
				   own, nothing that you ever have done, nothing that you can do, to
				   induce God to spare you one moment. - And consider here more
				   particularly,
				</p><p>
				    1. Whose wrath it is: it is the wrath of the infinite God. If it were
				       only the wrath of man, though it were of the most potent prince, it
				       would be comparatively little to be regarded. The wrath of kings is
				       very much dreaded, especially of absolute monarchs, who have the
				       possessions and lives of their subjects wholly in their power, to
				       be disposed of at their mere will. <reference osisRef="Prov.20.2">Proverbs 20:2</reference>. "The fear of a king
				       is as the roaring of a lion: Whoso provoketh him to anger, sinneth
				       against his own soul." The subject that very much enrages an
				       arbitrary prince, is liable to suffer the most extreme torments
				       that human art can invent, or human power can inflict. But the
				       greatest earthly potentates in their greatest majesty and strength,
				       and when clothed in their greatest terrors, are but feeble,
				       despicable worms of the dust, in comparison of the great and
				       almighty Creator and King of heaven and earth. It is but little
				       that they can do, when most enraged, and when they have exerted the
				       utmost of their fury. All the kings of the earth, before God, are
				       as grasshoppers; they are nothing, and less than nothing: both
				       their love and their hatred is to be despised. The wrath of the
				       great King of kings, is as much more terrible than theirs, as his
				       majesty is greater. <reference osisRef="Luke.12.4 Luke.12.5">Luke 12:4-5</reference>. "And I say unto you, my friends,
				       Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that, have no
				       more that they can do. But I will forewarn you whom you shall fear:
				       fear him, which after he hath killed, hath power to cast into hell:
				       yea, I say unto you, Fear him."
				</p><p>
				    2. It is the fierceness of his wrath that you are exposed to. We often
				       read of the fury of God; as in <reference osisRef="Isa.59.18">Isaiah 59:18</reference>. "According to their
				       deeds, accordingly he will repay fury to his adversaries." So <reference osisRef="Isa.66.15">Isaiah 66:15</reference>. "For behold, the Lord will come with fire, and with his
				       chariots like a whirlwind, to render his anger with fury, and his
				       rebuke with flames of fire." And in many other places. So, <reference osisRef="Rev.19.15">Revelation of John 19:15</reference>, we read of "the wine press of the fierceness and wrath of
				       Almighty God." The words are exceeding terrible. If it had only
				       been said, "the wrath of God," the words would have implied that
				       which is infinitely dreadful: but it is "the fierceness and wrath
				       of God." The fury of God! the fierceness of Jehovah! Oh, how
				       dreadful that must be! Who can utter or conceive what such
				       expressions carry in them! But it is also "the fierceness and wrath
				       of almighty God." As though there would be a very great
				       manifestation of his almighty power in what the fierceness of his
				       wrath should inflict, as though omnipotence should be as it were
				       enraged, and exerted, as men are wont to exert their strength in
				       the fierceness of their wrath. Oh! then, what will be the
				       consequence! What will become of the poor worms that shall suffer
				       it! Whose hands can be strong? And whose heart can endure? To what
				       a dreadful, inexpressible, inconceivable depth of misery must the
				       poor creature be sunk who shall be the subject of this!
				       Consider this, you that are here present, that yet remain in an
				       unregenerate state. That God will execute the fierceness of his
				       anger, implies, that he will inflict wrath without any pity. When
				       God beholds the ineffable extremity of your case, and sees your
				       torment to be so vastly disproportioned to your strength, and sees
				       how your poor soul is crushed, and sinks down, as it were, into an
				       infinite gloom; he will have no compassion upon you, he will not
				       forbear the executions of his wrath, or in the least lighten his
				       hand; there shall be no moderation or mercy, nor will God then at
				       all stay his rough wind; he will have no regard to your welfare,
				       nor be at all careful lest you should suffer too much in any other
				       sense, than only that you shall not suffer beyond what strict
				       justice requires. Nothing shall be withheld, because it is so hard
				       for you to bear. <reference osisRef="Ezek.8.18">Ezekiel 8:18</reference>. "Therefore will I also deal in fury:
				       mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity; and though they
				       cry in mine ears with a loud voice, yet I will not hear them." Now
				       God stands ready to pity you; this is a day of mercy; you may cry
				       now with some encouragement of obtaining mercy. But when once the
				       day of mercy is past, your most lamentable and dolorous cries and
				       shrieks will be in vain; you will be wholly lost and thrown away of
				       God, as to any regard to your welfare. God will have no other use
				       to put you to, but to suffer misery; you shall be continued in
				       being to no other end; for you will be a vessel of wrath fitted to
				       destruction; and there will be no other use of this vessel, but to
				       be filled full of wrath. God will be so far from pitying you when
				       you cry to him, that it is said he will only "laugh and mock,"
				       <reference osisRef="Prov.1.25 Prov.1.26">Proverbs 1:25-26</reference>,etc.
				       How awful are those words, <reference osisRef="Isa.63.3">Isaiah 63:3</reference>, which are the words of the
				       great God. "I will tread them in mine anger, and will trample them
				       in my fury, and their blood shall be sprinkled upon my garments,
				       and I will stain all my raiment." It is perhaps impossible to
				       conceive of words that carry in them greater manifestations of
				       these three things, viz. contempt, and hatred, and fierceness of
				       indignation. If you cry to God to pity you, he will be so far from
				       pitying you in your doleful case, or showing you the least regard
				       or favour, that instead of that, he will only tread you under foot.
				       And though he will know that you cannot bear the weight of
				       omnipotence treading upon you, yet he will not regard that, but he
				       will crush you under his feet without mercy; he will crush out your
				       blood, and make it fly, and it shall be sprinkled on his garments,
				       so as to stain all his raiment. He will not only hate you, but he
				       will have you in the utmost contempt: no place shall be thought fit
				       for you, but under his feet to be trodden down as the mire of the
				       streets.
				</p><p>
				    3. The misery you are exposed to is that which God will inflict to
				       that end, that he might show what that wrath of Jehovah is. God
				       hath had it on his heart to show to angels and men, both how
				       excellent his love is, and also how terrible his wrath is.
				       Sometimes earthly kings have a mind to show how terrible their
				       wrath is, by the extreme punishments they would execute on those
				       that would provoke them. Nebuchadnezzar, that mighty and haughty
				       monarch of the Chaldean empire, was willing to show his wrath when
				       enraged with Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego; and accordingly gave
				       orders that the burning fiery furnace should be heated seven times
				       hotter than it was before; doubtless, it was raised to the utmost
				       degree of fierceness that human art could raise it. But the great
				       God is also willing to show his wrath, and magnify his awful
				       majesty and mighty power in the extreme sufferings of his enemies.
				       <reference osisRef="Rom.9.22">Romans 9:22</reference>. "What if God, willing to show his wrath, and to make his
				       power known, endured with much long-suffering the vessels of wrath
				       fitted to destruction?" And seeing this is his design, and what he
				       has determined, even to show how terrible the unrestrained wrath,
				       the fury and fierceness of Jehovah is, he will do it to effect.
				       There will be something accomplished and brought to pass that will
				       be dreadful with a witness. When the great and angry God hath risen
				       up and executed his awful vengeance on the poor sinner, and the
				       wretch is actually suffering the infinite weight and power of his
				       indignation, then will God call upon the whole universe to behold
				       that awful majesty and mighty power that is to be seen in it. <reference osisRef="Isa.33.12 Isa.33.13 Isa.33.14">Isaiah 33:12-14</reference>. "And the people shall be as the burnings of lime, as
				       thorns cut up shall they be burnt in the fire. Hear ye that are far
				       off, what I have done; and ye that are near, acknowledge my might.
				       The sinners in Zion are afraid; fearfulness hath surprised the
				       hypocrites," etc.
				       Thus it will be with you that are in an unconverted state, if you
				       continue in it; the infinite might, and majesty, and terribleness
				       of the omnipotent God shall be magnified upon you, in the ineffable
				       strength of your torments. You shall be tormented in the presence
				       of the holy angels, and in the presence of the Lamb; and when you
				       shall be in this state of suffering, the glorious inhabitants of
				       heaven shall go forth and look on the awful spectacle, that they
				       may see what the wrath and fierceness of the Almighty is; and when
				       they have seen it, they will fall down and adore that great power
				       and majesty. <reference osisRef="Isa.66.23 Isa.66.24">Isaiah 66:23-24</reference>. "And it shall come to pass, that from
				       one new moon to another, and from one sabbath to another, shall all
				       flesh come to worship before me, saith the Lord. And they shall go
				       forth and look upon the carcasses of the men that have transgressed
				       against me; for their worm shall not die, neither shall their fire
				       be quenched, and they shall be an abhorring unto all flesh."
				</p><p>
				    4. It is everlasting wrath. It would be dreadful to suffer this
				       fierceness and wrath of Almighty God one moment; but you must
				       suffer it to all eternity. There will be no end to this exquisite
				       horrible misery. When you look forward, you shall see a long for
				       ever, a boundless duration before you, which will swallow up your
				       thoughts, and amaze your soul; and you will absolutely despair of
				       ever having any deliverance, any end, any mitigation, any rest at
				       all. You will know certainly that you must wear out long ages,
				       millions of millions of ages, in wrestling and conflicting with
				       this almighty merciless vengeance; and then when you have so done,
				       when so many ages have actually been spent by you in this manner,
				       you will know that all is but a point to what remains. So that your
				       punishment will indeed be infinite. Oh, who can express what the
				       state of a soul in such circumstances is! All that we can possibly
				       say about it, gives but a very feeble, faint representation of it;
				       it is inexpressible and inconceivable: For "who knows the power of
				       God's anger?"
				</p><p>
				
				   How dreadful is the state of those that are daily and hourly in the
				   danger of this great wrath and infinite misery! But this is the dismal
				   case of every soul in this congregation that has not been born again,
				   however moral and strict, sober and religious, they may otherwise be.
				   Oh that you would consider it, whether you be young or old! There is
				   reason to think, that there are many in this congregation now hearing
				   this discourse, that will actually be the subjects of this very misery
				   to all eternity. We know not who they are, or in what seats they sit,
				   or what thoughts they now have. It may be they are now at ease, and
				   hear all these things without much disturbance, and are now flattering
				   themselves that they are not the persons, promising themselves that
				   they shall escape. If we knew that there was one person, and but one,
				   in the whole congregation, that was to be the subject of this misery,
				   what an awful thing would it be to think of! If we knew who it was,
				   what an awful sight would it be to see such a person! How might all the
				   rest of the congregation lift up a lamentable and bitter cry over him!
				   But, alas! instead of one, how many is it likely will remember this
				   discourse in hell? And it would be a wonder, if some that are now
				   present should not be in hell in a very short time, even before this
				   year is out. And it would be no wonder if some persons, that now sit
				   here, in some seats of this meeting-house, in health, quiet and secure,
				   should be there before tomorrow morning. Those of you that finally
				   continue in a natural condition, that shall keep out of hell longest
				   will be there in a little time! your damnation does not slumber; it
				   will come swiftly, and, in all probability, very suddenly upon many of
				   you. You have reason to wonder that you are not already in hell. It is
				   doubtless the case of some whom you have seen and known, that never
				   deserved hell more than you, and that heretofore appeared as likely to
				   have been now alive as you. Their case is past all hope; they are
				   crying in extreme misery and perfect despair; but here you are in the
				   land of the living and in the house of God, and have an opportunity to
				   obtain salvation. What would not those poor damned hopeless souls give
				   for one day's opportunity such as you now enjoy!
				</p><p>
				   And now you have an extraordinary opportunity, a day wherein Christ has
				   thrown the door of mercy wide open, and stands in calling and crying
				   with a loud voice to poor sinners; a day wherein many are flocking to
				   him, and pressing into the kingdom of God. Many are daily coming from
				   the east, west, north and south; many that were very lately in the same
				   miserable condition that you are in, are now in a happy state, with
				   their hearts filled with love to him who has loved them, and washed
				   them from their sins in his own blood, and rejoicing in hope of the
				   glory of God. How awful is it to be left behind at such a day! To see
				   so many others feasting, while you are pining and perishing! To see so
				   many rejoicing and singing for joy of heart, while you have cause to
				   mourn for sorrow of heart, and howl for vexation of spirit! How can you
				   rest one moment in such a condition? Are not your souls as precious as
				   the souls of the people at Suffield, where they are flocking from day
				   to day to Christ?
				</p><p>
				   Are there not many here who have lived long in the world, and are not
				   to this day born again? and so are aliens from the commonwealth of
				   Israel, and have done nothing ever since they have lived, but treasure
				   up wrath against the day of wrath? Oh, sirs, your case, in an especial
				   manner, is extremely dangerous. Your guilt and hardness of heart is
				   extremely great. Do you not see how generality persons of your years
				   are passed over and left, in the present remarkable and wonderful
				   dispensation of God's mercy? You had need to consider yourselves, and
				   awake thoroughly out of sleep. You cannot bear the fierceness and wrath
				   of the infinite God. - And you, young men, and young women, will you
				   neglect this precious season which you now enjoy, when so many others
				   of your age are renouncing all youthful vanities, and flocking to
				   Christ? You especially have now an extraordinary opportunity; but if
				   you neglect it, it will soon be with you as with those persons who
				   spent all the precious days of youth in sin, and are now come to such a
				   dreadful pass in blindness and hardness. - And you, children, who are
				   unconverted, do not you know that you are going down to hell, to bear
				   the dreadful wrath of that God, who is now angry with you every day and
				   every night? Will you be content to be the children of the devil, when
				   so many other children in the land are converted, and are become the
				   holy and happy children of the King of kings?
				</p><p>
				   And let every one that is yet out of Christ, and hanging over the pit
				   of hell, whether they be old men and women, or middle aged, or young
				   people, or little children, now hearken to the loud calls of God's word
				   and providence. This acceptable year of the Lord, a day of such great
				   favour to some, will doubtless be a day of as remarkable vengeance to
				   others. Men's hearts harden, and their guilt increases apace at such a
				   day as this, if they neglect their souls; and never was there so great
				   danger of such persons being given up to hardness of heart and
				   blindness of mind. God seems now to be hastily gathering in his elect
				   in all parts of the land; and probably the greater part of adult
				   persons that ever shall be saved, will be brought in now in a little
				   time, and that it will be as it was on the great out-pouring of the
				   Spirit upon the Jews in the apostles' days; the election will obtain,
				   and the rest will be blinded. If this should be the case with you, you
				   will eternally curse this day, and will curse the day that ever you was
				   born, to see such a season of the pouring out of God's Spirit, and will
				   wish that you had died and gone to hell before you had seen it. Now
				   undoubtedly it is, as it was in the days of John the Baptist, the axe
				   is in an extraordinary manner laid at the root of the trees, that every
				   tree which brings not forth good fruit, may be hewn down and cast into
				   the fire.
				</p><p>
				   Therefore, let every one that is out of Christ, now awake and fly from
				   the wrath to come. The wrath of Almighty God is now undoubtedly hanging
				   over a great part of this congregation. Let every one fly out of Sodom:
				   "Haste and escape for your lives, look not behind you, escape to the
				   mountain, lest you be consumed."
				</p>
			</div>

			<div type="chapter" osisID="A Divine and Supernatural Light">
				<title>A Divine and Supernatural Light</title>
				<p>
					Jonathan Edwards (1703-1758)
				</p><p>
                        A Divine and Supernatural Light,
				</p><p>
                        Immediately Imparted to the Soul
				</p><p>
                             by the Spirit of God,
				</p><p>
               Shown to be Both Scriptural and Rational Doctrine
				</p><p>
				Preached at Northampton, and published at the desire of some of the hearers, in the year 1734.
				</p><p>
				    And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Barjona: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but
   					my Father which is in heaven. <reference osisRef="Matt.16.17">Matthew 16:17</reference>
				</p><p>
				   CHRIST says these words to Peter upon occasion of his professing his
				   faith in him as the Son of God. Our Lord was inquiring of his
				   disciples, who men said he was; not that he needed to be informed, but
				   only to introduce and give occasion to what follows. They answer, that
				   some said he was John the Baptist, and some Elias, and others Jeremias,
				   or one of the Prophets. When they had thus given an account who others
				   said he was, Christ asks them, who they said he was? Simon Peter, whom
				   we find always zealous and forward, was the first to answer: he readily
				   replied to the question, Thou art Christ, the Son of the living God.
				</p><p>
				   Upon this occasion, Christ says as he does to him, and of him in the
				   text: in which we may observe,
				</p><p>
				   1. That Peter is pronounced blessed on this account. Blessed art thou
				   - "Thou art a happy man, that thou art not ignorant of this, that I am
				   Christ, the Son of the living God. Thou art distinguishingly happy.
				   Others are blinded, and have dark and deluded apprehensions, as you
				   have now given an account, some thinking that I am Elias, and some that
				   I am Jeremias, and some one thing, and some another; but none of them
				   thinking right, all of them misled. Happy art thou, that art so
				   distinguished as to know the truth in this matter." 2. The evidence of
				   this his happiness declared; viz., that God, and he only, had revealed
				   it to him. This is an evidence of his being blessed.
				</p><p>
				   First, As it shows how peculiarly favored he was of God above others;
				   q.d., "How highly favored art thou, that others that are wise and great
				   men, the Scribes, Pharisees, and Rulers, and the nation in general, are
				   left in darkness, to follow their own misguided apprehensions; and that
				   thou shouldst be singled out, as it were, by name, that my Heavenly
				   Father should thus set his love, on thee, Simon Bar-jona. This argues
				   thee blessed, that thou shouldst thus be the object of God's
				   distinguishing love."
				</p><p>
				   Secondly, It evidences his blessedness also, as it intimates that this
				   knowledge is above any that flesh and blood can reveal. "This is such
				   knowledge as only my Father which is in heaven can give: it is too high
				   and excellent to be communicated by such means as other knowledge is.
				   Thou art blessed, that thou knowest that which God alone can teach
				   thee."
				</p><p>
				   The original of this knowledge is here declared, both negatively and
				   positively. Positively, as God is here declared the author of it.
				   Negatively, as it is declared, that flesh and blood had not revealed
				   it. God is the author of all knowledge and understanding whatsoever. He
				   is the author of the knowledge that is obtained by human learning: he
				   is the author of all moral prudence, and of the knowledge and skill
				   that men have in their secular business. Thus it is said of all in
				   Israel that were wise-hearted, and skilled in embroidering, that God
				   had filled them with the spirit of wisdom, <reference osisRef="Exod.28.3">Exodus 28:3</reference>.
				</p><p>
				   God is the author of such knowledge; but yet not so but that flesh and
				   blood reveals it. Mortal men are capable of imparting the knowledge of
				   human arts and sciences, and skill in temporal affairs. God is the
				   author of such knowledge by those means: flesh and blood is employed as
				   the mediate or second cause of it; he conveys it by the power and
				   influence of natural means. But this spiritual knowledge, spoken of in
				   the text, is what God is the author of, and none else: he reveals it,
				   and flesh and blood reveals it not. He imparts this knowledge
				   immediately, not making use of any intermediate natural causes, as he
				   does in other knowledge.
				</p><p>
				   What had passed in the preceding discourse naturally occasioned Christ
				   to observe this; because the disciples had been telling how others did
				   not know him, but were generally mistaken about him, and divided and
				   confounded in their opinions of him: but Peter had declared his assured
				   faith, that he was the Son of God. Now it was natural to observe, how
				   it was not flesh and blood that had revealed it to him, but God: for if
				   this knowledge were dependent on natural causes or means, how came it
				   to pass that they, a company of poor fishermen, illiterate men, and
				   persons of low education, attained to the knowledge of the truth; while
				   the Scribes and Pharisees, men of vastly higher advantages, and greater
				   knowledge and sagacity in other matters, remained in ignorance? This
				   could be owing only to the gracious distinguishing influence and
				   revelation of the Spirit of God. Hence, what I would make the subject
				   of my present discourse from these words, is this
				</p><p>
				    DOCTRINE
				</p><p>
				   That there is such a thing as a spiritual and divine light immediately
				   imparted to the soul by God, of a different nature from any that is
				   obtained by natural means.-And on this subject I would,
				</p><p>
				   I. Show what this divine light is.
				</p><p>
				   II. How it is given immediately by God, and not obtained by natural
				   means.
				</p><p>
				   III. Show the truth of the doctrine.
				</p><p>
				   And then conclude with a brief improvement.
				</p><p>
				   I. I would show what this spiritual and divine light is. And in order
				   to it, would show,
				</p><p>
				   First, In a few things what it is not. And here,
				</p><p>
				   1. Those convictions that natural men may have of their sin and misery,
				   is not this spiritual and divine light. Men in a natural condition may
				   have convictions of the guilt that lies upon them, and of the anger of
				   God, and their danger of divine vengeance. Such convictions are from
				   light or sensibleness of truth. That some sinners have a greater
				   conviction of their guilt and misery than others, is because some have
				   more light, or more of an apprehension of truth than others. And this
				   light and conviction may be from the Spirit of God; the Spirit
				   convinces men of sin: but yet nature is much more concerned in it than
				   in the communication of that spiritual and divine light that is spoken
				   of in the doctrine; it is from the Spirit of God only as assisting
				   natural principles, and not as infusing any new principles. Common
				   grace differs from special, in that it influences only by assisting of
				   nature; and not by imparting grace, or bestowing any thing above
				   nature. The light that is obtained is wholly natural, or of no superior
				   kind to what mere nature attains to, though more of that kind be
				   obtained than would be obtained if men were left wholly to themselves:
				   or, in other words, common grace only assists the faculties of the soul
				   to do that more fully which they do by nature, as natural conscience or
				   reason will, by mere nature, make a man sensible of guilt, and will
				   accuse and condemn him when he has done amiss. Conscience is a
				   principle natural to men; and the work that it doth naturally, or of
				   itself, is to give an apprehension of right and wrong, and to suggest
				   to the mind the relation that there is between right and wrong, and a
				   retribution. The Spirit of God, in those convictions which unregenerate
				   men sometimes have, assists conscience to do this work in a further
				   degree than it would do if they were left to themselves: he helps it
				   against those things that tend to stupify it, and obstruct its
				   exercise. But in the renewing and sanctifying work of the Holy Ghost,
				   those things are wrought in the soul that are above nature, and of
				   which there is nothing of the like kind in the soul by nature; and they
				   are caused to exist in the soul habitually, and according to such a
				   stated constitution or law that lays such a foundation for exercises in
				   a continued course, as is called a principle of nature. Not only are
				   remaining principles assisted to do their work more freely and fully,
				   but those principles are restored that were utterly destroyed by the
				   fall; and the mind thence forward habitually exerts those acts that the
				   dominion of sin had made it as wholly destitute of, as a dead body is
				   of vital acts.
				</p><p>
				   The Spirit of God acts in a very different manner in the one case, from
				   what he doth in the other. He may indeed act upon the mind of a natural
				   man, but he acts in the mind of a saint as an indwelling vital
				   principle. He acts upon the mind of an unregenerate person as an
				   extrinsic, occasional agent; for in acting upon them, he doth not unite
				   himself to them; for notwithstanding all his influences that they may
				   be the subjects of, they are still sensual, having not the Spirit, Jude
				   19. But he unites himself with the mind of a saint, takes him for his
				   temple, actuates and influences him as a new supernatural principle of
				   life and action. There is this difference, that the Spirit of God, in
				   acting in the soul of a godly man, exerts and communicates himself
				   there in his own proper nature. Holiness is the proper nature of the
				   Spirit of God. The Holy Spirit operates in the minds of the godly, by
				   uniting himself to them, and living in them, and exerting his own
				   nature in the exercise of their faculties. The Spirit of God may act
				   upon a creature, and yet not in acting communicate himself. The Spirit
				   of God may act upon inanimate creatures; as, the Spirit moved upon the
				   face of the waters, in the beginning of the creation; so the Spirit of
				   God may act upon the minds of men many ways, and communicate himself no
				   more than when he acts upon an inanimate creature. For instance, he may
				   excite thoughts in them, may assist their natural reason and
				   understanding, or may assist other natural principles, and this without
				   any union with the soul, but may act, as it were, as upon an external
				   object. But as he acts in his holy influences and spiritual operations,
				   he acts in a way of peculiar communication of himself; so that the
				   subject is thence denominated spiritual.
				</p><p>
				   2. This spiritual and divine light does not consist in any impression
				   made upon the imagination. It is no impression upon the mind, as though
				   one saw any thing with the bodily eyes: it is no imagination or idea of
				   an outward light or glory, or any beauty of form or countenance, or a
				   visible lustre or brightness of any object. The imagination may be
				   strongly impressed with such things; but this is not spiritual light.
				   Indeed when the mind has a lively discovery of spiritual things, and is
				   greatly affected by the power of divine light, it may, and probably
				   very commonly doth, much affect the imagination; so that impressions of
				   an outward beauty or brightness may accompany those spiritual
				   discoveries. But spiritual light is not that impression upon the
				   imagination, but an exceeding different thing from it. Natural men may
				   have lively impressions on their imaginations; and we cannot determine
				   but the devil, who transforms himself into an angel of light, may cause
				   imaginations of an outward beauty, or visible glory, and of sounds and
				   speeches, and other such things; but these are things of a vastly
				   inferior nature to spiritual light.
				</p><p>
				   3. This spiritual light is not the suggesting of any new truths or
				   propositions not contained in the word of God. This suggesting of new
				   truths or doctrines to the mind, independent of any antecedent
				   revelation of those propositions, either in word or writing, is
				   inspiration; such as the prophets and apostles had, and such as some
				   enthusiasts pretend to. But this spiritual light that I am speaking of,
				   is quite a different thing from inspiration: it reveals no new
				   doctrine, it suggests no new proposition to the mind, it teaches no new
				   thing of God, or Christ, or another world, not taught in the Bible, but
				   only gives a due apprehension of those things that are taught in the
				   word of God.
				</p><p>
				   4. It is not every affecting view that men have of the things of
				   religion that is this spiritual and divine light. Men by mere
				   principles of nature are capable of being affected with things that
				   have a special relation to religion as well as other things. A person
				   by mere nature, for instance, may be liable to be affected with the
				   story of Jesus Christ, and the sufferings he underwent, as well as by
				   any other tragical story: he may be the more affected with it from the
				   interest he conceives mankind to have in it: yea, he may be affected
				   with it without believing it; as well as a man may be affected with
				   what he reads in a romance, or sees acted in a stage play. He may be
				   affected with a lively and eloquent description of many pleasant things
				   that attend the state of the blessed in heaven, as well as his
				   imagination be entertained by a romantic description of the
				   pleasantness of fairy land, or the like. And that common belief of the
				   truth of the things of religion, that persons may have from education
				   or otherwise, may help forward their affection. We read in Scripture of
				   many that were greatly affected with things of a religious nature, who
				   yet are there represented as wholly graceless, and many of them very
				   ill men. A person therefore may have affecting views of the things of
				   religion, and yet be very destitute of spiritual light. Flesh and blood
				   may be the author of this: one man may give another an affecting view
				   of divine things with but common assistance: but God alone can give a
				   spiritual discovery of them. - But I proceed to show,
				</p><p>
				   Secondly, Positively what this spiritual and divine light is.
				</p><p>
				   And it may be thus described: a true sense of the divine excellency of
				   the things revealed in the word of God, and a conviction of the truth
				   and reality of them thence arising. This spiritual light primarily
				   consists in the former of these, viz., a real sense and apprehension of
				   the divine excellency of things revealed in the word of God. A
				   spiritual and saving conviction of the truth and reality of these
				   things, arises from such a sight of their divine excellency and glory;
				   so that this conviction of their truth is an effect and natural
				   consequence of this sight of their divine glory. There is therefore in
				   this spiritual light,
				</p><p>
				   1. A true sense of the divine and superlative excellency of the things
				   of religion; a real sense of the excellency of God and Jesus Christ,
				   and of the work of redemption, and the ways and works of God revealed
				   in the gospel. There is a divine and superlative glory in these things;
				   an excellency that is of a vastly higher kind, and more sublime nature
				   than in other things; a glory greatly distinguishing them from all that
				   is earthly and temporal. He that is spiritually enlightened truly
				   apprehends and sees it, or has a sense of it. He does not merely
				   rationally believe that God is glorious, but he has a sense of the
				   gloriousness of God in his heart. There is not only a rational belief
				   that God is holy, and that holiness is a good thing, but there is a
				   sense of the loveliness of God's holiness. There is not only a
				   speculatively judging that God is gracious, but a sense how amiable God
				   is upon that account, or a sense of the beauty of this divine
				   attribute.
				</p><p>
				   There is a twofold understanding or knowledge of good that God has made
				   the mind of man capable of. The first, that which is merely speculative
				   and notional; as when a person only speculatively judges that any thing
				   is, which, by the agreement of mankind, is called good or excellent,
				   viz., that which is most to general advantage, and between which and a
				   reward there is a suitableness, and the like. And the other is, that
				   which consists in the sense of the heart: as when there is a sense of
				   the beauty, amiableness, or sweetness of a thing; so that the heart is
				   sensible of pleasure and delight in the presence of the idea of it. In
				   the former is exercised merely the speculative faculty, or the
				   understanding, strictly so called, or as spoken of in distinction from
				   the will or disposition of the soul. In the latter, the will, or
				   inclination, or heart, are mainly concerned.
				</p><p>
				   Thus there is a difference between having an opinion, that God is holy
				   and gracious, and having a sense of the loveliness and beauty of that
				   holiness and grace. There is a difference between having a rational
				   judgment that honey is sweet, and having a sense of its sweetness. A
				   man may have the former, that knows not how honey tastes; but a man
				   cannot have the latter unless he has an idea of the taste of honey in
				   his mind. So there is a difference between believing that a person is
				   beautiful, and having a sense of his beauty. The former may be obtained
				   by hearsay, but the latter only by seeing the countenance. There is a
				   wide difference between mere speculative rational judging any thing to
				   be excellent, and having a sense of its sweetness and beauty. The
				   former rests only in the head, speculation only is concerned in it; but
				   the heart is concerned in the latter. When the heart is sensible of the
				   beauty and amiableness of a thing, it necessarily feels pleasure in the
				   apprehension. It is implied in a person's being heartily sensible of
				   the loveliness of a thing, that the idea of it is sweet and pleasant to
				   his soul; which is a far different thing from having a rational opinion
				   that it is excellent.
				</p><p>
				   2. There arises from this sense of divine excellency of things
				   contained in the word of God, a conviction of the truth and reality of
				   them; and that either directly or indirectly.
				</p><p>
				   First, Indirectly, and that two ways.
				</p><p>
				   1. As the prejudices that are in the heart, against the truth of divine
				   things, are hereby removed; so that the mind becomes susceptive of the
				   due force of rational arguments for their truth. The mind of man is
				   naturally full of prejudices against the truth of divine things: it is
				   full of enmity against the doctrines of the gospel; which is a
				   disadvantage to those arguments that prove their truth, and causes them
				   to lose their force upon the mind. But when a person has discovered to
				   him the divine excellency of Christian doctrines, this destroys the
				   enmity, removes those prejudices, and sanctifies the reason, and causes
				   it to lie open to the force of arguments for their truth.
				</p><p>
				   Hence was the different effect that Christ's miracles had to convince
				   the disciples from what they had to convince the Scribes and Pharisees.
				   Not that they had a stronger reason, or had their reason more improved;
				   but their reason was sanctified, and those blinding prejudices, that
				   the Scribes and Pharisees were under, were removed by the sense they
				   had of the excellency of Christ and his doctrine.
				</p><p>
				   2. It not only removes the hinderances of reason, but positively helps
				   reason. It makes even the speculative notions the more lively. It
				   engages the attention of the mind, with the fixedness and intenseness
				   to that kind of objects; which causes it to have a clearer view of
				   them, and enables it more clearly to see their mutual relations, and
				   occasions it to take more notice of them. The ideas themselves that
				   otherwise are dim and obscure, are by this means impressed with the
				   greater strength, and have a light cast upon them; so that the mind can
				   better judge of them. As he that beholds the objects on the face of the
				   earth, when the light of the sun is cast upon them; so that the mind
				   can better judge of them. As he that beholds the objects on the face of
				   the earth, when the light of the sun is cast upon them, is under
				   greater advantage to discern them in their true forms and mutual
				   relations, than he that sees them in a dim starlight or twilight.
				</p><p>
				   The mind having a sensibleness of the excellency of divine objects,
				   dwells upon them with delight; and the powers of the soul are more
				   awakened and enlivened to employ themselves in the contemplation of
				   them, and exert themselves more fully and much more to the purpose. The
				   beauty and sweetness of the objects draws on the faculties, and draws
				   forth their exercises: so that reason itself is under far greater
				   advantages for its proper and free exercises, and to attain its proper
				   end, free of darkness and delusion. - But,
				</p><p>
				   Secondly, A true sense of the divine excellency of the things of God's
				   word doth more directly and immediately convince of the truth of them;
				   and that because the excellency of these things is so superlative.
				   There is a beauty in them that is so divine and godlike, that is
				   greatly and evidently distinguishing of them from things merely human,
				   or that men are the inventors and authors of; a glory that is so high
				   and great, that when clearly seen, commands assent to their divinity
				   and reality. When there is an actual and lively discovery of this
				   beauty and excellency, it will not allow of any such thought as that it
				   is a human work, or the fruit of men's invention. This evidence that
				   they that are spiritually enlightened have of the truth of the things
				   of religion, is a kind of intuitive and immediate evidence. They
				   believe the doctrines of God's word to be divine, because they see
				   divinity in them; i.e., they see a divine, and transcendent, and most
				   evidently distinguishing glory in them; such a glory as, if clearly
				   seen, does not leave room to doubt of their being of God, and not of
				   men.
				</p><p>
				   Such a conviction of the truth of religion as this, arising, these
				   ways, from a sense of the divine excellency of them, is that true
				   spiritual conviction that there is in saving faith. And this original
				   of it, is that by which it is most essentially distinguished from that
				   common assent, which unregenerate men are capable of.
				</p><p>
				   II. I proceed now to the second thing proposed, viz., to show how this
				   light is immediately given by God, and not obtained by natural means.
				   And here,
				</p><p>
				   1. It is not intended that the natural faculties are not made use of in
				   it. The natural faculties are the subject of this light: and they are
				   the subject in such a manner, that they are not merely passive, but
				   active in it; the acts and exercises of man's understanding are
				   concemed and made use of in it. God, in letting in this light into the
				   soul, deals with man according to his nature, or as a rational
				   creature; and makes use of his human faculties. But yet this light is
				   not the less immediately from God for that; though the faculties are
				   made use of, it is as the subject and not as the cause; and that acting
				   of the faculties in it, is not the cause, but is either implied in the
				   thing itself (in the light that is imparted) or is the consequence of
				   it. As the use that we make of our eyes in beholding various objects,
				   when the sun arises, is not the cause of the light that discovers those
				   objects to us.
				</p><p>
				   2. It is not intended that outward means have no concern in this
				   affair. As I have observed already, it is not in this affair, as it is
				   in inspiration, where new truths are suggested: for here is by this
				   light only given a due apprehension of the same truths that are
				   revealed in the word of God; and therefore it is not given without the
				   word. The gospel is made use of in this affair: this light is the
				   "light of the glorious gospel of Christ", <reference osisRef="2Cor.4.4">2 Corinthians 4:4</reference>. The gospel is as
				   a glass by which this light is conveyed to us, <reference osisRef="1Cor.13.12">1 Corinthians 13:12</reference>. "Now we
				   see through a glass." - But,
				</p><p>
				   3. When it is said that this light is given immediately by God, and not
				   obtained by natural means, hereby is intended, that it is given by God
				   without making use of any means that operate by their own power, or a
				   natural force God makes use of means; but it is not as mediate causes
				   to produce this effect. There are not truly any second causes of it;
				   but it is produced by God immediately. The word of God is no proper
				   cause of this effect: it does not operate by any natural force in it.
				   The word of God is only made use of to convey to the mind the subject
				   matter of this saving instruction: and this indeed it doth convey to us
				   by natural force or influence. It conveys to our minds these and those
				   doctrines; it is the cause of the notion of them in our heads, but not
				   of the sense of the divine excellency of them in our hearts. Indeed a
				   person cannot have spiritual light without the word. But that does not
				   argue, that the word properly causes that light. The mind cannot see
				   the excellency of any doctrine, unless that doctrine be first in the
				   mind; but the seeing of the excellency of the doctrine may be
				   immediately from the Spirit of God; though the conveying of the
				   doctrine or proposition itself may be by the word. So that the notions
				   that are the subject matter of this light, are conveyed to the mind by
				   the word of God; but that due sense of the heart, wherein this light
				   formally consists, is immediately by the Spirit of God. As for
				   instance, that notion that there is a Christ, and that Christ is holy
				   and gracious, is conveyed to the mind by the word of God: but the sense
				   of the excellency of Christ by reason of that holiness and grace, is
				   nevertheless immediately the work of the Holy Spirit. - I come now,
				</p><p>
				   III. To show the truth of the doctrine; that is, to show that there is
				   such a thing as that spiritual light that has been described, thus
				   immediately let into the mind by God. And here I would show briefly,
				   that this doctrine is both scriptural and rational.
				</p><p>
				   First, It is scriptural. My text is not only full to the purpose, but
				   it is a doctrine that the Scripture abounds in. We are there abundantly
				   taught, that the saints differ from the ungodly in this, that they have
				   the knowledge of God, and a sight of God, and of Jesus Christ. I shall
				   mention but few texts of many. <reference osisRef="1John.3.6">1 John 3:6</reference>, "Whosoever sinneth, has not
				   seen him, nor known him." 3 John 11, "He that doth good, is of God: but
				   he that doth evil, hath not seen God." <reference osisRef="John.14.19">John 14:19</reference>, "The world seeth me
				   no more; but ye see me." <reference osisRef="John.17.3">John 17:3</reference>, "And this is eternal life, that
				   they might know thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou
				   hast sent." This knowledge, or sight of God and Christ, cannot be a
				   mere speculative knowledge; because it is spoken of as a seeing and
				   knowing, wherein they differ from the ungodly. And by these Scriptures
				   it must not only be a different knowledge in degree and circumstances,
				   and different in its effects; but it must be entirely different in
				   nature and kind.
				</p><p>
				   And this light and knowledge is always spoken of as immediately given
				   of God, <reference osisRef="Matt.11.25 Matt.11.26 Matt.11.27">Matthew 11:25-27</reference>: "At that time Jesus answered and said, I thank
				   thee O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because thou hast hid these
				   things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes.
				   Even so, Father, for so it seemed good in thy sight. All things are
				   delivered unto me of my Father: and no man knoweth the Son but the
				   Father: neither knoweth any man the Father, save the Son, and he to
				   whomsoever the Son will reveal him." Here this effect is ascribed alone
				   to the arbitrary operation, and gift of God, bestowing this knowledge
				   on whom he will, and distinguishing those with it, that have the least
				   natural advantage or means for knowledge, even babes, when it is denied
				   to the wise and prudent. And the imparting of the knowledge of God is
				   here appropriated to the Son of God, as his sole prerogative. And
				   again, <reference osisRef="2Cor.4.6">2 Corinthians 4:6</reference>, "For God, who commanded the light to shine out of
				   darkness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge
				   of the glory of God, in the face of Jesus Christ." This plainly shows,
				   that there is such a thing as a discovery of the divine superlative
				   glory and excellency of God and Christ, and that peculiar to the
				   saints: and also, that it is as immediately from God, as light from the
				   sun: and that it is the immediate effect of his power and will; for it
				   is compared to God's creating the light by his powerful word in the
				   beginning of the creation; and is said to be by the Spirit of the Lord,
				   in the 18th verse of the preceding chapter. God is spoken of as giving
				   the knowledge of Christ in conversion, as of what before was hidden and
				   unseen in that. <reference osisRef="Gal.1.15 Gal.1.16">Galatians 1:15-16</reference>, "But when it pleased God, who separated
				   me from my mother's womb, and called me by his grace, to reveal his Son
				   in me." The Scripture also speaks plainly of such a knowledge of the
				   word of God, as has been described, as the immediate gift of God, <reference osisRef="Ps.119.18">Psalms 119:18</reference>: "Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wondrous things out of
				   thy law." What could the Psalmist mean when he begged of God to open
				   his eyes? Was he ever blind? Might he not have resort to the law and
				   see every word and sentence in it when he pleased? and what could he
				   mean by those wondrous things? Was it the wonderful stories of the
				   creation, and deluge, and Israel's passing through the Red Sea, and the
				   like? Were not his eyes open to read these strange things when he
				   would? Doubtless by wondrous things in God's law, he had respect to
				   those distinguishing and wonderful excellencies, and marvellous
				   manifestations of the divine perfections, and glory, that there was in
				   the commands and doctrines of the word, and those works and counsels of
				   God that were there revealed. So the Scripture speaks of a knowledge of
				   God's dispensation, and covenant of mercy, and way of grace towards his
				   people, as peculiar to the saints, and given only by God, <reference osisRef="Ps.25.14">Psalms 25:14</reference>:
				   "The secret of the Lord is with them that fear him; and he will show
				   them his covenant."
				</p><p>
				   And that a true and saving belief of the truth of religion is that
				   which arises from such a discovery, is also what the Scripture teaches.
				   As <reference osisRef="John.6.40">John 6:40</reference>, "And this is the will of him that sent me, that every one
				   which seeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlasting life;"
				   where it is plain that a true faith is what arises from a spiritual
				   sight of Christ. and <reference osisRef="John.17.6 John.17.7 John.17.8">John 17:6-8</reference>, "I have manifested thy name unto
				   the men which thou gavest me out of the world. Now they have known that
				   all things whatsoever thou hast given me, are of thee. For I have given
				   unto them the words which thou gavest me; and they have received them,
				   and have known surely that I came out from thee, and they have believed
				   that thou didst send me;" where Christ's manifesting God's name to the
				   disciples, or giving them the knowledge of God, was that whereby they
				   knew that Christ's doctrine was of God, and that Christ himself was of
				   him, proceeded from him, and was sent by him. Again, <reference osisRef="John.12.44 John.12.45 John.12.46">John 12:44-46</reference>,
				   "Jesus cried and said, He that believeth on me, believeth not on me,
				   but on him that sent me. And he that seeth me, seeth him that sent me.
				   I am come a light into the world, that whosoever believeth on me,
				   should not abide in darkness." Their believing in Christ, and
				   spiritually seeing him, are spoken of as running parallel.
				</p><p>
				   Christ condemns the Jews that they did not know that he was the
				   Messiah, and that his doctrine was true, from an inward distinguishing
				   taste and relish of what was divine, in <reference osisRef="Luke.12.56 Luke.12.57">Luke 12:56-57</reference>. He having there
				   blamed the Jews, that though they could discern the face of the sky and
				   of the earth, and signs of the weather, that yet they could not discern
				   those times; or as it is expressed in Matthew, the signs of those
				   times; he adds, yea, and why even of your own selves, judge ye not what
				   is right? i.e., without extrinsic signs. Why have ye not that sense of
				   true excellency, whereby ye may distinguish that which is holy and
				   divine? Why have ye not that savor of the things of God, by which you
				   may see the distinguishing glory, and evident divinity of me and my
				   doctrine?
				</p><p>
				   The Apostle Peter mentions it as what gave them (the apostles) good and
				   well grounded assurance of the truth of the gospel, that they had seen
				   the divine glory of Christ. <reference osisRef="2Pet.1.16">2 Peter 1:16</reference>, "For we have not followed
				   cunningly devised fables when we made known unto you the power and
				   coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were eyewitnesses of his majesty."
				   The apostle has respect to that visible glory of Christ which they saw
				   in his transfiguration: that glory was so divine, having such an
				   ineffable appearance and semblance of divine holiness, majesty and
				   grace, that it evidently denoted him to be a divine person. But if a
				   sight of Christ's outward glory might give a rational assurance of his
				   divinity, why may not an apprehension of his spiritual glory do so too?
				   Doubtless Christ's spiritual glory is in itself as distinguishing, and
				   as plainly showing his divinity, as his outward glory, and a great deal
				   more: for his spiritual glory is that wherein his divinity consists;
				   and the outward glory of his transfiguration showed him to be divine,
				   only as it was a remarkable image or representation of that spiritual
				   glory. Doubtless, therefore, he that has had a clear sight of the
				   spiritual glory of Christ, may say, I have not followed cunningly
				   devised fables, but have been an eyewitness of his majesty, upon as
				   good grounds as the apostle, when he had respect to the outward glory
				   of Christ that he had seen. - But this brings me to what was proposed
				   next, viz., to show that,
				</p><p>
				   Secondly, This doctrine is rational.
				</p><p>
				   1. It is rational to suppose, that there is really such an excellency
				   in divine things, that is so transcendent and exceedingly different
				   from what is in other things, that, if it were seen, would most
				   evidently distinguish them. We cannot rationally doubt but that things
				   that are divine, that appertain to the Supreme Being, are vastly
				   different from things that are human; that there is that godlike, high
				   and glorious excellency in them, that does most remarkably difference
				   them from the things that are of men; insomuch that if the difference
				   were but seen, it would have a convincing, satisfying influence upon
				   any one, that they are what they are, viz., divine. What reason can be
				   offered against it? Unless we would argue, that God is not remarkably
				   distinguished in glory from men.
				</p><p>
				   If Christ should now appear to any one as he did on the mount at his
				   transfiguration; or if he should appear to the world in the glory that
				   he now appears in, as he will do at the day of judgment; without doubt,
				   the glory and majesty that he would appear in, would be such as would
				   satisfy every one that he was a divine person, and that religion was
				   true: and it would be a most reasonable, and well grounded conviction
				   too. And why may there not be that stamp of divinity, or divine glory
				   on the word of God, on the scheme and doctrine of the gospel, that may
				   be in like manner distinguishing and as rationally convincing, provided
				   it be but seen? It is rational to suppose, that when God speaks to the
				   world, there should be something in his word or speech vastly different
				   from man's word. Supposing that God never had spoken to the world, but
				   we had noticed that he was about to do it; that he was about to reveal
				   himself from heaven, and speak to us immediately himself, in divine
				   speeches or discourses, as it were from his own mouth, or that he
				   should give us a book of his own inditing; after what manner should we
				   expect that he would speak? Would it not be rational to suppose, that
				   his speech would be exceeding different from man's speech, that he
				   should speak like a God; that is, that there should be such an
				   excellency and sublimity in his speech or word, such a stamp of wisdom,
				   holiness, majesty and other divine perfections, that the word of man,
				   yea of the wisest of men, should appear mean and base in comparison of
				   it? Doubtless it would be thought rational to expect this, and
				   unreasonable to think otherwise. When a wise man speaks in the exercise
				   of his wisdom, there is something in every thing he says, that is very
				   distinguishable from the talk of a little child. So, without doubt, and
				   much more, is the speech of God (if there be any such thing as the
				   speech of God) to be distinguished from that of the wisest of men;
				   agreeably to <reference osisRef="Jer.23.28 Jer.23.29">Jeremiah 23:28-29</reference>. God having there been reproving the false
				   prophets that prophesied in his name, and pretended that what they
				   spake was his word, when indeed it was their own word, says, "The
				   prophet that hath a dream, let him tell a dream; and he that hath my
				   word, let him speak my word faithfully: what is the chaff to the wheat?
				   saith the Lord. Is not my word like as a fire? saith the Lord; and like
				   a hammer that breaketh the rock in pieces?"
				</p><p>
				   2. If there be such a distinguishing excellency in divine things; it is
				   rational to suppose that there may be such a thing as seeing it. What
				   should hinder but that it may be seen? It is no argument, that there is
				   no such thing as such a distinguishing excellency, or that, if there
				   be, that it cannot be seen, that some do not see it, though they may be
				   discerning men in temporal matters. It is not rational to suppose, if
				   there be any such excellency in divine things, that wicked men should
				   see it. It is not rational to suppose, that those whose minds are full
				   of spiritual pollution, and under the power of filthy lusts, should
				   have any relish or sense of divine beauty or excellency; or that their
				   minds should be susceptive of that light that is in its own nature so
				   pure and heavenly. It need not seem at all strange, that sin should so
				   blind the mind, seeing that men's particular natural tempers and
				   dispositions will so much blind them in secular matters; as when men's
				   natural temper is melancholy, jealous, fearful, proud, or the like.
				</p><p>
				   3. It is rational to suppose, that this knowledge should be given
				   immediately by God, and not be obtained by natural means. Upon what
				   account should it seem unreasonable, that there should be any immediate
				   communication between God and the creature? It is strange that men
				   should make any matter of difficulty of it. Why should not he that made
				   all things, still have something immediately to do with the things that
				   he has made? Where lies the great difficulty, if we own the being of a
				   God, and that he created all things out of nothing, of allowing some
				   immediate influence of God on the creation still? And if it be
				   reasonable to suppose it with respect to any part of the creation, it
				   is especially so with respect to reasonable, intelligent creatures; who
				   are next to God in the gradation of the different orders of beings, and
				   whose business is most immediately with God; who were made on purpose
				   for those exercises that do respect God and wherein they have nextly to
				   do with God: for reason teaches, that man was made to serve and glorify
				   his Creator. And if it be rational to suppose that God immediately
				   communicates himself to man in any affair, it is in this. It is
				   rational to suppose that God would reserve that knowledge and wisdom,
				   that is of such a divine and excellent nature, to be bestowed
				   immediately by himself, and that it should not be left in the power of
				   second causes. Spiritual wisdom and grace is that highest and most
				   excellent gift that ever God bestows on any creature: in this the
				   highest excellency and perfection of a rational creature consists. It
				   is also immensely the most important of all divine gifts: it is that
				   wherein man's happiness consists, and on which his everlasting welfare
				   depends. How rational is it to suppose that God, however he has left
				   meaner goods and lower gifts to second causes, and in some sort in
				   their power, yet should reserve this most excellent, divine, and
				   important of all divine communications, in his own hands, to be
				   bestowed immediately by himself, as a thing too great for second causes
				   to be concerned in!
				</p><p>
				   It is rational to suppose, that this blessing should be immediately
				   from God; for there is no gift or benefit that is in itself so nearly
				   related to the divine nature, there is nothing the creature receives
				   that is so much of God, of his nature, so much a participation of the
				   deity: it is a kind of emanation of God's beauty, and is related to God
				   as the light is to the sun. It is therefore congruous and fit, that
				   when it is given of God, it should be nextly from himself, and by
				   himself, according to his own sovereign will.
				</p><p>
				   It is rational to suppose, that it should be beyond a man's power to
				   obtain this knowledge and light by the mere strength of natural reason;
				   for it is not a thing that belongs to reason, to see the beauty and
				   loveliness of spiritual things; it is not a speculative thing, but
				   depends on the sense of the heart. Reason indeed is necessary in order
				   to it, as it is by reason only that we are become the subjects of the
				   means of it; which means I have already shown to be necessary in order
				   to it, though they have no proper causal in the affair. It is by reason
				   that we become possessed of a notion of those doctrines that are the
				   subject matter of this divine light; and reason may many ways be
				   indirectly and remotely an advantage to it. And reason has also to do
				   in the acts that are immediately consequent on this discovery: a seeing
				   the truth of religion from hence, is by reason; though it be but by one
				   step, and the inference be immediate. So reason has to do in that
				   accepting of, and trusting in Christ, that is consequent on it. But if
				   we take reason strictly - not for the faculty of mental perception in
				   general, but for ratiocination, or a power of inferring by arguments -
				   the perceiving of spiritual beauty and excellency no more belongs to
				   reason, than it belongs to the sense of feeling to perceive colours, or
				   to the power of seeing to perceive the sweetness of food. It is out of
				   reason's province to perceive the beauty or loveliness of any thing:
				   such a perception does not belong to that faculty. Reason's work is to
				   perceive truth and not excellency. It is not ratiocination that gives
				   men the perception of the beauty and amiableness of a countenance,
				   though it may be many ways indirectly an advantage to it; yet it is no
				   more reason that immediately perceives it, than it is reason that
				   perceives the sweetness of honey: it depends on the sense of the heart.
				   - Reason may determine that a countenance is beautiful to others, it
				   may determine that honey is sweet to others; but it will never give me
				   a perception of its sweetness.
				</p><p>
				   I will conclude with a very brief improvement of what has been said.
				</p><p>
				   First, This doctrine may lead us to reflect on the goodness of God,
				   that has so ordered it, that a saving evidence of the truth of the
				   gospel is such, as is attainable by persons of mean capacities and
				   advantages, as well as those that are of the greatest parts and
				   learning. If the evidence of the gospel depended only on history, and
				   such reasonings as learned men only are capable of, it would be above
				   the reach of far the greatest part of mankind. But persons with but an
				   ordinary degree of knowledge, are capable, without a long and subtile
				   train of reasoning, to see the divine excellency of the things of
				   religion: they are capable of being taught by the Spirit of God, as
				   well as learned men. The evidence that is this way obtained, is vastly
				   better and more satisfying, than all that can be obtained by the
				   arguings of those that are most learned, and greatest masters of
				   reason. And babes are as capable of knowing these things, as the wise
				   and prudent; and they are often hid from these things, as the wise and
				   prudent; and they are often hid from these when they are revealed to
				   those. <reference osisRef="1Cor.1.26 1Cor.1.27">1 Corinthians 1:26-27</reference>, "For ye see your calling, brethren, how that not
				   many wise men, after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble are
				   called. But God hath chosen the foolish things of the world -."
				</p><p>
				   Secondly, This doctrine may well put us upon examining ourselves,
				   whether we have ever had this divine light, that has been described,
				   let into our souls. If there be such a thing indeed, and it be not only
				   a notion or whimsy of persons of weak and distempered brains, then
				   doubtless it is a thing of great importance, whether we have thus been
				   taught by the Spirit of God; whether the light of the glorious gospel
				   of Christ, who is the image of God, hath shined unto us, giving us the
				   light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ;
				   whether we have seen the Son, and believed on him, or have that faith
				   of gospel-doctrines which arises from a spiritual sight of Christ.
				</p><p>
				   Thirdly, All may hence be exhorted earnestly to seek this spiritual
				   light. To influence and move to it, the following things may be
				   considered.
				</p><p>
				   1. This is the most excellent and divine wisdom that any creature is
				   capable of. It is more excellent than any human learning; it is far
				   more excellent than all the knowledge of the greatest philosophers or
				   statesmen. Yea, the least glimpse of the glory of God in the face of
				   Christ doth more exalt and ennoble the soul, than all the knowledge of
				   those that have the greatest speculative understanding in divinity
				   without grace. This knowledge has the most noble object that is or can
				   be, viz., the divine glory or excellency of God and Christ. The
				   knowledge of these objects is that wherein consists the most excellent
				   knowledge of the angels, yea, of God himself.
				</p><p>
				   2. This knowledge is that which is above all others sweet and joyful.
				   Men have a great deal of pleasure in human knowledge, in studies of
				   natural things; but this is nothing to that joy which arises from this
				   divine light shining into the soul. This light gives a view of those
				   things that are immensely the most exquisitely beautiful, and capable
				   of delighting the eye of the understanding. This spiritual light is the
				   dawning of the light of glory in the heart. There is nothing so
				   powerful as this to support persons in affliction, and to give the mind
				   peace and brightness in this stormy and dark world.
				</p><p>
				   3. This light is such as effectually influences the inclination, and
				   changes the nature of the soul. It assimilates the nature to the divine
				   nature, and changes the soul into an image of the same glory that is
				   beheld. <reference osisRef="2Cor.3.18">2 Corinthians 3:18</reference>, "But we all with open face, beholding as in a
				   glass the glory of the Lord, are changed into the same image, from
				   glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord." This knowledge will
				   wean from the world, and raise the inclination to heavenly things. It
				   will turn the heart to God as the fountain of good, and to choose him
				   for the only portion. This light, and this only, will bring the soul to
				   a saving close with Christ. It conforms the heart to the gospel,
				   mortifies its enmity and opposition against the scheme of salvation
				   therein revealed: it causes the heart to embrace the joyful tidings,
				   and entirely to adhere to, and acquiesce in the revelation of Christ as
				   our Saviour: it causes the whole soul to accord and symphonize with it,
				   admitting it with entire credit and respect cleaving to it with full
				   inclination and affection; and it effectually disposes the soul to give
				   up itself entirely to Christ.
				</p><p>
				   4. This light, and this only, has its fruit in a universal holiness of
				   life. No merely notional or speculative understanding of the doctrines
				   of religion will ever bring to this. But this light, as it reaches the
				   bottom of the heart, and changes the nature, so it will effectually
				   dispose to a universal obedience. It shows God's worthiness to be
				   obeyed and served. It draws forth the heart in a sincere love to God,
				   which is the only principle of a true, gracious, and universal
				   obedience; and it convinces of the reality of those glorious rewards
				   that God has promised to them that obey him.
				</p>
			</div>
		</div>
	</osisText>
</osis>